Before I start with today's lecture,
I want to point out that there is a
recent development in the playground
that fixes an issue that many of
you have been complaining about.
Namely that sometimes the
timeout that was hard-coded into
the playground was too short.
So sometimes your simulations failed
because the simulation just took more
time than this timeout specified.
And it was very difficult to change
the timeout because it was hard-coded.
So you would have to change the
source code and then recompile it.
And now there's an option when you start
the Plutus playground server and -i and
then you can specify something like 120
seconds to set the timeout to two minutes.
When I explained the extended UTxO model
in the first lecture, I explained it in
order to unlock a script address, the
script attached to the address is run.
And that script gets three
pieces of input, the datum,
the redeemer and the context.
And in the second lecture, we saw
examples of that and we saw how
that actually works in Haskell.
We saw the low level implementation where
all three arguments, datum, redeemer, and
context are represented by the data type.
But I also mentioned that in practice
that is not used and we use instead
the typed version, where datum and
redeemer can be customed types, as
long as they implement the is data type
class and where the third argument,
the context is of type script context.
And the example we have seen so far only
looked at the datum and the redeemer,
but we have always ignored the context.
But the context is of
course very important.
So in this lecture, we want to start
looking at the context and this script
context type it's defined in package
plutus-ledger-api which is a package
that until now we haven't needed,
but now we do need it and I also
included it in this week's cabal file.
And the context is in module
Plutus.V1.Ledger.Contexts and
we see the definition here,
so the type script context.
And we see it as a record type with
two fields, one of type Tx info,
which is the most interesting one.
And then the second field of type script
purpose and the script purpose type
is defined in the same module here.
And it describes for which
purpose the script is run.
So the most important purpose for us
will be this one, the spending purpose.
So this is what we have talked
about until now in the context
of the extended UTxO model.
So this is when a script is run
in order to validate spending
input for a transaction, but
there are three other purposes.
The second most important
one is the minting one.
So that comes into play when you want
to define a native token and then this
purpose of this script would be to
describe under which circumstances the
native token can be minted or burned.
And then there are two more
purposes, rewarding and certifying.
So rewarding seems to be related to
staking and certifying to certificates
like delegation certificates.
But first we will concentrate
on the spending purpose.
So now the actual context is in
this field of type Tx info, which is
defined also in the same module here.
And this basically describes, I mean, it's
an abbreviation for a transaction info,
so it describes the spending transaction.
I always say that in the UTxO model
that Cardano uses, the context of
validation is the spending transaction.
So the transaction and
its inputs and outputs.
And that is expressed
in this Tx info type.
So there are a couple of fields that
are basically global to the transaction.
And then in particular, we have
the list of all the inputs of the
transaction and the list of all
the outputs of the transaction.
And these Tx in info and Tx out
types, again have lots of fields
to allow you to drill into each
individual input respectively output.
So let's go through the Tx info fields
briefly, so Tx info inputs the inputs,
Tx info outputs the outputs, Tx info
fee is the fee, the transaction fee, Tx
info forge is the amount of newly forged
native tokens or if it's a negative
amount, newly burned native tokens.
So we'll come to that in a later lecture,
then we have a list of certificates,
something like delegation certificates.
Then staking withdrawals,
so withdrawals from rewards.
Then Tx info valid range denotes
the time range in which this
transaction will be valid.
And we'll talk about that in
much more detail in a minute.
Then the Tx info signatories,
that's the list of public keys
that have signed this transaction.
Tx info data, I mentioned before
that spending transactions, I mean,
transactions that spend a script
output need to include the datum of
that script output whereas producing
transactions that send money to a script
address have an output at the script
address, only have to include the hash.
So this field Tx info data is
basically a dictionary from datum hash
to data to include the fully datum
values belonging to a given hash.
There's also mentioned before,
spending transactions always have to
include the datum of the inputs they
spent, but producing transactions
optionally can also do that.
And finally, Tx info id is
the id of this transition.
This brings us to an interesting dilemma.
I have stressed several times that
one of the big advantages that the
Cardano UTxO model has over something
like Ethereum is the fact that
validation can help them in the wallet.
So as I explained before, transactions
can still fail because a transaction
can consume an input that when the
transaction arrives on the blockchain
at the node for validation has already
been consumed by somebody else.
But in that case, the transaction simply
fails without having to pay fees, but
what can never happen or should never
happen under normal circumstances
is that a validation script runs and
then fails because you can always
run the script under exactly the same
conditions in the wallet already.
So you see that it would fail
before you ever submit it.
And that is a very important
and a very nice feature.
But if you think about it, it's not
clear how to manage time in that
context, because time is obviously
important because we want to be able to
express validation logic that says that
a certain transaction is only valid.
After a certain time has been reached
or before certain time has been reached.
You saw an example of that in the
very first example, the auction
example, where bids are only allowed
until the deadline has been reached
and the close endpoint can only be
called after the deadline has passed.
And if you think about that,
that seems to be a contradiction
because time is obviously flowing.
So when you try to validate a transaction
that you're constructing in your
wallet, the time that you do that in
the wallet can of course be different
to the time that the transaction
arrives at a node for validation.
So it's not clear how to bring these two
together to on the one hand handle time.
But on the other hand guarantee that
validation is deterministic in the sense
that if it even only if it succeeds in the
wallet, it will also succeed in the node.
And the way Cardano solves that is by
adding this POSIX time range field.
Tx info valid range field to a transaction
and what that specifies, so it's...
we you will look at that type in detail in
a moment, but basically it gives a valid
time interval, it is a time interval.
So it says this transaction is
valid between this and that time.
And that is specified in the transaction,
and now when the transaction gets sent
to the blockchain, submitted to the
blockchain and validated by a node
then before any scripts are run some
general checks are done for example,
that all the inputs are present and
that the balances at up and so on that
the fees are included and run of those
checks that happens before validation
is that the time range has changed.
So when a node is validating, one of
these pre-checks before validation
is the node checks the current
time and compares it to the time
range specified in the transaction.
And if the current time does not
fall into this time range, then
validation fails immediately without
ever running the validator scripts.
But that also means that if these
pre-checks succeed, then we can
assume that the current time
does fall into this interval.
And then validation is
completely deterministic again.
This is just a static piece of
data attached to the transaction.
So the result of validation does not
depend on when it is run, whether
it's run in the wallet before
submission or in one of the nodes
when validating a transaction.
And this makes it possible to resolve
this apparent contradiction between
having deterministic validation
on the one hand and taking time
into account on the other hand.
So the trick is to do the time check
before validation is run, and then
during the execution of the validator
scripts, we don't have to worry about
it anymore and if we can just assume
that the current time falls into this
interval, because if it wouldn't then
validation wouldn't even run in the first
place, because then validation of the
transaction would have failed before.
By default all transactions use the
infinite time range that starts at the
beginning of time or at the Genesis
block and lasts for all eternity.
So such transactions will always be
valid no matter at what time they
arrive at a node for validation.
The only exceptions we have seen so far
were those in the auction example, because
the bid and the close couldn't use the
infinite interval, because we made sure
that the bid happens before the deadline
and the close after the deadline, but by
default all transactions, including those
that you send from Daudalus for example,
always use the infinite time range.
There's one slight complication with this.
And that is that or bores itself the
consensus protocol powering Cardano
doesn't use POSIX time, time...
it uses slots.
So it counts slots and each slot
there's lottery happens where a slot
there's determined, and it's got to
be, that can produce a block and so on.
So a slot is the native measure of
time when Cardano, but Plutus uses.
So some of this has to be converted.
So we need to be able to convert back
and forth between real time and slots.
And this is no problem as long
as the slot length is fixed,
right now it is one second.
So right now it's easy to go back
and forth between real time and slot
numbers, but this could change in future.
So there could be a hard fork,
some parameter change that
will change the slot time.
And of course, we can't know that
in advance, that may be a decision
that is made years in the future.
So we don't know right now what the slot
length will be in 10 years, for example.
And that means that slot intervals specify
the transactions mustn't have a definite
upper bound that is to find the future.
It must only be...
as fine the future as it is possible
to know what the slot length will be.
And that happens to be
something like 36 hours.
We know what the slot length will be in
the next 36 hours, because if there's
a hard fork, if there's a change in
protocol parameters, then we know
that at least 36 hours in advance.
So that is something to keep in mind,
you can't specify arbitrary time ranges
there, in the transaction interval.
It must only be at most 36 hours in
the future, or it can be indefinite,
so for all eternity, that's also fine.
But if it's a fixed time, like the
deadline in our auction example when
we submit a transaction, the deadline
basically mustn't be farther than 36
hours in the future, then we submit
that, or the deadline could be, but
then we must specify the deadline
is upper bound, but some other time
that lives before the deadline that
is at most 36 hours in the future.
So that's a slight complication
that arises from the fact that
Plutus uses a different concept
of time then all boards itself.
Of course, it's more convenient to use
real time, especially for real world
contracts where you may want to specify
deadlines in real time dates, for example.
But in order to translate back and forth
between time and slots, you have to be a
bit careful when you submit a transaction,
when you construct transactions and set
the slot interval or the time range.
So let's look at this
POSIX time range type.
And we see it's defined in module
Plutus.V1.Ledger.Time and it's just a
type synonym for interval POSIX time,
so let's look at the interval type.
We see interval type, the one type
parameter, and we see it's specified
by a lower bound and upper bound.
We can drill into those types as well.
So in lower bound has one
construct, a lower bond, and
then extended a and closure.
Let's first look at closure, that's
just another name for bool and it
specifies whether that boundary is
included in the interval or not.
And let's look at this extended,
so this extended can just be an A,
defined constructor, or it can be
negative infinity or positive infinity.
Now, if we scroll down here, we see there
are a couple of convenience functions.
So member for example, allows
us to check whether a given
A is included in interval A.
Provided A is the ord constraint
is an instance of the ord class,
which means that you can compare
two As whether one is less than or
greater than or equal to the other.
So POSIX time, for example, is
an instance of ord as our slots.
Interval is a smart constructor
for intervals that just  gives us
an interval with these two As as
lower and upper bound included.
Then we have from and to, to
construct an interval that starts
at A and last until eternity.
And to, the opposite an interval
that stops at A, then always is the
interval that is used by default,
that includes all times, never is
the empty interval, singleton is an
interval that only contains this one A.
Hull is the smallest interval that
contains the two given intervals.
Intersection as the name suggests
intersects two intervals, the
result will again be an interval.
Overlaps checks whether two
intervals have an element in common.
Contains checks whether one interval
is contained in the other, so we
must just check which will round,
so I think the second one must
be included in the first one.
Is empty checks whether
an interval is empty.
Before checks whether the given time
is before everything in this interval.
After the opposite, whether the given
time is after everything in this interval.
These are just convenience functions to
construct strict lower and upper bounds.
We can play with intervals a
bit, so let's start a repl.
And let's import Plutus
V1 ledger interval.
Now, for example, we can use this
interval smart constructor and
as A let's just use integers for
simplicity, so for example, the
interval between 10 and 20, let me see.
Okay, it says the lower bound is
finite 10, 10 is included, the upper
bound is finite 20, 20 is included.
So for example, we can now check
with member whether nine is a
member of this interval, it's not.
But 10 should be.
It is.
So it should be 12 and
20, but 21 shouldn't.
Or let's use the from, so we have from 30,
21 is not included in that, 30 should be.
And now everything larger
than 30 should also be.
Right, and to, let's try the to.
So 31 still shouldn't be included.
30 should be, and everything
lower than 30 as well.
Okay, so that seems to work.
Let's try one more thing, maybe the
intersection, so let's intersect this
one from 10 to 20 with the one from,
I don't know, 18 to 30 and as expected
we get the interval from 18 to 20.
Let's also try the
contains and the overlap.
So for example, contains
to 100 interval 30 80.
True.
So what does that mean?
That means the interval that starts at
30 and ends at 80 is contained, fully
contained in the interval that starts at
the beginning of time and goes to 100.
If you now change this 80 to 100
should still be true, but if you
change it to 101, it's no longer true.
But if we check overlaps, then it is
true because for example, 40 is contained
in this interval and also in that one.
So overlaps is true, but contains is false
because the second interval is not fully
contained in the first one, the 101 is in
the second one, but not in the first one.
If we, however, use
something like 101 to 110.
Then it's false, then it
don't overlap any longer.
So now let's look at an example
for using this time range.
One of my colleagues at
input output bought some ADA
for his nephews and nieces.
And of course, I don't know any details
about that, but just imagine you want
to make a gift of ADA to a child.
So you want the child to own the
ADA, but you only want the child
to have access to the ADA when he,
or she turns 18 or 21 or whatever.
And using Plutus, this is a very
easy to implement a scheme like
that, a vesting scheme like that.
So I copied the is data contract and Into
a new module that are called vesting.
And as our first example of validator
that actually uses the context.
I want to try to implement
this vesting idea.
So you put money into a script
and only the dedicated person
can retrieve it, but only once a
certain deadline has been reached.
So the first step is to think about
the types of datum and redeemer.
And the datum, I think in this
case, it makes sense to have exactly
these two pieces of information,
the beneficiary and the deadline.
So let's define this type,
let's call it vesting datum.
Let's make it a record type with those
two fields, beneficiary of type, well...
How do we identify the beneficiary
by his or her public key or to
be more precise, public key hash.
And then we need the deadline
that will be of type POSIX time.
We can derive a show instance, might
be useful for debugging, we don't
need the my silly redeemer anymore.
But we do need an is data
instance of our vesting datum.
Right, so the first argument is the datum.
So that's now of type vesting datum.
So for redeemer, do we need any
information in the redeemer?
What do we need in order to check
whether a transaction is allowed
to spent this script output.
We need to know that it has been signed
by the beneficiary and we must know that
it's only submitted after the deadline,
but those two pieces of information are
both contained in the transaction itself.
So we don't need anything in
addition to that in the redeemer.
So we can just use unit for the redeemer.
So first argument now we need it.
so, let's call it dat for datum.
So the redeemer is just unit, and now
we can't any longer ignore the context.
So let's give it a name, right?
So now we need to check two conditions.
That the transaction is signed
by the beneficiary and that, it
has been submitted or that the
current time is after the deadline.
So let's delegate the helper functions,
let's just write the general structure.
So let's say beneficiary's
signature missing.
So this is the error message we get
in case it's false and let's call it
something like signed by beneficiary.
And so we need the second condition
that the deadline has been reached.
So dead line not reached, let's
call that, deadline reached.
Okay.
Now, of course these two signed
by beneficiary and deadline
reached be must defined.
And for both, we will need this Tx info.
So let's first define
that, of type Tx info.
And that, I am here in the repl and
I imported ledger and asked for the
information on the script context again.
So in order to get the Tx info from
the script in context, we must use
this field name script context Tx info.
So that script context TX info
of our context, now we can
define the two conditions.
Let's first do the signed
by beneficiary of type bool.
Okay.
How do we check that?
Well, if we check in the repl again
there's a function called Tx signed by
the takes a Tx info, which we now have
and the pub key hash, and then says
whether that transaction that had Tx info
has been signed by this public key hash.
So we can use that.
Tx signed by info, which I just
defined and now we need the public key
hash of the beneficiary and that we
have, because we have the datum, dat.
And this is of type vesting datum
and we have the beneficiary there,
so I can do beneficiary of that.
So that's our first condition.
And the second condition, deadline
reached, was of type bool.
So how do we check that?
So if we look at this crew diagram,
so this is time, and let's say
the deadline is here and let's
consider a transaction with, let's
first say this validity interval.
So recall what that means before
the validator script is run.
Other checks are made
including the time check.
So the node checks whether the
current time falls into the valid
range of the transaction and
only then it's the validator run.
So we know now that we are in the
validator, the current time lives
somewhere in the validity interval.
But if this here, the first one
would be the validity interval,
then the current time could be for
example, here, which would be fine.
It would be after the deadline,
but it could also be here,
which would not be fine.
It would be before the deadline.
So this validity interval
is no good for us.
We mustn't declare the
transaction to be valid.
If this is the validity interval.
This one, the other hand is fine, we
still don't know where the current
time exactly is, it can be anywhere
in this interval, but no matter
where it is, it's after the deadline.
So we must check that we have this
situation that the whole interval
is to the right of the deadline.
And one way to do is to use this contains
function that you played with earlier.
And look at this interval, the half
open interval that starts at the
deadline and stretches into infinity.
And if this interval contains
the validity interval of the
transaction, then we are good.
Then we know no matter where the current
time is, it will be after the deadline.
So we can use contains.
Now the interval starting at
the deadline is from, and the
deadline we can get from the datum.
And now we need the validity interval
of the transaction and that if we look
here at the information of the Tx info,
then this was called Tx info valid range
of the info, and that should be it.
Next let's look at this dummy typed
that wraps up datum and redeemer type.
Typed is not a good name.
Let's call it vesting and the
datum type is now our vesting
datum type and the of our vesting.
And the redeemer type it's just unit.
Okay, this is just boiler plate.
We must just put the right types here.
So vesting, datum and
unit, that should be fine.
Now, of course we also have to
change the off-chain part, but as
before, because the focus of this
lecture is on-chain validation.
I already prepared that and
we just briefly go through it.
And I should also mention that at the top
of the module, I added some additional
GHC extensions, like derive any class and
derive generic and also added some imports
like to json, from json generic and so on.
So let's briefly look
at the off-chain part.
So, this type here, vesting
schema defines the endpoints that
we want to expose to the user.
And as before in our silly example
from last week call the give and grab.
So give is for the person that wants to
set up this vesting contract and then
grab for the beneficiary to collect.
So what parameters do we need?
For give, I mean, what this endpoint
will do is it will create a UTxO
at the vesting address with the
specified amount and the correct datum.
And if you recall our vesting datum
contains the beneficiary and the deadline.
So this give endpoint must
in particular know those, the
beneficiary and the deadline.
So this is here and we also of course,
have to specify how much money we
want to put at this UTxO, therefore
I need a third field, the amount.
The grab endpoint on the other hand,
doesn't need any parameters because the
beneficiary will just look for UTxOs
sitting at the vesting address and then
can check whether he is the beneficiary.
And whether the deadline has
already passed and can then pick
those UTxOs and consume them.
And we know from the way that we've
wrote the validator, that will
then succeed and no additional
information has to be supplied.
Let's briefly look at the
endpoints, first at give.
So it takes the give parameters and
first I compute the datum I want to use.
So recall I need the beneficiary and
the deadline, then I can get those
simply from reading it from the give
parameters now for the transaction.
I need as constraint that I want
to create a transaction that has
an output at this script address.
That's why I use this must pay to the
script with the data, my justified,
and then I must provide the value.
So I take the value, the amount
from the give parameters, and then
use this function here to convert
that to a value in lovelace.
The rest is as before I just
changed the log message.
So I mention the amount, the
beneficiary and the deadline.
Now for the grab, that's a bit
more involved because there can be
many UTxOs at this vesting address.
And some of them might not be
suitable for me, either because I
am not the beneficiary or because
the deadline has not yet passed.
So I grab the current time, I lookup
my own public key and computes hash,
and then I look at all UTxOs sitting
at the script address, but I filter
those and the filter is defined here.
So I get such a UTxO and then I
first check the datum hash whether.
So I first check the datum hash and
if I find it it's this H, then I try
to lookup the corresponding datum
and recall what I said several times
before, the producing transaction.
So in our case, the one that has been
produced by the give endpoint, doesn't
necessarily have to contain the datum.
It can all only contain the datum
hash, but if that was the case, then
I would have a problem here in grab, I
wouldn't be able to find the datum that
corresponds to the UTxO that I find.
But by using this must pay to the script
constraint, I make use of the option to
include the datum into the transaction.
So this transaction will actually
optionally contain the datum.
So it will contain the datum and
that's why I should be able to
find it here, look at up here.
So I have this datum and
then I must deserialize it.
So this is of the data type, but
I want the vesting datum type.
So that's the last step.
So if all of this succeeds, then I
can check whether the beneficiary of
the datum is myself and whether the
deadline doesn't lie in the future.
So at this point the UTxOs are only
UTxOs sitting at this vesting address
where I am the beneficiary and
where the deadline has been reached.
And if I find no such UTxOs I
just log a message that nothing is
available and don't do anything else.
And if there's at least one, then I
construct one transaction that consumes
all of them as inputs and paste the
money in there, to my own wallet.
So, I have to as look-ups provide
these UTxOs, and I also have to
provide the validator script.
Recall, if a transaction wants to spend
a UTxO sitting at the script address.
The script must be provided
by this spending transaction.
So this lookup here takes care of that.
And this here I basically just
go over the list of all UTxOs and
say "I want to spend that one".
And as I said, by default, the time
range of a transaction will be this
always, the time range it start
and Genesis and goes on forever.
So if I don't do anything,
I would use that.
And that wouldn't be good because
then validation would fail
because recall validation checks
that the deadline has passed.
And It only knows that the current
time lives in this validity interval.
So if the validity interval is
from the beginning of time, to the
end of time, I have no information
and then I wouldn't be able to be
sure that the deadline has passed.
So I must provide the different
validity interval that I can do with
this must validate in constraint.
And here I picked from now, it's just
important that everything interval that
I provide here is after the deadline.
But so I could, for example, just
use the Singleton interval now, but
then I would have a problem if the
transaction doesn't get there in the
same slot to the node for validation.
So if it only reaches their slot later,
then the current time at that point
would already not be in this interval
anymore, which only contains now.
So the best is to make
it as large as possible.
So I started now, but then get it last
into eternity and the rest is same as
before, and then I just bundled them
up in this endpoints contract and
some boiler plate for the playground.
Let's try it in the playground.
So we see that the playground
has changed earlier.
Last week, we saw that the default
amount was 10 lovelace, which is too low.
Because fees are now included and the
fees are normally higher than 10 lovelace.
So this default was no longer adequate.
So now it's, what is it?
100 ADA is the default value.
So let's add a third wallet and
I want wallet one to make gifts
to wallet two and wallet three.
Okay.
So wallet one starts, makes a gift and
normally it will be possible to submit all
three give transactions in the same slot.
So I wouldn't need a wait action,
but the way I implemented it, the
give endpoint after submitting the
transaction, I wait for confirmation.
Maybe I shouldn't have done
that, but it is what it is.
And that means we, before this
give endpoint returns, the
transaction must be confirmed.
So we do have to wait.
So let's wait one block.
And the second give,
let's wait another block.
In the third give.
Oh, okay.
So the idea is wallet one makes two
gives to wallet two with different
deadlines and one give to wallet three.
So now we have our first problem.
What is the public key hash of
wallet two and of wallet three?
There is a way to find out what it is.
So let's switch to the repl.
Let's load our module, let's import
ledger and let's import Wallet.Emulator.
Now, first of all, we have a wallet
type and we see wallet it's just
a newtype wrap around integer.
Secondly, we have something
called wallet pub key, given
a wallet gives us a pub key.
And finally, we have pub key hash, given
a pub key gives us the pub key hash.
So, putting all of these together,
we can do pub key hash of
wallet pub key of wallet two.
And there we have the
hash and wallet three.
So let's grab the pub key hash
of wallet two and let's put
it in the first two gives.
Let's grab the pub key
hash of wallet three.
And put it in the third give.
Next problem is the deadline.
In last lecture, I showed you
how to convert between slots
and deadlines or POSIX times.
But unfortunately, this has
changed in the meantime.
So back then you just needed a
slot and out came a POSIX time.
Now there's a second argument.
If you go back to the repl and import
ledger time slot, then there's a
function slot to begin, begin POSIX time.
And this now takes a slot config and the
slot to give us a POSIX time, by the way,
there are versions with begin and end.
This is because a slot has,
it's not just a point in time.
It's, it's a duration in time.
So it has a beginning and an
end, so these two are for that,
so what's this lot config?
That contains the slot length
and the zero slot time.
So that POSIX time at
which sc zero starts.
So now we have to find out what slot
config to use for the playground.
Luckily it's the default slot config.
So what's the default slot config?
For that we need to import yet
another module, Data.Default.
And that defines a class called
default, lots of instances.
And we see a def method of type A.
So if a type A implement, is an
instance of class default, then by
using def we get an A, so the idea is
that, that is then the default value.
And if you check slot config again, then
now that we imported Data.Default, we
see it is indeed an instance of default.
So by using def and telling the
compiler what type we're interested
in, we get the default slot config.
So we see slot length is 1000.
So that means POSIX time is
obviously in milliseconds.
So the 1000 is one second and we see
when in the playground slot zero starts.
So now we can use the slot to begin POSIX
time and can use def as our slot config.
And now we can, for example, see what
POSIX time slot 10 begins and slot 20.
So let's take the POSIX time for slot 10.
Let's say the first give to wallet
two has a deadline of 10 and the give
to wallet three has a deadline of 10.
And to take the POSIX time for
20 and say the second give to
wallet two has deadline 20.
Now let's add the amount,
let's say 10 ADA each.
Okay.
And now let's first check the scenario
where everything works perfectly.
So let's say wallet three grabs at
slot 10 when the deadline for wallet
three has passed, don't need any
parameters or arguments for grab.
And let's say that...
Oh, it's wait until not wait for
and here as well wait until slot 20.
And now wallet two grabs.
So both give to wallet two at
that point should be available.
And finally, we'll wait one more block
for giving it a chance to process and
end up on the blockchain and evaluate.
Okay, let's look at the transactions.
So as always slot zero first one
is the Genesis transaction that
distributes the initial funds.
So wallet 2, 1, 3, all get a hundred ADA.
Slot one is the gift from wallet
one to wallet two with deadline 10.
So we see almost 90 ADA changed
go back to wallet one and 10 are
locked by the script address.
So the second one is the give
to wallet two with deadline 20.
So now the change is 80, so wallet
one has 80 left, another 10 go
into a different UTxO in the
script, at that script address.
Finally, the third gift.
Now wallet one ends up with
70 and another 10 go into a
third UTxO at the same address.
Now in slot 10, this is now where
three grabs and that succeeds.
So the third UTxO is the input, is spent.
Some fees are paid and wallet
three ends up with roughly 10 ADA.
Finally slot 20, wallet two picks up
the two UTxOs that were for wallet two,
both deadlines have passed at 10 and 20.
Some fees paid roughly twice
because now two validators have
to run for each script input.
And wallet two ends up
with roughly 20 ADA.
And the final balances should
reflect that, that wallet one has
70 left, wallet two has roughly
1.20, wallet one has roughly 1.10,
so that all works as expected.
Let's try what happens if
wallet two doesn't grab at
slot 20, but only at slot 15.
Okay.
So the first transaction should be the
same and now the transaction slot 15, only
one input because the second UTxO, the
one with deadline 20 is not yet available.
So only one input and wallet
two only ends up with 10.
And we see that still 10 are still
locked at the script address.
So those can only be claimed
by wallet two after slot 20.
There's one thing I should point out
that I've wrote the off-chain code, the
wallet code in a way that only submits
a transaction, if it can actually
grab the UTxO, if you recall, I filled
out the UTxO to check that, I am the
beneficiary and the deadline has passed.
Which means that we don't really exercise
the validator because we only send
transactions to the blockchain that then
get validated, that will pass validation.
That's how we wrote the wallet code.
So if you want to actually
test the validator, you would
have to modify the wallet code.
If you like, you can do
that as an option homework.
So remove these checks in the wallet
and just try to grab everything, and
then it should fail if you are not
the beneficiary or if the deadline
has not yet been reached and then
it should fail you in validation,
not already just in the wallet, not
even submitting the transaction.
So you always have to be
careful or keep that in mind.
Everybody of course can
write off-chain code.
So, even though now it works as long as
you use the grab endpoint that I provided.
I mean, I wrote it in a way that you
never try to claim something that's
not for you, but of course, somebody
else could write different piece of
off-chain code that doesn't try that.
And then if your validator is not
correct, if it for example, forgets to
check the beneficiary or the deadline,
then something could go horribly wrong.
So we must keep that in mind that only
because it works for the endpoints
you have provided doesn't mean that
somebody else couldn't come up with
other endpoints where it doesn't work.
Okay.
So this is the vesting example where
we made use of the context for the
first time and where we made use
of this valid time interval in the
transaction to implement a deadline.
I copied the code of the vesting module
into a new model called parameterized.
And I want to talk about
parameterized contracts next.
So note that in this example, we used
this vesting datum type as datum, but
the datum was just fixed, that was
just sitting there, it didn't change.
And alternatively, we could bake
it into the contract, so to speak.
So we can write a contract where the
script itself already contains this
information, beneficiary and deadline.
So all the examples of contracts we have
seen so far, they were always fixed.
So we had this type validator,
and that was just of type typed
validator, so it's a constant, a
compile time constant actually.
So the idea of parameterized scripts
is that you can have a parameter.
So depending on the value of
the parameter, you get different
values of typed validator.
So instead of just defining one
script, you, so to say, define
a family of scripts that are
parameterized by a given parameter.
So I want to demonstrate how we can
do this here by instead of using datum
for these two pieces of information,
using a parameter so that the contract
will be parameterized by this.
So in order to do that, vesting
datum is no longer appropriate name.
So let's call it vesting param instead,
and then we don't need the datum is data
instance anymore, so let's remove that.
Now this has to change, this now
gets an additional parameter,
namely the parameter of the script.
So vesting datum, and now comes the
datum and because all the information
we needed until now in the datum is
now contained in this param here.
We can simply use the unit type as datum.
So this is now one parameter more,
the parameter of this script.
So, by picking a specific value
of this parameter, I get what
I had before, of type signature
datum, redeemer context to bool.
And the code of course has to
change a little bit, but not much.
So let's call the parameter argument P
and instead of dat, we now just have unit.
And now all I have to do is I have
to exchange all the dats for Ps.
So here P and here.
Okay.
So small change, now these vesting
type also has to change because
now the datum type is no longer a
vesting datum, it's simply unit.
Now we have to think what to do here.
So this is now no longer, just a
constant, this typed validator, it now
takes the parameter, so vesting param.
So let's put that here.
And now the question is
what to do with this.
So the function make typed validator
expects as its first argument, the
compiled code of something of type
datum to redeemer, to context to bool.
But now this make validator doesn't
have this type anymore because
it has this extra parameter P
so this wouldn't work like that.
What we would like to do.
Oh, and before I forget, I must
change this to unit as well.
So what we would like
to do is put a P here.
Now that the type would be correct
or it looks like that because
P is this vesting param type.
So if we apply, make validator to P
we apply the first argument here, and
what we are left with is something of
type unit to unit to script context
to bool which is a suitable type for
this make type validator function.
Let's leave it like this for the moment,
and let's just change the rest because now
all these things are no longer constance,
validator now also takes a parameter.
And instead of doing this, we have
to compose it with typed validator.
So actually, I mean, to write that
like more explicitly, we would
have this P here and then it would
have to apply the P first to type
validator to get a typed validator.
And then we can apply validator script,
but in Haskell in simpler cases like
that, we like to do a pointfree, so we
use function composition instead,, same
for validator hash that now also takes
the vesting param type and same thing.
Let's replace it with function
composition and script address as well.
It's now also parameterized
by this parameter.
However, if we go to the repl, then
we get a compiler error and it says
"reference to a name which is not a
local, a builtin, or an external inlinable
function: variable P no unfolding".
And the problem is this.
And as I explained, when I explained the
template Haskell and these Oxford brackets
and the use of this inlinable Pragma,
I said that everything in the Oxford
brackets must be known at compile time.
It must be explicitly known.
So normally it would even have
to be explicitly included,
written inside these brackets.
But by using this inlinable Pragma,
we can also have it in external
functions, like our make validator.
But it must still be known as
at compile time because that's
how template Haskell works.
If it is run it's executed before the main
compiler, the Haskell compiler is run.
So at compiler time, template Haskell in
order to do this, to compile to Plutus
core must know what is inside these
brackets, but the P of course is not
known at compile time because we intend
to at run time, provide some arbitrary
value of type vesting param and then
apply this function type validator to it.
So the P will only be known at run time.
And therefore this can't possibly work,
even though the types look correct.
Luckily there's a way around
that, so what's the situation?
On the Haskell side, we have our
make validator function and we
have the P of type vesting param.
And we could apply the one to
the other like this and that
would have the right type.
Now in the Plutus core side, we
can compile this because make
validator is known at compile time.
And I don't know how to write this
let's for example, put it into angular
brackets to indicate that this is the
compiled to Plutus core version of
the Haskell function make validator.
And I want this, I want make validator
P compiled, but I can't apply compile
here because the P is not known at
compile time, so template Haskell
won't work for P so I can't do that.
So now the idea is, in Plutus
this angular brackets make
validator is also a function.
It's not a Haskell function anymore,
it's a Plutus core function,
but the function nevertheless,
that you can apply to arguments.
So if I could get my hands on the
compile version of P, then what
I could do, I can't do this here
directly, but then I can simply
apply the make validator compiled.
And actually that is called
apply code in Plutus to P,
that would then be what I want.
That would be the same as this, but
this looks as if it doesn't solve
anything because we still need a
compiled version of P and we have the
same problem that P is not known at
compile time, but only at run time.
However, P is not some arbitrary
Haskell code, it's data, so it
doesn't contain any function types.
And as we would see for such types,
there is a way if we make the type
of P in instance of a type class
called lift, that's called lift
code, that does work at runtime.
So using lift code, we can compile P
at run time to Plutus core, and then
using apply code, we can apply this
function, this Plutus core function
to this Plutus core value to get this.
Which is exactly what we want.
Let's briefly look at the lift class.
It has one method lift, but we won't
use that method directly as I mentioned
before, we will use something called
lift code, but lift code is available for
types A that implement this lift class.
And we see these...
A bunch of instances for it.
We can ignore this uni type parameter
here, but we see it's all for data,
it's characters, byte strings,
integers, booleans, unit, data, I
don't actually know what sqrt does...
lists of things that have an
instance, maybe ratio and so on.
Either pairs, maps, triples,
quadruplets, quintuples but no functions.
And that's the reason why we
can't use lift code all the time.
Not for compiling Haskell validators
to Plutus core validators, but we
can use it for these data, like types
that are similar to the data type
that we use to express our datum and
redeemers and the script context.
So for those sort of types that are
data like, and not function like
instances for the lift class are
available and then we can use lift code.
So let's have a brief look at lift code.
We can ignore these, the second
and the third precondition here.
So if you have lift of A, then we have
a function from A to compile code of A.
And that's exactly what we need.
So if we go back to the code,
we can't do this, as I said.
But we can use Plutus Tx apply
code and now lift code P.
However, this won't compile, or
it's probably Plutus Tx lift code.
However, this won't compile because
now the compiler complaints that we
don't have a lift instance for vesting
param, but there something similar
as true as what I said about is data,
there is a template Haskell mechanism
to automatically get such an instance.
So we can do Plutus Tx make
lift and vesting param.
Now we get another error, illegal instance
declaration, use multi param type classes.
It is because we saw this lift class
had additional type parameters.
So in standard Haskell 98, you can
only have one type parameter for
a class, but lift uses more and
that is enabled by this extension.
So we have to add this to our extensions.
Try again, it compiles.
Now let's briefly look at the
off-chain code, which hasn't
changed much, but somewhat.
So the give parameters are still the same.
I must know the beneficiary,
the deadline and the amount.
The schema has slightly changed, the
one for give is still the same, but for
grab, we now need to know the deadline.
Because in order to find the UTxOs of
gifts that are locked at the script.
Now, because the script address
depends on these parameters, the
beneficiary and the deadline.
We need those in order to find the UTxOs.
We know the beneficiary, that will be
the pub key hash of the wallet that calls
grab, but we can't know the deadline.
So I made that parameter here.
So the give endpoint is very similar, but
instead of computing the datum, we just
define something of type vesting param
and then this must pay to the script,
now the datum is just unit, and here
when we submit the transaction, now we...
typed validator is no longer constant,
so we provide this parameter P that
we define, the rest is the same.
Grab is now different, recall,
earlier we got all the UTxOs
sitting at this one script address.
And that could be for arbitrary
beneficiaries and for arbitrary deadlines.
So we had to filter those UTxOs
that were for us and where
the deadline had been reached.
Now, the situation is different.
So we, again, check what is now
and we check our own public key.
And now we do know the deadline in advance
because it's a parameter to this grab.
So we can immediately see whether
the deadline has been reached or not.
So if it has not yet been
reached, we simply log a message
that it's too early and stop.
If it has been reached, we can
compute the vesting params.
We have the beneficiary and the deadline,
and we lookup the UTxOs at this address.
Now address again is not a constant
anymore, but takes this parameter.
So now we will only get UTxOs that
are for us and for this deadline
D and we know that all of them
are available, so we don't have to
filter anything because we already
checked that the deadline has passed.
So, all we do is, we check whether
there are none and if they are
none, we don't even bother and
just say no gifts available.
And if there is, then we do
more or less what we did before.
So we defined the lookups that
define these UTxOs and the script.
And the constraint is that we want to
spend all those UTxOS that we found.
And that it must validate in
the right validity interval.
And we submit as before, wait for
confirmation and log a message.
The endpoint is only slightly
different now here in grab,
because we have this one parameter.
Let's test this in the playground.
I copied the code into the editor
and compiled, and I already added
the third wallet and did exactly
the same give actions as before.
So wallet one gives 10 ADA each, twice
to wallet two, once to wallet three.
And for wallet two the deadlines
are slot 10 and slot 20 and
for wallet three it's slot 20.
Now the grab is slightly different
because in our earlier implementation,
one beneficiary, one wallet could
grab different deadlines provided
that had passed, but now the deadline
is part of the script parameter.
So it's also part of the
parameter for the endpoint, so
we have to specify the deadline.
So, wallet two can't grab the gift
for slot 10 and 20 at the same
time, the way I implemented it.
So let's see.
So first we can wait until slot 10 and
then wallet two should be able to grab the
first gift and wallet three the only gift.
So let's add a grab for wallet two and
three, and we don't have to wait in
between because it's to different wallets.
So if the one blocks until it's confirmed,
the other ones should still work.
So now we need one parameter, namely the
deadline, which in this case is slot 10.
So that's this value here.
Okay.
Now let's wait for slot 20.
Well, now wallet two can grab, second
time, as parameter we need slot 20.
That should be this one.
We need to wait for one more
block and check whether works.
It seems to have worked.
So let's go through the transactions
quickly again, Genesis in the beginning.
Now this is the first gift
from wallet one to wallet two.
And take note of the script
address, it starts with a58.
Now the second transaction is
from wallet one to wallet two
with the slot 20 deadline.
And this script address is now different,
so earlier in our first version,
the script address was a constant.
So all our gift ended up at the same
script address and only the datum in those
three UTxO was different, with different
beneficiary and different deadline.
Now the datum is just unit and the
beneficiary and the deadline are
included as part of this script itself,
so the addresses are different now,
depending on beneficiary and deadline.
So this is the second gift to wallet
two, this is the gift to wallet
three, again, a different address.
Now in slot 10, we see concurrently
both wallet two and three grabs.
So this is the one of wallet three.
So this is deterministic in
which order they are processed.
So wallet three gets this one gift
that was for wallet three and grabs it.
And wallet two gets the
first gift and grabs it.
And finally in slot 24, wallet two gets
the second gift and successfully grabs it.
We see the balances at app, so
wallet one ends up with roughly
70, wallet two with roughly 120
and wallet three with roughly 110.
For the first part of this week's
homework, I've taken the vesting
contract and changed the vesting datum.
So I added a second beneficiary.
So now we have two and the deadline.
And the idea of validation
should now be that up till the
deadline, beneficiary one can grab.
And once the deadline has
passed beneficiary two can grab.
So it's like you make a gift to
beneficiary one, but beneficiary one
only has time till the deadline to
retrieve it, otherwise you can get it
back if you self are beneficiary too.
Of course it's more general here.
So your task is simply to
write the correct logic here.
Everything else should be complete.
And I also modified the give and grab.
So the give simply sets the given
beneficiary as beneficiary one and
the wallet itself as beneficiary two.
So the giver can get or can grab back once
the deadline has been reached and passed.
And grab now filters the UTxOs
into two different UTxOs sets.
One checks that this wallet is beneficiary
one and the deadline has not yet passed.
And the second checks that
this wallet is beneficiary two
and the deadline has passed.
And then it generates
transactions accordingly could
be one or two transactions.
So one transaction for the UTxOs in
the first group and one transaction
for the UTxOs in the second group.
I need two different transactions because
the validation interval must be different.
For the first group I must use
two now, I must make sure that the
deadline has not yet been reached
or has reached, but not passed.
And for the second group of UTxOs
if I want to grab them, I must use a
different validity interval from now.
To try this out in the playground
to see the expected behavior.
I copied my solution in
the editor and compiled.
Now only need need two wallets
with the initial 100 ADA.
By doing two gives, one from wallet one,
one from wallet two in the same slot.
So the beneficiary of wallet one's
gift is wallet two and the beneficiary
of wallet two's gift is wallet one.
The deadline of the first gift is slot 10.
The deadline of the second gift is slot 5.
So what does that mean?
That means here until slot
10 wallet two can grab it.
And after that, wallet one can get it
back and here until slot 5, wallet one can
get it and after slot 5, wallet two can
get it back, So now I wait until slot 6.
So that means this deadline, here
the first deadline has not yet been
reached so wallet two can still grab.
But the second deadline
has already passed.
So wallet two can get it back, so
at that point slot 6 wallet two
should be able to grab both gifts.
So I do a grab and wait for
another block and then evaluate,
and we see that it has worked.
So let's go through the transactions.
As always Genesis transaction,
initial funds, then the two gives.
This is the one from
wallet two to wallet one.
So 50 ADA are locked
at the script address.
And this is the one from wallet one
to wallet two, again 50 ADA locked.
And these other two grabs from wallet two.
So, wallet two collects the one donation.
This is the one, this one,
the one from wallet two, so
from itself, it gets it back.
And that one is the give from wallet one.
So indeed as expected, wallet
one ends up with roughly 50 ADA
and wallet two with 150 ADA.
And I just want to point out
that we can also nicely see the
different validity intervals.
So, this grab uses the
one that starts at slot 6.
And that grab uses the
one that ends at stop six.
For the second part of the homework,
I want you to revisit the vesting,
the original vesting once again.
And remember we had two versions
of the original one to one with
one beneficiary and one deadline.
The unparameterized version where the
datum carried both beneficiary and
deadline, and then a parameterized
version where both beneficiary and
deadline were now the parameter
and the datum turned into unit.
And for this homework, I would like you
to do another parameterized version where
we split beneficiary and deadline between
parameter of the contract and datum.
So the signature of the validator, make
validator function will be like this.
Pub key hash is the parameter of the
contract and deadline is the datum.
So we split these two pieces
of information into parameter.
So then you have to implement this.
So the logic is the same, but
now the data just comes from
these two different sources.
And then just write this boiler plate.
And I adopted the wallet endpoints,
the wallet contracts accordingly.
So now it's actually nicer again, the
grab, or it depends how you look at it,
but the grab now, again, doesn't need a
parameter, because it gets the beneficiary
by just taking its own public key hash.
And it does no longer need the
deadline in order to construct the
address, because now the deadline is
no longer part of the address because
it's no longer part of the parameter.
And I had to change the logic a bit,
but actually it gets much simpler.
So maybe this is actually the right way
to do it, to take the beneficiary in
the, as a parameter of the contract,
but put the deadline into the datum.
To try this in the playground,
I have two wallets.
And wallet one makes two gifts, so I
have to wait for one block in between.
Both gifts are to wallet two, so this
is the pub key hash of wallet two, but
different deadlines and different amounts.
So this is slot 10 and this is
slot 20 and 40 ADA and 30 ADA.
So after slot 10, this should be
available and after slot 20 this.
Then I wait until slot 10
and wallet two does a grab.
So it should be able to grab the
first gift, but not yet the second.
And I wait until slot 20 and wallet
two grabs again, and now should
be able to retrieve this gift as
well and I wait for one more block.
So let's go through the
transactions, initial distribution
of funds, then the first gift...
locking 40.
So this is the one for with deadline 10.
The second gift with deadline 20 30.
The first grab of wallet two, it picks
up the first gift, but not the second
and collects the roughly 40 ADA.
And then in slot 20 wallet two picks up
the other gift and collects the 30 ADA.
If instead, I immediately wait until slot
20, then I can remove the second grab.
And this final wait and try again.
Then the first three transactions
are the same, here the
first gift, the second gift.
But then in slot 20 wallet two was able
to grab both of them simultaneously.
The 30 and the 40 gift and
collect 70 in one transaction.
So this concludes the third lecture and
we have now looked at validation scripts
that actually look at the context.
We have looked at the type that
defines the context, and we have seen
examples of how to use it, in this,
in the form of this vesting contract.
And we have particular discussed how
time sensitive contracts or validation
logic can be written in Plutus.
And we have seen how to write
parameterized contracts.