Welcome to the last lecture
of the Plutus Pioneer Program.
And in this lecture, I don't want to
introduce any new topics or concepts,
but instead demonstrate another walk
through end to end through a demo I wrote
some months ago that clones the very
popular Uniswap contract from Ethereum.
So I'll demonstrate that
and then explain that.
And the one new think I want
to show following a very
requests that some of you had.
Is I want to show how you can query
the endpoints created by the PAB with
curl commands just from the console.
So for those of you who haven't
heard of Uniswap, what is Uniswap?
Uniswap is so-called DeFi for the
centralized finance application that
allows swapping of tokens in the
case of Ethereum it's ERC20 tokens on
Ethereum without any central authority.
So you don't need a centralized exchange,
the traditional way to exchange tokens
or other crypto assets, but everything
is governed by smart contracts and works
fully automatically on the blockchain.
And another interesting feature of Uniswap
is that it doesn't discover prices the usual
way with the so-called order book, but uses
a different automatic price discovery system.
And the idea is that people can
create so-called liquidity pools.
So if they want other users to be able to
swap two different tokens, then somebody can
create a liquidity pool and put a certain
amount of those two tokens in this liquidity
pool, and then return the creator of the
pool will receive so-called liquidity tokens
that are specific to this one pool, and
then other users can use that pool to swap.
So they take some amount of one of
the tokens out in exchange for putting
an amount of the other token back in.
Additionally, people can also add liquidity
to the pool and receive liquidity tokens
as well, or they can also burn liquidity
tokens in exchange for tokens from the pool.
And all these features are also implemented
in the version of Uniswap that works on
Cardano that I'm going to demonstrate now.
So let's look at the various
operations that are available in turn.
It all starts by somebody
setting up the whole system.
So some organization or entity that
wants to offer this Uniswap service.
So it starts with a transaction that creates
a UTXO at this script address that is
here called factory for Uniswap factory.
And it contains an NFT that identifies the
factory, same trick that we have used a
couple of times before and as datum, it will
contain the list of all liquidity pools.
So in the beginning, when the factory is
just being created, that list will be empty.
Now let's assume that one
user, Alice wants to create a
liquidity pool for tokens A and B.
A pool that allows others to swap A against
B or B against A, so she has to provide
some initial liquidity for the pool.
So she needs some amount of token
A and some amount of token B,
let's say she has 1,000A and 2000B.
And it's important to note here that the
ratio between A and B reflects Alice's
belief in the relative value of the tokens.
So if she wants to set up a pool with
1000A and 2000B, then she believes
that one A is as value as much as two
Bs in order to create the liquidity
pool, she will create a transaction
with two inputs and three outputs.
The two inputs will be the
liquidity she wants to provide.
So the 1000A and 2000B and the
Uniswap factory invoked with the
create redeemer and the three outputs
will be the newly created pool.
We call it pool AB here to indicate
that it contains tokens AB, which
will contain the liquidity that Alice
provided the 1000A and the 2000B and
a freshly minted token that identifies
this pool, an NFT, I call it AB NFT here.
And the datum of the pool, the 1,415 will
be the amount of liquidity tokens that
Alice receives in return for setting up
this pool and providing the liquidity.
And if you wonder about the number that
is the square root of the product of
1000 and 2000, so that's how the initial
amount of liquidity tokens is calculated.
It doesn't really matter, you
could scale it arbitrarily.
But that's the way Uniswap does it.
The second output is the Uniswap
factory again, with the same NFT
as before that identifies it.
And now the datum has been updated.
So in this list that was empty before
the list of all liquidity pools.
There is now an entry for
the newly created AB pool.
Finally, there's a third output for Alice,
where she receives the freshly minted
liquidity tokens that I called AB here to
indicate that they belong to the pool AB.
Now that the liquidity pool has been
set up, other users can use it to swap.
So let's assume that Bob
wants to swap 100A against B.
So what will Bob do?
He will create a transaction that
has two inputs and two outputs.
The two inputs are the 100A he wants to
swap and the pool with the swap redeemer.
And the outputs are the Bs he gets in return.
In this example, that would be
181 piece and the pool updated.
So the pool now has the one hundred
A, that Bob provided additionally.
So now it's 1,100A.
And it has 181 B fewer than before.
It still, of course, has the NFT that
identifies the pool and the datum hasn't
changed because the amount of liquidity
tokens that have been minted hasn't changed.
So now of course, the question
is, where does this 181 come from?
And this is this ingenious idea, how
price discovery works in Uniswap.
So the rule is roughly that the
product of the amounts of the
two tokens must never decrease.
So initially we have 1000 As and 2000 Bs
and the product is one times 2 million.
So 2 million.
And if you do the calculation, then you
will see that after the swap 1,100 times,
1,819 will be larger than 2 million.
And if you think about it and maybe try a
couple of examples by yourself, then you
will see that in principle, you will always
pay this ratio of the As and Bs in the pool.
At least if you swap small amounts.
So originally the ratio from A to B was one
to two, 1000 to 2,000 and 100 is relatively
small in comparison to the 1,000 liquidity.
So Bob should roughly get
200 Bs, but he does get less.
So there are two reasons for that.
One is that the amount of
tokens in the liquidity pool
is never allowed to go to zero.
And the more of one sort you
take out, the more expensive, it
gets the less you get in return.
So 100 depletes the pool a bit of As.
So he doesn't get the full factor two
out, he gets a little bit less out.
That's exactly how this
product formula works.
If you think about it, and this also makes
it too ingenious because it automatically
accounts for supply and demand.
So if the next person, now would also want
to swap 100A, he would get even less out.
So the idea is if a lot of people want
to put A in and want to get B in return,
that means the demand for B is high.
And that means the price of B
in relation to A should raise.
And that is exactly what's happening.
So the more people do a swap in this
direction, put A in and get B out, the less
of the gap because the price of B rises.
If there were swaps in the other direction,
you would have the opposite effect.
So if there's an equal amount of swaps from
A to B and B to A, then this ratio between
the two amounts would roughly stays the same.
And there's an additional reason why
Bob doesn't get the full 200 that
he might expect and that is fees.
So we want to incentivize Alice to
set up the pool in the first place.
She won't just do that for fun.
She wants to profit from that.
So she wants to earn on
swaps that people make.
So this original product formula is modified
a bit to insist that the product doesn't
only not decrease, but that it increases
by a certain amount, a certain percentage,
depending on how much people swap.
So that's, I think open 3% in this
example of the 100A that Bob swaps, and it
would be the same if you swap B instead.
So this is basically added
on top of this product.
So anytime somebody swaps the product
actually increases, not only does it
not decrease, it actually increases.
And the more people swap,
the more it increases.
And the idea is that if Alice now would close
the pool by burning her liquidity tokens, she
gets all the remaining tokens in the pool.
And that would be more, the product would
be higher than what she originally put in.
And that's her incentive to set
up the pool in the first place.
The next operation we look at is the
add operation where somebody supplies
the pool with additional liquidity.
So let's say that Charlie also believes that
the ratio from A to B should be one to two
and he wants to contribute 400A and 800B.
He could also have tokens
in a different ratio.
Basically the ratio reflects his belief
in the true relative value of the tokens.
So Charlie wants to add 400 As and
800 Bs, and he creates a transaction
with two inputs and two outputs.
The inputs are the pool and his contribution,
his additional liquidity and the outputs
are the updated pool where now his As
and Bs have been added to the pool tokens
and note that now the datum has changed.
So we had 1,415 liquidity tokens
before, and now we have 1,982, and
the difference the 567 go to Charlie.
So that's the second
output of this transaction.
And that's the reward to Charlie
for providing this liquidity,
this additional liquidity.
And there the formula is a bit
complicated, but in principle,
it also works with the product.
So you check how much the product was
before and after the tokens have been added.
And you take into account, how
many have already been minted?
And that also ensures that now basically
Alice profits from the fees that Bob
paid with the swap and Charlie doesn't.
So this is taking into account, but
the specific formula doesn't matter.
The idea is just that it's fair.
So people should receive liquidity tokens
proportional to their contribution,
but, if they only add liquidity after a
couple of swaps have already happened,
then they shouldn't profit from the fees
that have accumulated in the meantime.
The next operation we look at is called
removed and it allows owners of liquidity
tokens for a pool to burn some of them.
So in this example, let's assume that Alice
wants to burn all her liquidity tokens.
She could also keep some, she doesn't have
to burn on, but in this example, she wants
to burn all her 1,415 liquidity tokens.
So for that, she creates another transaction
with two inputs and two outputs, the inputs
are the liquidity token she wants to burn.
And of course the pool again
with the remove redeemer.
And The outputs are the tokens from the
pool that she receives in return, so in
this case, she would get 1078 A and 1,869 B.
And the updated pool is the second output.
So the 1078 A and 1,869 Bs have been
removed from the pool and the datum has
been updated, so the 1,415 liquidity
tokens that Alice burnt are now
subtracted from the 1,982 we had before.
And we see that 567 are remaining which
are exactly those that Charlie owns.
And the formula for how many tokens
Alice gets for burning liquidity
tokens, is again, somewhat complicated,
but it's basically just proportional.
So we know how many liquidity tokens
there are in total 1,982 from the datum.
And she basically just gets
1,415 over 1,982 of the pool.
And she gets the tokens in the
ratio that they are in now.
So the 1072, 1,869 should be the
same ratio as the 1,500 to 2,619.
So by burning, you don't
change the ratio of the pool.
The last operation is close and it is for
completely closing a pool and removing it.
And this can only happen when the last
remaining liquidity tokens are burnt.
So in our example, Charlie holds all
the remaining 567 liquidity tokens, and
therefore he can close down the pool.
And in order to do that, he creates
a transaction with three inputs.
One is the factory and note that we only
involve the factory when we created the
pool and now when we close it again,
which also means that the contention
on the factory is not very high.
So the factory only gets involved when
new pools are created, when pools are
closed down, but once they exist and
as long as they are not closed, the
operations are independent of the factory.
But if you just need the factory, when
we want to update the list of existing
pools, and by the way, this list is used to
ensure that there won't be duplicate pools.
So the create operation that we looked
at in the beginning will fail if somebody
tries to create a pool that already exists
for a pair of tokens that already exist.
So there will always for any given
pair of tokens, be at most one pool
that country against those two tokens.
Okay, so let's go back
to the close operation.
So the first input is the factory with
the close redeemer, second the input
is the pool that we want to close.
And third input are all the remaining
liquidity tokens, and we get two
outputs, one is the updated factory.
So in this case we only had one pool.
So the list only contains this one pool, and
this is now removed from the list, and the
second output contains of all the remaining
tokens, all the tokens that were still in
the pool by the time it gets closed down.
So the remaining liquidity tokens
are burnt and Charlie gets all the
remaining tokens from the pool.
The code for Uniswap is actually
part of the Plutus repository.
And it's contained in the
Plutus use cases package.
And it's in the Plutus dot contracts
dot Uniswap module, which just
re-exports these five modules here.
On-chain, off-chain, types, pool, and trace.
And as the name suggests on-chain contains
the on-chain validation, off-chain the
off-chain code, types contains common
types that are used by the other modules.
Pool contains the business logic.
So the calculations, how many liquidity
tokens does the create a pool get,
how many liquidity tokens do I get if
I add liquidity, how many tokens do I
get back when I burned liquidity and
under which conditions is a swap valid.
Finally trace contains an
example emulator trace.
As I said, nothing here uses any Plutus
techniques that we haven't seen before.
So I don't want to spend too much
time looking at the code, but
let's at least have a brief look.
So let's look at the types module first.
You represents the Uniswap coin, the one
that identifies the factory A and B are used
for pool operations where we have these two
sorts of tokens inside the pool, pool state
is the token that identifies a pool, actually
in the diagram earlier I said it's an NFT.
And by definition, NFT is something that
only exists once actually here in the
implementation for each pool, an identical
coin is created that identifies that pool.
So it's not strictly speaking NFT.
So all the liquidity pools have
one coin of that sort and liquidity
is used for the liquidity tokens
that the liquidity providers gets.
And all these types are then
used in the coin A type.
So A is a type parameter,
that's a so-called Phantom type.
So that means it has no
representation at run time.
It's just used to not mix up the various
coins to make it easier to see what goes
where, so in the datum, a coin is simply
an asset class that we have seen before.
So asset class recall is a combination
of currency symbol and token name.
then amount is just a wrapper around
integer that also contains such a Phantom
type parameter, so that we don't confuse
amounts for token A and token B for example.
Then we have some helper
functions, constructing a
value from coin and the amount.
And here, for example, we see the use
of this Phantom type, that's actually a
common trick in Haskell because now if
you have, for example, pool operations
that has two different coins and two
different amounts for the different coins.
And if the one is tag with this type capital
A and the other with capital B, then normally
one could easily confuse them and somehow do
operations with the one coin, with the amount
for the other, and then make a mistake.
And here the type system
enforces that we don't do that.
So we can only use this value of
function, for example, if we a coin and
the amount with the same tag type tag.
So as I said, that's a common trick
in Haskell that some lightweight type
level programming that is doesn't
need any fancy GHC extensions.
Unit Value creates one
amount of the given coin.
Is unity checks whether this coin is
contained in the value exactly once,
then amount checks how often the
coin is contained in the value, and
finally make coin turns a currency
symbol into a token name, into a coin.
And we have the Uniswap type which
identifies the instance of the
Uniswap system we are running.
So of course, nobody can stop anybody from
setting up a competing Uniswap system with
the competing factory, but the value of
this type identifies a specific system.
And all the operations that are
specific to pool will be parameterized
by a value of this type, but it's
just a wrapper around the coin U.
And that is just the NFT
that identifies the factory.
Then we have a type for liquidity
pools, and that is basically just
two coins, the two coins in there.
However, there is one slight
complication, only the two types
of tokens inside the pool matter.
Not the order, there is no first or
second token, a pool that has coin
A, A and coin B, B should be the same
as one where A and B are swapped.
And in order to achieve that, the eq
instance has a special implementation.
So it's not the standard, we don't
just compare if we want to compare two
liquidity pools, we don't just compare
the first field with the first field of
other, and the second with the second,
but we also try the other way round.
So liquidity pool tokens AB would be the
same as liquidity pool with tokens BA.
So that's the only slight complication here.
Then we define the actions,
that's basically the redeemers.
So create with argument liquidity
pool is for creating a new liquidity
pool closes for closing one, swap is
for swapping, remove is for removing
liquidity and add is for adding liquidity.
Note that in the diagrams I
showed earlier for simplicity, I
called the redeemer simply create.
So I didn't mention this
argument of type liquidity pool.
The datum is a bit more complex
than we have seen before.
So it's not just a simple
integer or similarly simple
type, it's a type Uniswap datum.
And there are two constructors, one
for the factory and one for each pool.
So the factory will use the
factory constructor and the pool
will use the pool constructor.
And as I explained before,
the datum contains...
for the factory contains a list of all
liquidity pools that currently exist.
And the datum for pool contains the liquidity
pool that I didn't mention in the diagram.
And what I did mention in the diagram,
it contains the amount of liquidity
that has been minted for this pool.
Remember that gets updated when somebody
adds liquidity or removes liquidity.
Next let's look at the pool module,
which as I explained before, contains
the business logic, the calculations.
So we have calculate initial liquidity.
It gets the initial amount of token
A and B that I put into the pool and
returns the liquidity tokens that
are returned in exchange for those.
Then calculate additional liquidity for
the case that the pool already exists and
somebody provides additional liquidity.
So the first two arguments are the
amount of token already in there.
Then the third one is the liquidity that
has already been minted for the pool, the...
not the liquidity, the liquidity
tokens that have already been minted.
And the next two arguments are how
many As and Bs are added to the pool.
And the result is how many liquidity
tokens will be minted in exchange
for this additional amount.
That's additional liquidity.
Calculate removal is for the opposite case.
So given how many tokens are in the pool
how much liquidity tokens have been minted.
How many liquidity tokens to be removed?
It gives how many token's
A and B remain in the pool.
Check swap is arguably the
central function of the whole
Uniswap system, calculates a swap.
So this, and this is how many As and
Bs are originally in the pool and
this and this says how many As and
Bs are after the swap in the pool.
And it just returns
whether that's okay or not.
So in principle, it just checks that
the product of the last two arguments is
larger than the product of the first two.
And as I explained before, it's
a bit more complicated because
the fee is taken into account.
So in this case, it's Oh, 0.3%.
So you can see this is
taking into account here.
It also makes sure that none of
the amounts ever drops to zero.
So it's not allowed to remove all coins,
have one sort or both from a pool.
And that also makes sense because
of this product, if one of the
factors was zero, then of course it
couldn't be larger than it was before.
Finally, there's this LP ticker function.
It's just a helper function that
given a liquidity pool, computes a
token name for the liquidity token.
And the idea here is that this
token name should only depend on the
liquidity pool and should be unique.
So each pair of tokens should
result in a unique token name.
And in principle it just takes the currency
symbols and the token names of the two
tokens or coins, concatenates all of them
and hashes that, and then uses the hash
of the concatenation just to get something
unique and a slight complication is here
that again must make sure that the order
of coins in the pool doesn't matter.
So this way there's a condition here.
So it's checked that they are
sorted and if they are not
sorted, then you swap them around.
So the, this function should return the same
token name for liquidity pool with token A
and B and for liquidity  pool, with token B
and A which also corresponds to what I said
earlier about equality for liquidity pools.
Now let's look at the on-chain part.
Only two functions are exported to
make the validator for the Uniswap
both factory and pools, because
they share the same script address.
They address distinguished by the
datum and by the coins that identify
them and validate liquidity forging.
So that's the monetary policy script
for the liquidity tokens, but there...
it's a lot of code in this module.
And as I said, I don't want to
go through it in detail, let's
rather look at the structure.
So this is the make
Uniswap validator function.
And this function contains all
the cases for factories and
pools and the various redeemers.
And we have the function validated
liquidity forging, which is the
monetary policy for liquidity tokens.
And the idea here is that it doesn't
contain any logic and simply delegates
the logic to the Uniswap validator.
And the way it does that is it checks
the inputs of the forging transaction
and checks that it's either contains a
factory or contains a pool, because if
it does, then this validator will run.
We know that this validator will
run and then the validator can
check that the forging is okay.
And the way it does check with the...
Either the factory bool is an
input is why are the coins that
identify a factory or pool?
So it checks whether this Uniswap
factory coin is in the input or whether
one of the pool coins is in the input.
And then we just have helper functions for
all the various cases and they haven't looked
quite long but it's all straightforward.
And it's basically what I explained
in the diagram, just spelled out in
detail that all these conditions are
satisfied for all the different cases.
One thing I should mention is
I didn't use state machines
and I'm not sure it's possible.
I was thinking about that and it wasn't
obvious to me, the problem is, I mean, one
should think that both the factory and the
individual pools behave like state machines.
I mean, they are identified by their tokens
and they are these legal transitions and
then the data gets updated and so on.
But the problem are, is that sometimes
we have both of them invoice the
factory and one of the pools.
And it's not obvious to me
whether that's possible with the
current state machine machinery.
So I basically did it by
hand and I've wrote this.
Finally, let's look at the off-chain code.
Also no surprises here, it's the usual boiler
plate, be defined two different schemas.
The idea is that one is for the entity
that creates the Uniswap factory.
And that only has one endpoint
start and no parameters.
And then once that is created a second
schema for people that make use of this
Uniswap system, and all the contracts in
here will be parameterized by the uniswap
instance that this first action creates.
we make use of the state mechanism.
So of this monad writer mechanism that
is accessible via tell, and basically for
all the user operations, we have our own
state, we call it user contract state.
So there will be a helper contract
that queries for all existing pools.
So then the state would be using this pools
constructor and return a list of pools in
a simplified form, it's just a nested pair
of pairs of coin and amount in each pool.
Now the helper function to query the
existing funds of a wallet that will
just return a value and then construct
us for all the other operations.
So if they have happened, then
one of those will be the state.
So for example, if we did a
swap, then afterwards the status
will be updated to swapped.
If we removed liquidity, it will
be updated to removed and so on.
Then some names for the various tokens,
so you need swap for, with the token
name of the NFT in the Uniswap factory,
pool state will be the token name for the
coins that identify the liquidity pools.
Then our usual boiler plate to
actually get a script instance and
the policy for the liquidity tokens.
Some various helper functions, then
all the parameters for the endpoints.
So for example, if we want to create a pool
we need to know the tokens and the amounts.
If you want to swap, it must know
the tokens and how much to swap and
the idea is here that one of these
two last fields should be zero.
So if you want to put in A and get our
B we've would specify the SP amount, how
many As we want to put in, but we would
leave the B at zero and the other way
round if we want to swap B against As.
Close if you want to close a pool,
we just have to specify which pool.
So we give to two tokens that are in there.
Remove you have to specify the pool and
how much liquidity we want to burn and
add again, identify the pool and how
many As and how many Bs we want to add.
Now here we have the implementation.
So start, as I said, sets up the whole
system and did again, makes use of this
other use case we have used before,
the currency forge contract to mint
this NFT, the factory NFT that's then
used to identify the Uniswap factory.
Create it's the contract that
creates a liquidity pool.
And we see all of these will be,
as I mentioned before, identified
by the Uniswap value, which is the
result of this start contract here.
So if we have create, we have
close, again parameterized by
Uniswap, remove, add, and swap.
And all these functions also make
use of the functions from the pools
module, that contain the business logic.
So that will be used both in the validator,
on the on-chain side, as well as on the
off chain side in these contracts here.
Swap.
Pools as I said just
curious the existing pools.
So it looks for the factory UTXO
and checks the datum of that.
And as we know, the datum of the
factory contains the list of all pools.
And finally funds just checks our own funds,
the funds in the wallet and returns them.
So these all return values or I
mean, funds for example returns
value, pools returns a list of this.
But I mentioned earlier, we want to
write that in the state, and this is now
done in, in these endpoint definitions.
So first we have the owner endpoint
for setting up the whole system,
which just uses the stop contract.
And then we have the user
endpoints, which combined all these
operations that a user can do.
And now there is no return value anymore,
and instead we make use of the state.
So we use the last monoid again.
So only the last toll state will be kept.
And we also allow for error.
So if there's an error in one of these
contracts, then we will catch that error,
but use a left to write it in the state.
And if there was no error we write the
appropriate user contract state value in the
state with the right constructor for either.
So this is done here.
Finally, we also have a stop endpoint
that simply stops, it doesn't do anything.
Just, if you look at the definition
here at any time you can invoke stop
or one of the others, and if it was
one of the others then recursively user
endpoints is called again, but in the
case of stop not, so if stop endpoint
is ever called then the contract stops.
There are also tests for Uniswap contained
in this Plutus use cases library,
but I don't want to look at them now.
Let's rather look at the Plutus PAB path and
how you can write a front-end for Uniswap.
There is actually one also
contained in the Plutus repo.
It's in the Plutus PAB library and there in
the examples folder, so there's a Uniswap
folder that contains the simulation monad
path of, of an example, how to do that.
And I took this and copied it into
our Plutus pioneer program repo and
slightly modified it to make it more
suitable for what I wanted to show you.
When we look at the cabal file for this
week's code, there are two executables.
One Uniswap minus PAB, which will run the
PAB Memphis solver, and then one Uniswap
minus client, which is a simple console
based front-end for the Uniswap application.
And you see, in the other modules
field there is a module Uniswap
and that's listed in both.
So that will contain some common
definitions that are used by both paths.
So let's first look at that.
First of all, as I explained when I
presented the Oracle demo, we need some
data type that captures the various
instances we can run for the wallets.
And in this case, I have three in it.
Hasn't been mentioned before.
That has nothing specifically
to do with Uniswap.
This is just used to create some example
tokens and distribute them in the beginning.
Then Uniswap start correponds to the
Uniswap start or Uniswap owner schema
that I showed you just now for setting
up the whole system and Uniswap user
corresponds to the other path, to the various
endpoints to interact with the system.
And this task construct is parameterized
by a value of type Uniswap,
which is the result of starting.
So after having started the system, the
result would be of type Uniswap and this
is then needed to parameterize the client.
This is just boiler plate, this is this init
contract that distributes the initial funds.
So it again makes use of the forge
contract that we have seen before.
And it now producers tokens with token
names A, B, C, D and 1 million of each.
And actually it also multiplies
that by the number of wallets.
So in this case, I want to use four wallets,
wallets one to four, it's actually 4 million
of each of the tokens will be forged.
And once they have been forged, I sent
from the forging wallet to all the
other wallets, 1 billion of the tokens.
So one wallet forges 4 million of
each, and then loops over the other
wallets and sends them 1 million each.
So this is just needed to set
up example tokens and distribute
them amongst the wallets.
This is just a helper function because
in order to communicate the various
contract instance IDs and other things
I need, I just use helper files and this
is the file name for a given wallet.
Finally this instance here
has of class has definitions.
This has changed from the last
time I did a walk through and show
the PAB with the Oracle example.
This is the link between this type
here, this Uniswap contract type,
which basically defines the API.
Reifies the contracts I want to be
able to run and the actual contracts.
So now this link happens with
this type class has definitions.
And here we...
the important parts are the get
schema and the get contract.
So the get schema links this type, the three
constructors with the corresponding schemas.
So for Uniswap user it's
our Uniswap user schema.
For Uniswap start it's
our Uniswap owner schema.
And for init it's the empty schema
we don't need any endpoints there.
And this get contract links this
type against the actual contracts.
So Uniswap user parameterized by
value of type Uniswap, will call this
user endpoints with that parameter.
Uniswap start calls the owner endpoint.
And init calls this init contract here.
So now let's look at the PAB part.
So in the simulator monad,
we execute certain things.
So first we set up the whole
system, we start the server and get
the handle to shut it down again.
And then in the end we just
wait until the user types a key
and then we shut it down again.
Okay.
So first thing we do is wallet
one activates this init contract.
So we know from looking at the code
what that will do, it will mint all
these example tokens, ABCD, 4 million
of each, and then distribute them.
So that wallets one to four end
up with 1 million of each of the
four different tokens and we wait.
So, I mean, this will concurrently start this
contract, but then immediately continue at
one block, so we use this wait for state that
I explained when we talked about Oracles to
wait until init returns and what init will
do is it will write the currency symbol of
the forged example tokens into the state.
So we wait until we see that and
then we remember it and we wait until
this init contract has finished.
And then we write the currency symbol
into a file that I called symbol dot json.
And we just use encode that comes
from data dot aeson, the json
standard json library for Haskell.
So we take this currency symbol and
encode it to json and write it in
this file and we write a log message.
Then again for wallet one,
we start the Uniswap system.
So we use the Uniswap start constructor and
we again use wait for state to wait until we
get the result and the result of the Uniswap
start, I explained it earlier will be a value
of type Uniswap, and we need that value in
order to parameterize the user contracts.
So we wait until we get this, I called
it US and will log and now Uniswap, the
system is running and now we can start
the user instances for all the wallets.
So I loop all our wallets and activate
the Uniswap user contract which is
now parameterized by the US value
I got in the previous step here.
Okay.
Now I have these handles and in order to
interact, to communicate from the front-end
with the server, I need these handles.
So I write them into a file and this
is where you says helper function
CID file that I showed you earlier.
So I will end up with four files W one
dot CID until W four dot CID, which
contains these contract instance IDs
for the four contracts, log message, and
then I just wait until the user types
a key and I can shut down the server.
Let's try this out with cabal run Uniswap
minus PAB, and now a lot of stuff is
happening, remember, first we forge these
example tokens ABCD, and then we need
to distribute them to the other wallets.
Then we have to start the Uniswap system.
And for that, we again have to first forge
the Uniswap NFT that identifies the factory
and then create the initial UTXO for the
factory that contains an empty list of pools.
And now we see that all the Uniswap
user contracts have started for
wallets one, two, three, four.
If we look, we see the various files
that I wrote, so we can look at those.
So symbol dot json is the currency
symbol of the example tokens I created.
So I need that to refer to them.
And then we have these W one to W four.
So if you look at one of those, that's
the contract instance IDs for the
contract instances for the four wallets.
And in order to find the correct
HTTP endpoints to communicate
with them, I need these.
Let's look at the client next.
So as for the Oracle, I also wrote that
in Haskell using the same library for
doing HTTP requests and in the main
program, first of all, I expect one
command line parameter, just a number
from one to four, so that the main program
knows for which wallet it's running.
Then I read the corresponding CID file to
get the contract instance ID for that wallet.
And I read this symbol dot json file to get
the currency symbol of the example tokens.
I read that with something, read file
coming from the byte string library, and
decode comes from the aeson library to
decode the json back to Haskell data type,
I just check whether there was an error.
And if not, I invoke this go function where
give as parameters the CID, the contracts
instance ID and the currency symbol.
And here it's just a loop, I read a
command from the console, we get to the
commands a second, and then depending
on the command, I involve various helper
functions and the commands exactly
correspond to the endpoints we have,
except for stop, I didn't implement stop.
So we can carry our funds, we can look for
existing pools, we can create a pool, we
can add liquidity to a pool, we can remove
liquidity from a pool, we can close a pool,
and we can swap, which is the whole point.
And commands, it's just this.
So for each of those, we have a command
and in order to enter amounts and currency
tokens, currency symbols and token names.
Because the currency symbol will always be
the CS, we are only using our example tokens,
I don't need that and for the token name,
because the token names for ABCD I just use
a character for that, it's easier to type.
So for example, create Integer
Character Integer Character.
So that means create a liquidity pool
with that amount of the token with
that token name and that amount of the
token with this token name and so on.
This read command, it's just straightforward
reads from the keyboard and then tries to
pass that as a command and if it fails it
will just recursively read command again.
And if it succeeds, it returns this command.
Then there are just various helper functions
to convert something of type command
into the corresponding parameter types,
like create params or add params from the
Uniswap module that I showed you earlier.
This here show coin header and show coin
are just to make it look a bit prettier
when we query the funds or the pools,
and then we have the various endpoints
and that all makes use a helper function.
Last time, I think for the Oracle
I spelled it out, now extracted it.
So I have these helper functions get status,
which we need in order to get something
back from the contracts and call endpoint.
So I'm just using this library,
this IQ library as last time.
And here, this is the interesting
part, this is the request.
So it will be the post request,
this is the URL, and I must give
the instance ID, this is here.
So this is of type UUID, so I just
convert it into a string and then pick
it to a text because this HTTP library
expects text here and the name of the
endpoint and the request body that
depends, of course, what parameters.
So this is just a parameter here, that's
the third argument in the function.
The response will always be unit and I just
check whether I get a 200 status code or not.
And the get status is a get request
that invokes this HTTP endpoint
called status, again with the CID.
And it doesn't take a request body and
I have to tell it what I'm dealing with.
So that's why I need this
Uniswap contracts type here.
And that's also why this Uniswap
client executable also needs
access to this Uniswap module.
And then I just check if the state is
empty, which happens right in the beginning
because before in anything else told
anything to the state, then I wait a second
and recurse and if there's a state, so
it's just E, then I know that this is of
type either text a user contract state.
Recall this user contract state that was
one constructor for each of the endpoints,
but if there's an error during contract
execution, I get the error message as a text.
And if something went wrong,
then I end in this third case.
And with these two it's easy to write
all the cases for the endpoints.
So let's maybe look at one, it get funds.
So I use this call endpoint helper
function that I stress short.
So for the endpoint named funds, and in
this case, the argument, the request body.
And I wait for two seconds and then I
use this get status helper function.
And if I get a right, then I show the
funds that I got and otherwise I recurse.
So I wait until I get the right, because in
this case, there's funds should never fail.
There's no way that can fail.
Therefore I can safely wait forever.
Get pools is similar.
So it's more or less the same, except
that instead of funds, I have pools now.
And let's look at one more example,
for example, for creating a pool.
So again, I call the endpoint.
I wait for two seconds.
Now that could actually go something wrong.
For example, if I try to create a pool
where both coins are the same, or if I
specify a larger liquidity than I have
in my wallet, then I would get an error.
So in this case, I, if I get an
error, I just log it for the console
and the others are very similar.
Now let's try it out.
Let's start three instances for wallets
one, two, three, and try to recreate the
scenario from the diagrams in the beginning.
So I can start it simply by a
cabal run Uniswap minus client.
And then as command line parameter, I
give one for wallet one, and I do the
same for wallet two and for wallet three.
And I see here that these log
messages, that the contract instance
ID and the symbol for token that I
can use, the ABCD read correctly.
So now what can I do?
I can, for example, clearing my funds
and I see I have A, B, C, D, 1 million
each and a lot of lovelace, let's
see three, six, nine, 100,000 ADA.
And I can also look for pools,
but right now, there shouldn't be
any, and indeed none are listed.
So let's switch to wallet one, let's say this
is Alice, Bob is two and Charlie is three.
And in the diagrams, we started with
Alice setting up a liquidity pool
for tokens A and B, 1,000 and 2,000.
So to do this here, we can
type, create thousand A.
Remember that was of type character, so
I have to use single quotes and 2000 B.
And I get the created status spec.
So it seems to have worked.
I can query for pools again,
and indeed there is one now.
So I see it has A and B and with the
correct amounts, 1,000 and 2,000.
The next step was that
Bob swaps 100 A for Bs.
So let's do swap 100 A for Bs.
Okay.
Let's check how many funds Bob now has and
indeed he has 100 less As and 181 more Bs.
Next Charlie added liquidity.
I think it was 400 and 800, so
we can use add 400 A, 800 B.
Now check the pools.
Let me see, it's 1500 and 2619.
Is that correct, so we have 1000 at the
beginning, then 100 for add it by Bob and now
400 by Charlie, so I think that's correct.
Now, if we go back to Alice, she
wants to remove her liquidity.
So let's first create her funds.
So she has less A and Bs now because she
provided them as liquidity for the pool,
but she has this liquidity token 1,415.
So for example, she can burn
them and get tokens in exchange.
She doesn't have to burn all,
but in the diagram she did.
So let's do this, so remove 1415 A
B, and let's clear her funds again.
So now she doesn't have liquidity token
anymore, but she got As and Bs back.
So if we compare, so was
8,000 here so now it's 9,869.
So she got 1,869 Bs and 1,070 As.
And I think the last step was
that Charlie closes the pool.
So let's switch to Charlie
and let's say, close A B.
And if now we look for pools,
then again, we don't get any.
So it all seems to work.
Finally, I want to show how to do this
without Haskell, the front-end, and
just use something like curl because
somebody in the Q & A asked for that.
So let's see, I have For example, status dot
SH you will also find it in the code folder
and I expect one argument, that's the wallet.
And then I just curl to this URL and
I interpolate the content of that
file, the correct wallet file given by
the first parameter here and status.
And because that's very unwieldy, I
pass it on at Piper through tool JQ.
And then I only interested in the current
state and dot observable state of the
corresponding json after resulting json.
So if I try this right now for wallet one,
for example
We get the pool state.
So the last request that wallet one
did the last endpoint that wallet
one called was the pools endpoint.
And here we see the result in json format.
So we see right now there's
one pool with tokens A and B.
We did close this pool afterwards.
So that means that the pools endpoint
was called while the pool still existed.
And we see the result of the
last endpoint call in the status.
Now let's look at the funds script,
which calls the funds endpoint.
So again, it just takes one
parameter, just the wallet.
And again, here, the file name that
contains the contract instance id
is interpolated here into the URL.
And this time recall the funds
endpoint it's a post request.
So we provide request body,
which in this case is empty.
So let's call this for wallet one.
Okay, and now if we do status again,
it has changed and now contains the
result of calling the funds endpoint.
So now we see the funds in wallet one.
A bit more interesting is what to do with the
post requested to have interesting arguments.
For example, if now wallet one wants to
create a pool again with 1,000 A and 2000 B.
So, we need a request body for the
correct parameters for the create params.
So, in principle the curl is simple,
so now again, contract instance id.
And now it's endpoint create.
But the question is what
to write in this body.
So I have it here, so I use similar
arguments to in the Haskell implementation.
So first the wallet and then the A
amount, A token, B amount B token.
So maybe we should first check whether works.
So I can do create wallet...
Was it one?
It doesn't matter.
Let's say wallet one, 1,000 A, 2000 B.
Okay.
And now if I query the status we see as
expected that now we get the created status.
Now I also have a pools script
that calls the pools endpoint.
So if we do that and now ask
what the status again, we do get
this pool that we just created.
So remains the question, how I got this,
this body, because that's complicated.
It's hard to do this by hand, but if we
look back at the Haskell output, What I
did was here, for example, for create,
I always write the URL, where do the
request to, and also the request body.
And we can actually check the code for this.
This is in the, in this helper
function called endpoint.
So if we look at Uniswap client.
I brushed over that earlier
when I show you the code.
So this is this line here,
there write the request body.
So I get the A, that's just a Haskell
value that can be encoded to json and I
here in this, in this line where I log,
I just use encode from the json library
from sorry, from the aeson library.
So this is now a byte string.
And in order to write that to the console,
I need two strings, so I use something
from the byte string library it's called
a byte string dot lazy dot character
eight, for character eight encoding.
And so I  unpack this byte string
to a string and then I log it.
And that's the way I would recommend in order
to figure out what requests bodies to use.
I mean, you don't of course have
to write a whole program, you can
also do that in the repl so you just
need a value of the correct type.
And then use aeson to encode it and
look at the result and then you see
the shape of the json that is expected,
and then you can use that and then it's
straightforward to do the call request.
So we don't need a Haskell backend.
You, I mean, once you have curl you
can use anything like JavaScript,
for example, to write the front-end.
Okay, that concludes the lecture.
And I think because it's the last
lecture, I also don't want to give
you homework, of course you can.
If you like play around with this demo
and set up your own liquidity pools and
do some swaps, and of course, whatever
you want, I mean, you for example, can
try to write a JavaScript front-end, a
nice graphical UI, or you could also as
a challenge, think about whether it is
possible to, use the state machine mechanism
instead of doing it by hand, as I did.
So this, as I said was the last
regular lecture of this course.
I thank you very much again,
for all your hard work and your
attention and your enthusiasm.
And I hope you learned a lot
and are eager to try it out once
plutus is available on the Testnet.
And then later on the main net.
And I hope to see you again soon in,
in a future course about some other
technologies like Atala PRISM or Marlowe.
I also briefly want to announce that
other institutions are picking up Plutus.
So for example, we are collaborating
with the EBU, the European
Business University in Luxembourg.
And that's a university that does
remote classes all over the world,
mostly in Africa and Latin America.
And we share our Haskell and Plutus
content with them and they will probably
start teaching end of September.
If you're interested, there will
be a blog post coming out next
week with more details about that.
Thank you very much again, it was a
great pleasure teaching this course.