We have spent the last two lectures
talking about the on-chain part of Plutus,
the validation logic that is compiled
to Plutus script and actually lives
on the blockchain and then is executed
by nodes that validate a transaction.
And there's a lot more to
say about the on-chain part.
We haven't looked at more complex
examples of validation yet that
make more sophisticated use of the
context and actually look at the
inputs and outputs of the transaction.
And we haven't seen how
native tokens work yet.
So Plutus script is also used to validate
the minting and burning of native tokens.
And we'll definitely have to talk about
those topics and come back to that.
However, before we go into too
many sophisticated topics of
on-chain validation, I don't want
to neglect the off-chain part
because that's equally important.
The on-chain part takes care of
validation but in order to, for there
to be something to be validated,
we must build these transactions
and submit them to the blockchain.
And that's what the off-chain part does.
So I want to start talking
about how to write off-chain
Plutus code in this lecture.
And unfortunately there is
a slight problem concerning
the Haskell features needed.
So the on-chain part that we have seen so
far is somewhat alien and need some time
to get used to due to the fact that we
have this compilation to Plutus script,
but we don't really have to worry about
that, if we accept that there's this
template Haskell metric, the validation
function is just a plain Haskell function.
And it's actually a very simple Haskell
function from the technical point of view.
We don't use any fancy Haskell
features to write this function.
And one of the reasons for that is
the way Plutus compilation works.
I explained that, in principle, in
these template Haskell quotes, we need
to have everything, all the code inside
these quotes, and we can get around that
using this inline Pragma, but that still
means that everything we want to use
all the helper functions or combinators
we want to use, must have this inline
PragmA and Because the standard Haskell
libraries don't have it, we have the
Plutus prelude, for example, that is like
a copy or it's similar to the Haskell
standard prelude but it adds these inline
pragmas to all the functions in there so
that we can use them in validation code
that gets compiled to Plutus script.
But of course they are hundreds of
thousands of Haskell libraries out there.
And most of them didn't ever
written with Plutus in mind.
So we can't use them inside validation.
And that has the effect that the Haskell
code insight validation will be relatively
simple and not have many dependencies.
So it's really just a
plain old Haskell function.
It gets these three arguments,
the datum, the redeemer and the
context and returns a boolean.
Or maybe a fourth argument if
you parameterize a contract.
And somehow in the off-chain part of
Plutus, the situation also reversed.
We don't have to worry about
compilation, nothing gets compailed
to Plutus script, it's just Haskell.
So we just write plain old Haskell in
the off-chain part, but the flip side
is that the way this is implemented,
the way that works use as much more
sophisticated Haskell features,
quite advanced Haskell features,
so-called effect systems and
streaming and in particular, monads.
So, all the wallet code, the
off-chain code is written in a special
monad called the contract monad.
And monads are very infamous
in the Haskell world.
They are normally the first
stumbling block for beginners, for
people that are new to Haskell.
And there are a lot of tutorials out
there that try to explain monads.
Monads get compared to burritos
and all sorts of metaphors to
try to explain the concept.
But I thought I should at least try to
give a crash course in monad for those
of you that, that are new to Haskell.
And I do realize that will
be a bit boring from...
for people that are already familiar
with Haskell, but you can just skip
ahead until I get to the actual contract
monad that is relevant for the wallet.
So I want to start with a brief,
quick introduction to monads.
Before I get to general monads,
I want to start with IO.
So how IO side-effects
are handled in Haskell.
And before we get to Haskell,
let's look at a mainstream language
like Java, and imagine we have a
Java method with this signature.
With this signature, a Java
method foo that doesn't take
an Argument and returns an int.
And somewhere in the code later
we use it, maybe we use it twice.
So in Java, this call of the first call
of foo and the second call of foo can
very vary result in different Integers.
Even though there is no argument, as long
as we don't know what these "..." do.
We have no way of saying that this
and this will result in the same.
And why?
Because in Java it's perfectly
possible that some IO happens here
inside the body of the foo method.
For example, inside the body
that could be code that, asks
the user to input an integer on
the console and then returns it.
So if you call it here
and then again here.
Maybe at those two occasions, the user
provides a different integer from the
terminal and we get different results.
And that also means that we really
have to look at the code of this
function in order to understand
it, or in order to reason about it.
Which makes testing, for
example, more difficult.
And it also means that, I mean,
if we evaluate it here and for
example, get the result 13.
We can replace all other occurrences
of foo, of invocation of foo, with
the number 13, because as I said,
maybe it wouldn't always result in 13.
That can be something like console
input here, or it could carry a
website or a database, for example.
And that could change between
different invocations of foo.
Now in Haskell the situation is
very different because Haskell
is a pure functional language.
So the equivalent signature in Haskell
would be something like, foo type int.
And, if then we have the same situation
that we encounter foo twice, then...
I don't know what the value of
foo is, but if, for example, I see
that here it is 13, then I can be
sure that here it will also be 13.
And I don't have to look at
the dots in order to know that.
I don't care what happens here.
I know that if I use the same thing
twice, it will have the same value.
And that's a very important feature
that's called referential transparency.
And that's a feature that Haskell has.
Actually I'm lying, there are ways
there are like escape hatches to get
around it, but, we can ignore that.
So the vast majority of Haskell programs,
something like this, we have a fixed
value and that value can't never change.
And you can rely on that fact.
That for example, makes refactoring
very easy because I can just replace
foo everywhere by 13, or I could do
something like, let X equals foo in
and then do the same code as before
now with this local variable X.
And I guarantee that this term in line
15 and the term in line 14 will have
exactly the same behavior semantics value.
And that's this referential, transparency.
So that's a very nice feature,
It makes many things, much nicer
in Haskell than other languages.
Also, for example, testing, because
it means if I have something like
that in order to test it, I must
just check that the test, the right
value, this value can't change.
So if I have, I mean, this is, no,
it doesn't take any arguments, but if
I had an Argument, then I just have
to, I know that if I plug in the, if
I call foo with the same argument,
I will always get the same result.
Which is not true in a Java function,
because side-effects can happen.
So that is very nice and all very well.
But of course you need side-effects
to have an effect on the world.
Otherwise, all your program
does is heat up the processor.
So you need input and you need output.
you must make things happen in the world,
I mean, must write results on the screen
or read input from the terminal or from
a network connection or from a file.
If you can't do that, then,
your program is useless.
It doesn't do anything.
There's a famous video by Simon
Peyton Jones on YouTube, that's
called Haskell is useless.
And that is about this thing that it's
beautiful mathematically to have a
pure side-effect free language, but
eventually in the end you do need
side-effects to make anything happen.
And of course, Haskell has
way to deal with side-effects.
And that is the so-called IO type
constructor or IO Monad but don't
worry about the monad right now.
So the equivalent of something like
that in Java, in Haskell would be
foo of type not int, but IO int.
So IO is type constructor,
that takes one argument.
Like maybe for example, maybe it's another
example of type constructor with one
argument or list is yet another example.
So IO is one of these type constructors
and IO is special in the sense that you
can't implement it in the language itself.
So it's a built in primitive.
And, what does this mean?
What does this type IO int mean, it
means, this is a action or a recipe.
To compute an int and this
computation can invoke side-effects.
So you can think of it like a
cooking recipe or a baking recipe.
So it's like a list of instructions,
what a computer should do to end up
with an int in the end, as a result.
So this type IO int is a computation that
can have side-effects and results in int.
However, it's important to notice
that referential transparency
is not broken with this.
IO.
So it's a recipe to produce an
int, but when I evaluate this
foo, the recipe won't be executed.
And the result of the evaluation
is just a recipe to produce an int,
but the no execution is happening.
So, referential transparency is still
maintained and the only way to actually
execute such a recipe to execute an
IO action is in a main program, in the
executable, in the main entry point.
So if you compile Haskell to an
executable, if you have an executable,
then similar to other languages
like Java, for example, there is a
main function and that actually gets
executed by the Haskell runtime system.
And there's another way, the second
way you can also do it in the
repl, so GHCI also allows you to
execute IO so-called IO actions.
So, the hello world in
Haskell looks like this.
So we need, a module called main
or in case of the main module you
can also skip the module header.
And it must contain a function named
main and the type must be IO unit.
So this is a recipe that
can do some side-effects.
And in the end returns a
unit, which means nothing.
I mean, nothing of value because there's
only exactly one value of type unit.
So the only interesting part
are the side-effects and this
would be hello world in Haskell.
Put string line, I can ask
for the type in my repl.
So the type of put string line, it is a
function, it takes a string and returns
an IO action with no interesting result.
So the type of put string line, sorry.
Hello world is IO unit.
So it's suitable for a main program.
And I can actually execute it
for example, with cabal run.
Now, in my case, I called this hello,
so that specified in the cabal file.
It compiles and then indeed
has a side-effect and writes
hello world to the console.
I should briefly show you
the cabal file as well.
So until now I know previous
examples we only had this one
stanza out the library stanza.
So we were always just writing
Haskell libraries without a main
program, without an executable.
Now I added this stanza
here, is executable stanza.
There just specify the source
directory and then which file
contains the main module.
So I called it hello.hs.
So here is an exception, normally Haskell
modules always have to have, I mean,
the file name must equal the module
name, executables are the exception.
So the module name is allways main,
but the file can have a different
name like hello in this example.
I also mentioned that another
way to actually execute an IO
action is to do it in the repl.
So early, I asked for the type of this
expression, put string line hello world.
But if I just enter it like that, then
it will actually be executed in the repl.
So this hello world is the side-effect
happening by executing this iO action.
So we have, one example of, often
IO action way to create one, namely
this put string line, let's look at
another one it's called get line.
And that is of type IO string.
So that means it's a recipe,
possibly containing side-effects
that after having executed the
side-effects will produce a string.
And in the case of get line, the
side-effects in question is, it will
wait for user input from the keyboard.
So if I execute get line in the repl.
Now, it waits for keyboard input.
And if I enter something like Haskell
and press enter, then I get the result.
So the string result, which
is the string Haskell.
And there are of course variety of
IO actions predefined in Haskell.
And we now saw how to write to the
console and read from the keyboard.
And obviously there are many many
actions to do all sorts of things
that you would expect like reading
files, writing files, opening sockets,
reading from sockets and so on.
But obviously no matter how many
predefined actions you have, that
will never be enough if you want
to achieve something complex.
So there must be a way to combine these
primitive provided IO actions, into,
into bigger, more complex recipes.
One thing we can do is make use
of the functor instance of IO.
So if I ask for IO, information on IO
we see the dreaded monad instance that
I'm explaining now, but we also see
a functor instance and functor is a
very important type class in Haskell.
And it in principle only has this one
method that's important, I mean, this one,
the second one is just for convenience.
So if we have a functor type constructor,
then you can turn F A into an F B
If you have a function from A to B.
So we are now only interested
in the case for F is IO.
so if it's specialized this to IO, we see
that using F map and given a function from
A to B, we can turn IO A into an IO B.
And how does that work?
When IO A is a recipe
containing side-effects that
in the end produces an A.
So how do we get an IO B out of that?
Well we take the same recipe with
the same side-effects, but then
before eventually returning the A we
apply the given function to it, and
then return the result of applying
this function to A to get the B.
So, as an example, if we import data dot
character from the standard libraries, we
have the function to upper, which converts
a character into it's uppercase version.
So for example, to upper,
small Q, sorry, characters, not
double quotes, single quotes.
So to upper Q, give me
the character capital Q.
Now if I want to apply that to strings.
I can use the map function on
this because strings in Haskell
are just list of characters.
So if I map that to upper function
over a string, for example, Haskell.
Then it gives me the string when now
all the characters in this string
have been converted to upper case.
Okay, so this map to upper function
is a function from string to string.
Remember string is just another name
in Haskell for a list of character.
So that means I can use that
in combination with F map.
So if I have F map and as function
from A to B, so in this case A and B
are both string and as function from
string to string I use this to upper.
And then get line, I again, get
something of type IO string.
So get line was of type IO string.
The function I'm F mapping
is from string to string.
So I again get something
of type IO string.
And we can try that out
and see it in action.
So if I execute this in the repl,
it waits for user input and if I
now provide Haskell and press enter.
We see that the result is now,
not just a string I entered, which
would be the result of get line.
But this function, this map
to upper has been applied to
result before returning it.
So we get Haskell all capitals.
So that's one way how we can
take existing IO actions and
turn them into new IO actions.
The second way is provided
by the, by this character.
I don't actually know how to pronounce
it, greater than greater than.
That just chains two IO actions together
ignoring the result of the first.
So for example, we can do put
string line hello and then this
operator, put string line world.
And if we execute this simply both
actions will be performed in sequence.
So I think it's called
sequence the operator.
And in this case, the put string
line only has a unit result, but of
course this first one could also be a
function that has a non-trivial result,
but this operator simply ignores it.
So given these two recipes, what
the sequence operator does, it just
basically sticks the recipes together.
First performs all the side-effects
from the first recipe, then
throws away the result and then
just attaches the second recipe.
So That's one way, then there is
a very important operator, which
does not ignore the result of the
first one, and that is called bind.
So it's like this.
And if we look at the type of bind, we
see this monad constraint, but we can
ignore that for now and just think of IO.
So what that says is, if I have a recipe
that perform side-effects and returns an
A, and if I have a function that given
an A, gives me a recipe that returns a B.
Then this can, these two can be
combined to a recipe that produces a B.
And how does that work?
Well, if you have this IO A, we have a
recipe to produce an A, so we can perform
these side-effects that will eventually
give us an A, then once we have this A
we apply this function here to that A
and get a second recipe now of type iO B.
And we simply execute that and
in the end get a B as a result.
So as an example, I can apply
this to get line input string
that has exactly the right type.
So get line is IO string, and then put
string line has type string to IO unit.
So if I combine these two with this
operator, I get something of type IO unit.
And what does it do?
It will first execute the get line,
which will return a string, then plug
that string into put string line.
So it will put the string line that
was just entered out on the console.
So to demonstrate, if I do
this, get line put, sorry, it
must be bind, put string line.
So now the get line is executed.
If I enter Haskell, now this results
in the string Haskell, which is parsed
onto put string line and then put
string line executes its side-effects
and writes Haskell to the console.
There's another very important way to
create IO actions and that is to produce
recipes that immediately return a result
without performing any side-effects.
And that is done with a
function called return.
So if I asked for the type of
return, again, it's general for any
monad, but we can just think IO.
So will return as type A to IO A.
So given an A, it produces a recipe
that can contain side-effects and
eventually produces an A and in
the case of return, the recipe will
simply not perform any side-effects
and immediately return the given A.
So for example, I can do return
Haskell and now I have to give a
type annotation because otherwise,
I wouldn't know what monad it is.
So IO string and immediately
returns the string Haskell.
Returning back to our main program,
using these operators that I
just explained, we can now write
relatively complex IO actions.
For example, I can define an IO action
that will ask for two strings and
then write the result of concatenating
those two strings to the console.
So let's call it, I don't know, a bar.
So it will have type IO unit.
So what do I do?
I do a get line to read the first
string and I bind it to a function
and now I will use Lambda expression.
So I call the first elem...
write an element S.
And now, I format it a bit special,
but in Haskell you have a lot of
freedom when you format your code.
So now I bind this to a second get line.
And now I bind the third action.
So let's call the result
of this second get line T.
And now after I have this S
and T I'll do a put string
line of S concatenated with T.
I go back to the repl.
Okay.
I just get the warning that
it's defined, but not used.
So for example, I can, if I
want to get rid of that warning,
I can use bar here in main.
Okay, and now if I execute this
new executable now with bar.
So now it waits for the first input.
So let's say one, now it waits for
the second input, let's say two.
And it returns, it doesn't return
anything, but it writes the concatenation
of the two to the console, one two.
So you see that using these handful
of combinators, basically just the
bind and the return I can write
arbitrarily complex IO actions.
And this is enough for us now
for our purposes, because we
won't really need the IO monad.
Maybe much later in the course when
we talk about actually deploying
Plutus contracts to the Testnet.
But everything else, for
everything else, we won't need IO.
But it's an important example of a monad.
So I wanted to start with this.
Now for a while, let's
completely forget about IO.
Let's just write pure functional
Haskell using the maybe type.
The maybe type for those that
don't know it's one of the
most useful types in Haskell.
So it's a type constructor that takes
one type argument and maybe A is
often called something like optional
in other programming languages.
So it's an optional A, so there
are two constructors for this
type, nothing and just taking an A.
So a maybe A can either contain A
with a just constructor or nothing.
And let's import text read, sorry, read.
Yeah, text read.
Read maybe.
Right, in Haskell if you want to
parse a string to a value that has
a read instance that is normally
done with the read function.
So I can, for example, do read
42 and tell the compiler I expect
an int and it gives me, it parses
the string 42 into the int 42.
But read is a bit unpleasant because
if I have something that can't be
parsed as a string, then I get an
error and that's not very nice.
So that's why importing this read
maybe, read maybe it's very similar to
read, but in the case where parse is
not possible, it will return a nothing.
So if we replace this read with
read maybe, and now the return
type is maybe int, we get just 42.
But if we again try that with something
that can't be parsed as an int, then we
won't get an exception, we get a nothing.
I created a new Haskell
module called maybe.
Let's say I want to implement a
function, doesn't matter, let's
call it foo, that takes three
strings and return some maybe int.
And the idea is, that the function should
try to parse all three strings as ints.
And if that's successful, so if
all can be successfully parsed
as Ints, then I want to add those
three Ints and return the sum.
And if one of the parses fails,
I want to return nothing.
So, one way to do that, and I mean,
this is just plain elementary Haskell.
So I try read maybe, I apply it
to the first string and now there
are two cases it could fail.
So if I already can't parse the first
string, then I can immediately stop.
Then I do even have to
look at the other two.
But if that succeeds, let's say,
that's K, I called K, so it K is now
the integer that's parsed from X.
I can try do parse the second one.
And again, I have two cases.
This can fail in which case the whole
computation should return nothing
or there can be a successful parse.
So I parse it as a just L and now
I can look at the third string
and again, two cases, nothing, in
which case I failed or success.
Let's call the result M and now I have
successfully parsed all three int...
strings as integers.
And now I can join just K plus L plus M.
I can try whether that works.
So if I have foo one, two, three.
I get just six.
So this is parse this one, this is two,
this is three all three parsings succeed.
So I can add one plus two
plus three and get six.
But if one of those copy
past, then I get nothing.
And of course, if, sorry, I get nothing.
Okay.
But if we look at this code, we see
that we repeat the same pattern three
times and it's always very similar.
So we have something that is a maybe, this
read maybe X, read maybe Y, read maybe Z.
And then depending on the result, we
always have to consider the two cases
that it's nothing or just, and in the
nothing case, we always fail with nothing.
And in the just case, we carry on
with the rest of the computation.
And as Haskell us, we hate
repetition like that, lot of noise.
So I mean, the thing we want to do
is very simply, we want to parse the
three strings and add the result.
But with all these cases and the always
having to take care of the nothing
case, makes it very noisy and very ugly.
So as a Haskell or the natural
tendency is to try to abstract
the way the pattern we have here.
And one way to do that would be to
define something like bind maybe
given a maybe A and the function
from A to maybe B, we get a maybe B.
And how would we
implement this bind maybe?
Well, if it's nothing then we
don't even care about the function,
we immediately say nothing.
But if it's just X and we have the
function F then we apply F to our X.
And this is exactly what
we did three times here.
So to demonstrate the usefulness of
this bind maybe operator, we can now
write the same function again, now
foo, but now using this bind maybe.
Okay, so first we, we apply to read
maybe X, and now we use bind maybe
and I write that in inline style
to make it, the pattern nicer.
And if we successfully, so in the
nothing case nothing, this is now
encoded here in this bind maybe, but
if we succeed, let's call this K.
So then I can do read maybe Y,
use my new bind maybe again.
And if it succeeds I call the result
L and a third time, call the result M.
And in that case, I just
do just K plus L plus M.
Okay, and now I can try the same things
I tried before with foo prime and I
should get exactly the same results.
So in the case where all three parses
succeed, I get the sum, but if one of
the three can't be parsed, I get nothing.
So we see that by introducing this
bind maybe, we capture this pattern,
this very common pattern that you often
encounter when you use optional values
of type maybe, that if you, if it's
nothing you want to immediately stop,
it doesn't make sense to continue.
But if it's just something, then using the
value of this something you can continue.
And this is captured in
this bind maybe function.
And we see that using this, we can
write the original foo function
much nicer in a much nicer form.
So we don't have this dangling case
statements any longer and all this
noise with the nothings, because
this is now encapsulated abstracted
the way in this bind maybe function.
This does exactly the same as the
foo did, but it's much more compact
and the business logic is much
clearer, we see we try to read these
three strings parse them as Ints.
And if everything succeeds
will return the sum.
So there's far less noise now by
using this bind maybe function.
And what the bind maybe does is it
encapsulates the idea that we have
something of a maybe type and if that's
something is nothing, the overall
result of the computation is nothing.
And if it's just, then we continue
with the value of this just.
And if you think about it,
that's a bit like exceptions
in other programming language.
If you think of nothing as an exception,
then the normal behavior of exceptions
and other languages is that as soon as
an exception is thrown, you immediately
stop with the computation and return
the exception, bubble the exception up.
And this here now behaves very similarly,
as soon as we accounted nothing, we
immediately stopped with nothing.
And if not, we carry on.
And this pattern, this idea, this
exception like behavior is captured
in this bind maybe function.
And using that, we can write the
original logic very compactly.
Another very useful type in Haskell
is the either type that takes two
parameters, two type parameters, A and B.
So, if I ask for information for either,
then we see it has two constructors,
like maybe, but both carry a value.
So an either A B can either carry
an A, or it can carry a B and the
two constructors are left and right.
So for example, I can have left
haskell, it can be of type either
string int, but I can also have
right seven of the same type.
I created another module called
either where basically just
copied what we had for maybe.
And if we take this exception analogy
a little bit further, then one
issue with maybe is that if we do
nothing, if we return nothing, in
an analogy to throwing an exception,
then there is no error message.
It's just nothing, it just fails
without any indication of why.
So if you want something like that, then
we can replace maybe with an either type
where right corresponds to just and left
corresponds to an error like nothing did.
But now we, depending on what type we
choose for the first type parameter A,
we can have a type of error messages,
for example, we can use string.
And the read maybe returns
a maybe, and not an either.
So let's first define something,
let's call it read either.
So read maybe has type
read A string to maybe A.
There would be the type of read
maybe, but now let's replace this
with an either string A and we can
implement this in terms of read maybe.
So given a string, we just check what
read maybe tells us about this string.
So if parsing is not possible and if
we get a nothing, we can now return
a left and pick some error message.
This is now, it doesn't matter what
we say, but I can say something
like can't parse and just append
the string, the given string.
And if we can successfully parse
to an A, then we return right A.
So we can try this out, read either
42, either string int that succeeds
and we get right 42 where before
with read maybe we got just 42.
And if we pick something that can't
be parsed, then instead of just
nothing, now we get a more informative
error message "can't parse this".
Okay, and using that we can now rewrite
our foo in terms of either string int.
So when we replaced all the
read maybe's with read either's.
Now, of course the cases change.
Now, instead of nothing and
just we get left or right.
So if we get left error message well we
just stop with the same error message.
And if we get right K, we continue.
Same here, left error message, left error.
And if it's a right we continue and
once more left error, left error.
If we get a right we continue with right.
This...
would compile, but okay.
Let's see, so let's try this out.
So foo, for example, one
two three, we get right six.
But now if we, if one of the
arguments can't be parsed, then...
okay.
Now maybe I should, I mean, it's
correct, but we don't see much so if
I write something, then now it doesn't
simply fail, I get a nice error message.
And if I have an error in one of
the, or something that can't be
parsed an int in one of the other
arguments, it works accordingly.
And of course, we have the same problem
again, that we had with maybe, that we
have these dangling case statements and a
lot of repetition, a lot of boilerplate.
Because we always follow the same
pattern, we always pattern match on
the either and in the left case, we
simply return again the same left with
the same error message that we got.
So we immediately stop don't continue
and instead return the error we got.
And in the right case, we continue
with the rest of the computation.
And there's a similar solution
again, to what we did before.
So let's call, define a similar helper
function that we called bind either.
Then we replace each maybe with either
string and now try to abstract a way this
pattern that we repeated three times here.
So if we get left of an error
message, we simply return left
of the same error message.
And if we got a right X, then we
simply continue plugging X into the
continuation of our computation.
And now in the same way as before I can
rewrite this foo in a much nicer form.
I just have to replace each
bind maybe with bind either.
And of course here I have to
use read either instead of
read maybe and here right.
And now the same foo again
work if we use foo prime.
So if all goes well, we get right.
And if something can't be parsed as an
integer, I get a nice error message.
And the same I said before is again true.
So by introducing this little combinator,
I abstract the pattern in a way that
we repetitively use here and the
business logic becomes much clearer.
And to code incidentally is very
similar to what we had for maybe,
it's almost the same, except that
instead of bind either bind maybe
I'm not using bind either instead of
read maybe I'm not using read either.
So far, we've looked at three examples.
IO A, maybe A and either
E A or either string A.
And IO A represents plans
that can involve side-effects.
And when executed produce an A, and
maybe A an either string A represent
computations that can produce an A,
but can also fail and the difference
between maybe and either it's
just that maybe doesn't carry any
error message whereas either does.
Now let's look at a completely
different example, that kept us
the idea of computations that
can also produce log output.
And we can represent that with
the type, let's call it writer A.
And let's just say it's a constructor
that takes two arguments, an A
which is our result, but also a
list of log messages for simplicity.
Let's do it like this.
Okay, and let's actually,
we can deriving show.
And as an example, can define a
function number from int to writer int.
And give a number N....
we just produce that number and
as log output we just, it doesn't
matter, but we can, for example,
just say number and then show N.
I can try that out in the repl, So
number 42 is, so we have the 42,
the result and this log message.
And, now let's do something similar
as before, this foo function.
So say we have three logging computations
that each produce an int and we want
to compute those three computations
to one that, adds the three Ints.
So foo X Y Z, or let's pattern match,
writer K X, writer L Y and writer M Z.
What can we do?
we....
So the overall result is K plus L plus M.
And what should the log message be?
Well, so we know each of the X the
Y and the Z is a list of strings.
So I probably should rather
following the Haskell convention
for list call it Xs Ys and Zs.
And I can, for example, just
concatenate those three lists.
Okay.
And I can try this out also out, let's
say foo number one, number two, number
three, and I get the expected results.
So I get the sum as result and
I get these three log messages.
Let's write another useful function.
Let's call it tell And it should
just get a list of log messages
and produce a writer unit.
So one that doesn't have useful result
and just cares about the log messages.
And I can just define that like so.
Right.
Compiler helps me I can write
it simpler like this as well.
And, so I could make that this
example a bit more interesting.
I could add another log message.
So let's say let S equals K plus L plus
M and writer us equals tell sum show S.
And now I can actually do it like this.
And if I run the same example again,
now we have an additional log message
here that tells us the sum is six.
And we again we have the result.
So the idea is we see, we can again
combine computations, several writer
computations into a bigger computation.
And the idea here is that, we have
to concatenate the log message
from each computation in order
to get the overall log message.
And as before we can write
the function bind writer.
So given a writer that produces an A
and the function from A to writer B,
we can combine those to a writer B.
What do we do?
Again I can pattern match
against the first one.
Okay, and how do I do that?
Well, now I have the result A of the
first computation, so I can, plug this
A into the function F to get a writer
B, so I can say writer B Ys equals F A.
And now I can produce the result.
So the result of the computation is B.
And what are the log messages?
Well, the Xs from the
first one plus the Ys.
And now using that, I can rewrite
my foo using this bind writer.
And make it much nicer.
So I start with X bind writer.
Call the result K.
And Y bind writer, call the result L.
Z bind writer call the result M.
Now, tell sum K plus A plus M.
Actually, I should also,
I can also use a let here.
So let S equals K plus L
plus M in tell sum is show S.
Bind writer.
And here I don't care about
the result because tell
doesn't produce a nice result.
Now, writer sum a new log message.
Move the rest here.
Okay.
And now what we did with foo
before we can do with foo prime
and we get the same result.
And admittedly it's even
longer now than it was before.
So, or at least not much shorter,
but I think that it still is
much nicer than the foo version.
We don't have to do this pattern
matching to extract the log messages
from the three input computations.
We don't have to explicitly
combine the last log messages
where we could make a mistake and
forget one or get the order wrong.
Instead we basically abstract
all of that away and can just
concentrate on the business logic.
And a part from this part here we
have ever used as additional tell.
This is also very similar
to, if you remember what we
did, with maybe and either.
So the code looks very much the same.
So as before we have this business
logic, we have three computations.
And we that somehow result in int and
we form the sum and return the sum.
But note that the, like the special
aspect of these computations is
completely different in the, maybe and
either case, we captured the notion of
failure that something going go wrong.
Whereas here in the writer case, there is
no failure, but we have additional output,
these log messages that we combine.
So the bind maybe, and bind
either encapsulated the logic
that, if you want to combine two
computations that might fail.
And the first one fails, then
the overall computation fails.
Whereas if the first one succeeds,
you can take the result to continue
with the second computation.
Here, the bind writer captures a different
logic of sequencing computations, namely
the logic that if you want to sequence
to log output producing computations, we
simply combine the individual log outputs.
Now, I think we are in a position
to explain what a monad is.
So going back at the four examples,
what did they have in common?
Where we had a type constructor
with one type parameter in any every
case, IO for real world side-effects.
Maybe for computations that can
fail, either string for computations
that can fail with an error message.
And writer for computations that can
produce lists of string as log output.
And for all four of these
examples, we had to bind function.
So in the case of IO, it was this operator
token IO A and something A to IO B.
And you can combine the two to an IO B.
And we had a very similar functions that
we called bind maybe, bind either and
bind writer for other three examples,
and they always had the same shape.
You would take computation of the type
of computations you're considering
results in A and then a function from a
to another such computation that results
in a B, and you can bind the two together
to a computation that results in B.
And how this bind works?
Depends on the case.
In the case of IO it's built in metric,
but you can think of it as just combining
the two plans that describe the IO
actions to take during execution.
And in the bind maybe and bind either case
the logic is that if the first computation
fails, then the combination also fails,
but if the first computation succeeds,
you continue with the second one.
And in the bind writer example, the
logic of bind was to just combine
the list of log messages from
the two parts of the computation.
And that is the main idea of monads,
it's a concept of computation.
With some additional side-effect,
it can be real world side-effects,
it can be failure or failure with
error messages, it can be producing
log outputs and there are various
other examples that I didn't mention.
And the possibility to bind
two such computations together.
And how the bind works?
Depends on the computation
you're considering.
There's another aspect that I
briefly mentioned in the case of
IO, but not for the other examples.
Another thing that we can always
do whenever we have such a concept
of computation with side-effect, we
also always have the possibility to
produce a computation of this type
that doesn't have any side-effects.
So I talked about return in the IO case.
So given an A, you can turn it into an
IO A, and that is simply the computation
that immediately returns an A and has no
side-effects, no real world side-effects.
In the case of maybe we have
to just constructor of maybe.
So given an A, just A is soft
type maybe A, and it doesn't
fail because it's not nothing.
So it doesn't make use of the special
possibility to fail, it doesn't fail.
Same for the either case if
we use the right constructor.
So either string represents computations
that can fail with a string error message.
And if we use the right
constructor, we have such a
computation, but it doesn't fail.
No error message, it has an A result.
Finally for writer.
there's no short way to write it down.
We could, for example, define a function,
return writer or something, but I just
wrote it down here as a Lambda term.
So given an A, we just produce writer
A with an empty list of log messages.
So given an A, we can produce a log
message producing computation of type A
that doesn't make use of this possibility
to produce log messages and simply doesn't
log and immediately returns the result.
And the combination of these
two features, the possibility to
bind two computations together.
And the possibility to construct
a computation from a pure value
without making use of any of
the potential side-effects.
This is what defines a monad.
So if we look in the repl and ask
for monad, then we see the bind here.
So in the monad class we have this bind,
so monad is now type constructor M.
So we have seen various examples,
IO, maybe either string writer.
And here we have this bind operator.
So taking a computation that
results in A and a way to turn A
into a computation that results in
a B combine those two parts to a
computation that results in a B.
And the return that takes a pure value
of type A and turns it into a side-effect
in computation where the intuition
obvious is that the M allows potential
side-effects, but in the return case, it
doesn't make use of this and just reps
this pure value into such a computation.
We see here that we also have this
operator that I explained in the
case of IO, but that can easily
be defined in terms of the bind.
So it's just a given for convenience.
And what it does is, it just throws
away the result of the first computation
when it considers the second.
So in other words, you can easily
define it from bind by using the
constant function here, the function
that completely ignores its argument
and, always returns a fix and B
in order to once we have bind, you
also get this sequence operator.
There's another technical computation,
we see that monad actually
has a superclass applicative.
So every monad is applicative.
And if we ask what the applicative is,
we see it has a bunch of functions, but
actually you only need the first two.
And we see pure actually as the same
signature type signature as return.
And then there's this one, which looks
a bit more complicated, but the fact
is once we have return and bind in
a monad, we can easily define pure
and this operator that's called...
pronounced ap.
So pure is just return and
ap it's actually a library
function that automatically
given a monad implements this.
When we see that applicative in
turn also is a superclass functor.
And I mentioned that before
also in the context of IO.
Functor has this F map class, method.
So given a function from A to B,
we can turn an F A into an F B.
The prototypical example for function
is lists, and then F map put just B map.
So given the function from A to B and
a list of As, you can turn it into a
list of Bs by simply applying the given
function to each element in the list.
And we saw that we also have F map for IO.
And again, once we have return and
bind, it's easy to define F map in
turn, in terms of return and bind.
So there is a general patterns, so
basically you never, if you want to
define a monad you always defer and
return and binds and just to make the
compiler happy and to also give instance
for functor and applicative, there's
always a standard way of doing that.
So we can do this in
the example of writer.
So if I want to define a monad instance
for my writer type, I need functor,
applicative and monad, but in almost
all cases, you never do that explicitly.
So I leave it open for now.
So all you normally do, is you...
define return and bind.
So, bind is just our bind writer
and return is the, what I wrote
there in the comment earlier.
So we return by simply return the A
and giving empty list of log messages.
Right.
And given this, the standard way to
implement functor and applicative
is to use helper functions from
the prelude, from control monad.
And there something like lift M, that
always, so that basically makes use
of return and bind to implement F map.
And for applicative we need this
pure, which we can just use return,
and then we need this ap operator
and there's something in...
similar to lift M there is something
called ap in control monad that does that.
Again, using return and
bind, it implements this.
So this is the standard pattern
if you implement a monad, you
implement return and bind.
And then for the functor and the
applicative instance, you just use
these helper functions, lift M for pure
use return and for this ap operator
you use ap and that should compile.
Right, so now we have a...
by hand implemented a monad.
I don't have to do the same for maybe
either and IO, because they are all
already monads defined in the prelude.
So there I don't have to do anything.
And now that we have that, we can actually
try to understand why this is useful.
I mean, first of all, it's always
useful in general to identify a
common pattern and give it a name,
just to name things somehow makes the
importance of the concept clearer.
And, so, so it's always a good thing
to identify that this is an important
concept and important pattern that happens
all over the place and then explicitly
describes the pattern and give it a name.
So that's one advantage.
The second advantage is just that, I mean,
if we had to came up with all these names,
bind writer, bind maybe, bind either.
And now by using the type class, we don't
have to remember all these different
names for the different examples
we can always use return and bind.
And finally, maybe the most important
advantage is that there are lots of
functions that don't care which specific
monad instance we are dealing with.
They just work for all monads, so we
can write it once and for all monads
and then reuse it for specific examples.
So, both in the maybe and in the either
and in the writer case, I had this
thing where I took three computations
that represent Integers and then I
return the sum of them and I can now,
let's call it three Ints, do that
for all monads, once and for all.
So I get M int and M int and the
third M int and turn it into an M int.
And MX MY MZ.
And how do I do it?
Well, I take the first one,
call the result, for example, K.
And bind that to the second computation,
call the result L, bind it to the
third computation call the result M.
Now I can define the sum.
And now I can use the return
of the monad to return the sum.
I mean, I wouldn't need the let here.
I could also do that in line, of
course, which I basically did in...
I can also do it like this.
But for reasons that will be came,
come in a second, wait a minute.
Let me leave the let here.
And if we now look, if you go
back, for example, to our maybe.
We see this is now almost exactly
the same code that I wrote here,
except that instead of bind maybe,
I'm now just using the bind operator
that I have for every monad.
So we can now rewrite this.
if I import this, then I
have the three Ints function.
So I can now write a
third version of this foo.
So now using the three Ints function
that I defined in the monad module.
I can turn this into a one-liner read
maybe X, read maybe Y, read maybe Z.
Trying it out.
So foo one two three.
And again, I get just six and if one of
those is not possible, I get nothing.
I can do exactly the same for either.
Also import these three Ints function.
So in this case, it's three ints.
Read either X, read
either Y, read either Z.
Then Again I can try it out.
One, two, three.
And we get right six.
And if one of them is not
possible, I get a error message,
appropriate error message.
Writer, writer is a little bit...
I can't because of this line here
because of this additional log it,
it's not exactly the same, but I, if
I am happy with not doing this log.
Here it's then it's even simpler
because this is immediately
an instance of the three ints.
So...
ah, I must import the module.
So that would work, but of course that's
a bit cheating because now I don't
have this, but I can get that as well.
So I can simply use bind again as...
if I want to do that, I do have
to give the arguments X Y Z.
Okay, so I get the sum as a result,
and now I can do the tell sum show S.
The tell doesn't have an interest
in result, so I could write unit
here or I can simply ignore it,
or I can use the sequence operator
which is made for exactly this
case where I am not interested
in the result and then return S.
And again, if I run foo double prime.
Okay, so yeah.
I have to do number one,
number two, number three.
Then again I get the same as before.
So we see that now with this three Ints
function that we defined once and for
all for arbitrary monads, I can write
all this specific code that I did for the
various cases, just reusing this function.
So that's one of or maybe the
biggest advantage of actually
having this monad class.
There is, if you look into the control
monad module in the standard Haskell
prelude, there are many useful functions
that you can use for all monads.
And so you have to write them once
and for all in Haskell, and then you
can reuse them over and over again.
So lets go back to this
monad module one last time.
So yeah, I mean, the way I
think about monads it's....
A monad is...
is some sort of computation with
the side-effect or a special
feature or a special power.
It's like a super power.
And, so in the case of IO the super power
would be having real world side-effects.
In the case of maybe, the super
power would be to be able to fail.
The case of either the super power
would be to fail with an error message.
And in the case of writer, the super
power would be to log string log messages.
So we have this computation, we have a
type that represents computations with
some special features, some special power.
And what turns this into a monad is
the existence of return and bind.
So return says you must have
a way to given a pure value A.
You must be able to produce a
computation of this type with return
value A that does not make use of this
super power of the special feature.
So it's an IO action that doesn't
have any real world side-effects
or potentially failing computation
that doesn't fail or potentially
logging computation that doesn't log.
So that's return, returns a
pure value into such a value
in that type of computations.
And bind allows you to chain several
computations of this type together.
So giving two, I mean, giving,
giving one and the way to given a
result of the first one produce a
second computation, you can use bind
to bind those two together to one.
And that is of course crucial
if you want to assemble a
large complicated computation.
So you have like simple primitive
ones and using return and bind,
you can assemble them into
arbitrarily complex computations.
And there is this slogan in the
Haskell community that Haskell
has an overloaded semi-colon.
And the explanation for this is that
in many programming languages, in
imperative programming languages who
write lines of code and at the end
of the line you have a semi-colon.
And then basically what that does
is it executes one after the other.
And the different statements
are separated by the semi-colon.
But what exactly the semi-colon means?
Someone depends on the programming
language, for example, there could be
an exception in which case, computation
or execution would stop at the spot
where the exception happened and
wouldn't continue with the next lines.
Or there can be other things there
that could potentially happen.
And in a sense, this bind
is like a semi-colon.
So it binds different statements of
monadic, of computations together like a
semi-colon does in an imperative language.
And the cool thing about Haskell is that
it's basically a programmable semi-colon.
So we can save what the logic
is of binding two computations
together, depending on the monad.
Again, in the case of failure, the
logic is that if the first computation
fails, the whole thing fails.
In the case of logging of writer, the
logic is that you simply combine the list,
the individual list of log messages to a
long concatenated list of log messages.
So each monad comes with its own
semi-colon basically, its own bind that
tells you how to combine two computations.
One last thing that needs to
be mentioned is do notation.
Because this is so common and monadic
computations are all over the place and
we always have this pattern, so we do a
bunch of monadic computations and we bind
them together and give the result a name.
There is special notation for this
in Haskell that's called do notation.
It's just syntactic sugar, so it doesn't
add any more power to the language.
You could write everything simply
like this, but actually how it
would normally be written in
Haskell would be using do notation.
So let's write the same function
again, but using do notation.
And then this would look like that.
So it is do keyword.
And then, instead of writing it like
this, this would be written like so.
So, which has far less noise than this,
but it means exactly the same thing.
So the compiler will simply
translate this two version into this.
So whenever we want to bind and
use the result and give a name to
the result, we write it like this.
So the computations on the right of
this arrow from the right to the left
and on the left is the name that we
give to the result of this computation.
And then we can just, we don't have
to explicitly use the bind operator.
We can just write a new line.
And now in the following lines, the K
and the L and the M will be available.
So I can use it here for the return.
And another thing you can do is let.
So, oh yeah.
I said earlier that I want
to leave it like this.
So, I would do that like this.
So we can also use let
statements in a do block.
And note that the in keyword that
is normally needed in Haskell.
So normally in Haskell the
let it's let in, but in a do
block, you don't need the in.
So yeah.
So normally you would, in this
case, instead of using explicit
binds, you would use do notation.
For shorter expressions, it's
more less a matter of taste.
So you can always use do notation,
but you don't have to and often if
it's like one or two computations,
then people also use explicit binds.
But as I said, it's a matter of taste.
So if we...
once more go back to our writer example.
Let me just write this here in do
notation instead, this foo double prime.
So S goes here.
Then that's the tell.
Okay.
And If I'm not interested in the result,
I just can just write it like this.
So I don't need the inverse arrow and
the name if I'm not interested in that,
in the name and just do it like so.
And if I reload and run this again now
with the do notation, implemented with do
notation, I get exactly the same result.
So this is how I would normally write it.
And that's monads for you.
So hopefully now you have an idea
how monads work, what they mean.
And, there would be a lot
more to say about monads.
For example, if we have now seen
examples, how to do failure in pure
code and logging and also IO and not
in pure code, IO is not pure, but the
other examples were all pure code.
And how to use the monad instance of
these examples to basically handle all of
them uniformly choosing, for example, do
notation or bind and return explicitly.
But often as so we have these special
features like failure with error
message, log, logging messages and so on.
But often you are in a situation where
you need several of these effects.
So you want failure and log
messages, for example, and that
is also possible in Haskell.
And they are variety of
approaches how to do that.
One is called monad trasnformers.
So using so-called monad transformers
one can basically build custom
monads using these transformers.
We can just say "I want failure
and I won't log messages".
And then you use the monad transformer
library to build a custom monad that
has exactly the features that you
want, but there are other approaches.
One is called effect systems,
which has a similar objective.
So you basically want to tailor
make monads that have exactly the
features you want them to have.
And that is incidentally what
Plutus uses for important monads in
particular, the contract monad in
the wallet and also the trace monad
that is used to test Plutus code.
And the good news is that you
don't have to understand effect
systems to work with these monads.
So it's enough.
So for example, to work with the
contract monad that you use to define
Plutus code that runs in the wallet,
off-chain code, you must just know that
contract is a monad, which for example,
tells you that you can use do notation.
And you must know what special
super powers, what special
features this monad has.
So for example, in the writer,
monad we have this tell function
that's specific to the writer monad.
And, in the case of maybe or either
we have be can basically fail.
So we have something like we can
throw exceptions which would be
nothing and maybe or left in either.
And similar there's a list of things that
you can do in the wallet contract monad.
So all you have to know is basically
how monads work in general, how you
can chain statements or computations
together using bind, or do notation.
And then for a specific monad like
the contract monad, the wallet
monad you have to know what specific
features this specific monad offers.
So that is what we will look at next So
we will look at the contract monad and
see what this specific monad can do.
Now that we hopefully all have at
least basic understanding of monads
and how to write monadic code
either by using explicit bind and
return, or by using do notation.
We can look at a very important monad
for Plutus namely the contract monad.
And maybe you have already seen that
in the code examples I provided.
So the contract monad defines
code that will run in a wallet.
So that defines the off-chain
part of Plutus and is equally
important to the on-chain part.
But before we go into details
with this contract monad, I also
want to talk about a second monad,
so-called emulator trace monad.
Because quite a few of you asked me
whether we really need the playground
to test Plutus contracts and whether
there's a like quicker, easier and
faster way that doesn't require you
to, start this playground server
and then obvious manually copy paste
over into the editor and so on.
And there is indeed, and, this
is done via this emulator trace
monad and you can think of a trace
in this monad, programming this
monad as what we do manually in the
simulator tab of the playground.
So there are we always defined the initial
conditions and then a defined action.
So we set a wallet one does this,
invokes this endpoint with these
parameters, and then we wait.
So and so many slots and then
wallet two does this and so on.
And things like that, you can
also do in this trace monad, so
we should look at that first.
Emulator traces are defined in
module Plutus dot trace dot emulator
in package Plutus minus contract.
And we see that emulator trace A is a
type abbreviation, type synonym for some
very complicated looking effect monad.
This is what I mentioned before that the
Plutus team used so-called effect system
to build case custom tailor monads,
including this emulator trace monad.
But we don't have to worry
about that, what that means.
So before we look at how to define traces,
let's first look at how to run them.
And the most general way
is this run emulator trace.
So it takes a emulator
config, a fee config.
We will look at those two in a
minute and the trace with unit
result and then produces a triple
and note that there's no IO here.
So that means this run emulator
trace is a pure function.
It's a pure function without
any real world sie-effects.
And this triple, so it's
a list of emulator events,
then maybe an emulator error.
So if there's no error that's will be
nothing and if there is an error, it will
be just the error and some emulator state.
Okay, so let's look at the configs, so we
have the emulator config, which just has
one field of type initial chain state.
So let's look at initial chain
state, and that is either an
initial distribution or TX pool.
So look, let's look at initial
distribution and that is just
a map from wallet to value.
So it just specifies key value pairs
where the keys are the wallets and
the value is the initial value.
Value can be ADA, but it can also
be native tokens, but we'll get to
native tokens in a later lecture.
There's a default distribution we
can look at that in the repl and
there's also something called default
distribution for if you want to specify
how many wallets you want to have.
The default distribution, I think
uses 10 wallets and here you can have
a list of those wallets you want.
And then you get an initial
distribution by specifying the wallets.
So maybe we should look
at that in the repl.
Let's start the repl.
It doesn't really matter, but we can
load the trace module and we need
to import Plutus contract trace.
We have this initial
distribution, yes, it's available.
So we can look at the
default distribution.
Okay, and we see a...
entries from wallet one to wallet ten
and each wallet gets, I believe 100 ADA.
This default distribution for, as
I said, takes a list of wallets.
So if we, for example, only one wallet one
and wallet two, then we don't have wallets
three to wallet ten and just wallet one
and two, and they to have 100 million ADA.
If we in the repl import Plutus
contract trace again and then Plutus
dot trace dot emulator and data
default and ask for emulator config.
Then we see what we saw before in the
documentation, but we also see that
it is an instance of the default class
that I explained in the last lecture.
So if we look up the value of the default
value for emulator config, we see that
we get initial chain state left, recall
that was the initial distribution.
And we see, this is exactly the default
distribution that we saw just now.
So 10 wallets with 100 ADA each.
Back in the documentation, so we now
played a bit with initial distributions.
Of course, if you don't want the
default value of 100 million ADA, you
can just give an explicit map value
specify exactly what values you want.
Let's look at the other option, this was
the left option, look at the right option.
There's TX pool and we see this as just a
type synonym for a list of transactions.
And as it says here in the documentation,
in the comment, a pool of transactions
which have yet to be validated.
So instead of providing an
initial distribution, you can
also provide an initial list of
transactions that will be applied.
Okay.
So now this was initial change state,
which we needed for emulator config.
And if you go back to
this run emulator trace.
So we have looked at the emulator config.
So what's the fee config and we
see this is a record type with two
fields, a field config constant fee
and field config scripts fee factor.
So the constant fee per
transaction and lovelace.
So that's what you will always have
to pay and then a factor by which to
multiply the size-dependent script fee.
So this is just some calibration factor.
So the size depends on the memory
consumption of this script and
the run time, the number of
execution steps, and that then
gets multiplied by this constant.
If we go to the repl again, load our
module again, although that's not
necessary and import ledger dot fee.
And again, data dot default
and ask for fee config.
Then we see what we just saw
and we see that this type is
also an instance of default.
So let's look at the default.
So there's a flat rate fee of 10
lovelace, so the total fee will be
10 plus one times whatever the memory
consumption and execution steps are.
So let's load Plutus trace emulator again.
So, recall we were looking at
the run emulator trace function.
And now we have looked at
emulator config and fee config.
And we can use def for both so we
can use run emulator trace def def.
So the first def will be the
default emulator config which gives
us 10 wallets with 100 ADA each.
The second one will give
us the default fee config.
So now all that's missing is an actual
emulator trace and we haven't looked at
how to construct an emulator trace yet.
But we know because I told you
that emulator traces is a monad.
So without knowing anything else
about emulator traces, we know
that we have the standard monad
operations return and bind available.
So in particular return, so the simple,
most emulator trace we can possibly write
is the one that immediately returns unit.
So it doesn't do anything, it doesn't
call any contracts, doesn't wait for
any slots, it immediately returns.
So let's try what this gives us.
And wow, we get a lot of
output and that's mostly due to
this list of emulator events.
So even for a contract for a trace
that doesn't do anything, we have many
screens full of events, which also
demonstrates that this is not very useful
for trying out a contract in the repl
because there's too much information,
but luckily there's also something called
run emulator trace IO that just takes
an emulator trace, no configurations.
So those will just be the
default configurations.
And it's not a pure function anymore
it just write something to the screen.
So we can try this with our trivial
trace that immediately returns.
And we see we get a much
more concise output.
So we see right in the beginning,
a transaction is validated, that
will be the Genesis transaction
that distributes the initial funds
of 100 ADA to the  10 wallets.
And we see it waits for slot add 2.
And we get the final balances, and
because we haven't done anything,
those final balances are still
the initial balances of 100 ADA.
Sometimes of course you do want to specify
in different initial condition or you
want to have more fine grain control.
And for this, there's a variation
of run emulator trace IO, which
is called run emulator trace
IO prime, and that does take an
emulator config and the fee config.
And in addition also a trace
config, so what's a trace config?
That's a record type with two fields,
the second one is a handle and in
Haskell a handle can be a file,
but it can also be the console.
So the default would be that it's the
console, but you can also specify a file.
So, what we saw right now in
run emulator trace IO there the
handle is the standard output.
And we have a field show event
which takes an emulator event
prime and returns a maybe string.
So here, the idea is we get this
list of all the emulator events
and we run the run emulator trace
function, the one with so much output.
And then for each such event,
we can specify either nothing,
which means that event will be
suppressed or just the string that
should be displayed for that event.
And this trace config is
also an instance of default.
So we can use def for the default
trace config which will be the one
that's used by run emulator trace IO,
which shows very few events as we saw.
Now, let's look at the more interesting
trace and I copied the contract
from last lecture, the vesting
contract into the code for this
week, and I'm importing it here.
And class week we tried it
out in the playground, now
let's do the same in a trace.
So I find a trace and I use do notation.
So the first thing we have to
do is what the playground does
automatically start the contract in
all wallets that we are interested in.
So we only need two wallets, so let's
start it in wallet one and wallet two.
And for that, we have, a function in
this emulator trace monad activate
contract wallet and it takes a wallet.
So wallet one, and it takes the
contract we want to activate,
which was called endpoints.
It's always called endpoints If you
want to try it in the playground, of
course we could choose another name if
we are not worried with the playground.
Now this monadic function in
emulator trace actually returns a
value, it returns a so called handle
that we can then use with other
functions to refer to this specific
instance of this endpoints contract.
So we use do notation and this bind so
we bind the result the handle to H1.
Now we do the same for wallet two, and
now we can actually call endpoints so we
can call the endpoint, give on wallet one
and that we can do with call endpoint.
We have to specify which endpoint and this
uses some advanced type level Haskell.
So the syntax is at, and now the name
of the endpoint, give in our case,
now we have to specify the handle.
So on which instance of the
contract do will call this.
We did that in the UI in
the playground as well.
I mean, we clicked on wallet
one or wallet two depending
on where we wanted to do this.
So let's, do it on wallet one.
And now we must specify the parameters,
the values we give to this endpoint.
So in the case of give that was the
give params data type, and that had,
three arguments, the beneficiary,
the deadline, and the amount.
The beneficiary should be wallet two
and must be wallet two's pub key hash.
We can do that with pub key hash a wallet,
pub key wallet two, now the deadline.
Let's say slot 20 and the
amount, let's say 10 ADA.
Okay, so this will call
the end line, the endpoint.
Now, for wallet two to grab it
for that to be successful, the
deadline has to be reached.
And in the another thing we can do in
the trace monad part from activating
contracts and calling endpoints is also
waiting either for the number of slots
or until a specific slot, similar to
what we did in the playground as well.
So that is wait until slot.
We can say until slot 20, and
this will actually return a value
namely the slot we have reached.
So in this case 20, but we
are not interested in that.
And in order to avoid the warning,
we can use void from data functor,
which basically ignores the return
value and transit into a unit
and then we don't get a warning.
Okay, now we want to call the
grab endpoint on wallet two.
So that's grab.
The handle now is H2 and the parameters
to grab endpoint didn't take any
interesting parameters, it was just unit.
And finally, let's wait
another slot to see the effect.
And for that we have wait N slots one.
In order to test that let's define test IO
unit and that's just use this run emulator
trace IO with the trace we just defined.
Now in the repl I can invoke
test and we see our trace.
So we see this is the Genesis transaction,
and we see that we started these two
instances for wallet one and wallet two.
So this is very similar to the trace
output you also see in the playground.
So here we invoked our give
endpoint and the transaction
was submitted and validated.
Here we see a log that comes from
the contract, so the log messages
that we do inside the contract
monad inside the off-chain code are
actually well visible in this trace.
And now we reached slot 20 and the
grab endpoint is called transaction
submitted validated we wait until slot 21.
And we get the contract log
message, collected gifts.
We see that wallet one has
10 ADA and 10 lovelace less.
So that's 13 ADA gift and 10
lovelace transaction fees.
And wallet two has roughly 10 ADA
more, but had to pay more transaction
fees because the grab endpoint
involves validating a script,
which is a bit more expensive.
One other thing that we can do
in the trace monad is logging.
We saw that we do see the log messages
from the contract monad inside the
trace, but we can also explicitly log
from inside the trace monad itself.
So for example, if you want to log the
slot we reached here at the end instead
of ignoring the result of wait N slot,
we can bind it to a name, let's call
it S and then we can use extras log
info, it takes a string, reached show
S in the repl and run the trace again.
The result is almost completely
identical, the only difference is this
one line here, user log and there we
see our message reach slot, slot 21.
So the next line as before
is from the contract monad.
Now let's look at the contract monad.
The first thing you notice is that the
type contract takes four type parameters.
W S E and A.
So as in all monads the last
one is always the result type.
So the A is the overall
result of the computation.
I will get to all three of the others
in your time, but I briefly want
to go through them now just to give
you an idea of what they're for.
So the W is like in the writer example
I gave you, so it allows a contract
to write log messages of type W.
So in our example of the writer
was just list of strings, but
here you can specify some W.
And I did say log messages, but
the purpose is not really logging,
the purpose is to communicate
between different contracts.
So the written W is visible from the
outside, so this is a way for our
contract to pass information to other
contracts or to the outside world.
The S specifies the endpoints, so what
endpoints are available in this contract.
And the E is the type of error messages.
So similar to our examples of
maybe and either, in particular
either, we looked at either string,
various string error messages.
But here is more general, so you can
specify the type of error messages, and
then you can throw exceptions and also
catch them inside the contract monad.
So let's do a first example.
Let's call it my contract one, and let's
say we don't want to write any state, any
log messages so we can pick unit there.
Now we also, right now don't need any
endpoints and for that there's empty
so we can specify the empty type.
And that means no endpoints available.
For error messages a popular choice
is text which is a much more efficient
type than string for textual data.
So when you are dealing with large amounts
of texts or texts in general, then text
is normally a better choice than string.
And finally, I don't want interesting
results so I can take unit there as well.
And the very first thing we
can do is simply log a message.
And this is not to be confused
with making use of this W feature.
This is just really logging
as we have seen before so that
we can use contract log info.
And now I need a string or more
general I can use anything that's
serializable that has a toJson instance.
So let's say hello from the contract.
And now the compiler is complaining and
it's complaining that it doesn't know
what the type of this little string is.
Normally, as I explained before,
in Haskell, if you have a
string literal, it's a string.
But I activated this overloaded
strings extension, which as I explained
before, allows you to lose literal
strings for more general texture
types, including text or byte string.
So the complainant at this point
doesn't know what type this is.
Is it a string?
Is it a text?
Is it something else?
And in order to disambiguate this,
I also edit this type applications
extension, which allows me to specify
for polymorphic function like log
info, at which type it is used.
So log info it's polimorphic and
takes arbitrary serializable types.
But I now wanted to use it string and
the syntax that is enabled by type
applications is like, so, so I can use
the at symbol and then the type name.
So that means use this
log info for type string.
And then it's clear to the compiler that
this literal string is indeed a string.
Okay, if I want to test it, I also
need a trace let's call it my trace.
So that's of type emulator trace unit.
And all I want to do is I just
activate the contract, so I
just activate contract wallet.
Now I need to specify the
wallet and the contract.
So let's say wallet one
and my contract one.
And finally, in order to test
this as before I just use run
emulator trace IO my trace one.
Still complaining oh yes,
because I'm ignoring the result.
So I'm ignoring the handle.
So this wouldn't be this activate
contract wallet wouldn't result in a
unit, it would result in a handle, but
I say it should result in the unit.
So as before I can throw
away the result with void.
Okay.
In the repl, let's load this
module and let's try test one.
And as expected, we see
the log message here.
One thing I should still point out is I
qualified log info with contract here,
which tells that it's supposed to use
the log info, from Plutus dot contract.
And the reason I have to do that is
because as we saw before, you can also
log from the trace monad and there's also,
it's also called log info, but that's
define in control dot monad freer extras.
And in order to tell the compiler
which version of log info I
want to use, I qualified here.
So this is the logging from
inside the contract monad.
So next, let's try to throw an exception.
So as I said, we can now have
error messages of type text.
So let's turn this into a
do block and let's throw the
exception before I do the logging.
So this throw error allows me
to throw an exception and of
type E so in our case E is text.
So I can specify a text here.
I can use literal strings because I have
the overloaded strings extension active.
So I can use a literate string here,
which will then be passed as a text.
So for example, I can say, boom.
Okay, and I also have to disambiguate
this because in the emulator also
have the option so I also have to
disambiguate this with it with contract.
Okay, and now it's complaining that
this also has a result, which I'm
ignoring, so let's also do void, fine.
And let's try again in the repl.
I reload, and do test one again.
Okay, now we see the log message
is not displayed anymore, but we
see contract stopped with error and
we see our error message "boom".
So this behaves as expected as you would
expect of an exception that execution
stops at the moment exception has risen.
It's the same as we saw in maybe and
in either as soon as we got the left,
as soon as something went wrong, the
rest of the computation was ignored.
So here, because the exception is thrown
here in line 21, we never get to line
22 and we don't see the log message.
We can not only throw exceptions,
we can also catch or handle them.
We could have done that with maybe an
either as well, but let's just do it here.
So let me just copy this
and call it contract two.
And let's now change the
error type from text to void.
Void is a Haskell type defined in
data dot void that has no inhabitants
stays no value of type void.
This is different to unit unit has
exactly one value, which is also
called unit void has no value.
So what does it mean to have a
contract with error type void?
Well, it means this contract can't produce
any errors, it can't raise any exceptions
because in order to raise an exception,
it would need to provide an error message
of type void, but there is no value
of type void, so this can't happen.
So if we have a contract with an
error type of void we know this
contract won't have any exceptions,
it won't raise any exceptions.
So what I want to do is, I want to
handle, I just call contract one,
but handle the exception and to do
that there's contract handle error.
And if you look at the type,
it takes a contract with error
messages of type E and a handle.
So if an exception is raisen here in
this contract of type E, then we have
a handle that takes an E and turns
it into a contract with a potentially
different exception type E prime.
And the overall result of this
handle error construct is then
a contract with error type E
prime, and the same result type.
So what this will do is it
will run this inner contract.
If there is no exception, the result
will be an A, and that would be the
result of the overall computation.
However, if there is an exception of type
E, then the handle would be applied to the
E and this contract will be run instead.
So in both cases, whether there's
an exception here or not, it
gets something of this type.
So in our example, the E is text
because we will use contract one
here and the E prime is void.
So we need to specify the handle
and the contract we want to run.
So the handle, it takes an
error message of type text.
And now we must write a contract what
to do if he received this error message.
So for example, I can simply log it.
I can use contract log info again, but I
can also just for variety use log error.
And, now the error message and I want
to use a string, something like caught.
Okay, and now I want to use the
error message here, but this won't
compile because error is of type
text and this is of type string.
And, but there's a way to convert from
text to string, that's unpack, that's
defined in data dot text dot read.
So it converts a text to a string.
Note that in this case, I don't
have to specify which type I'm
invoking this as I did here.
Here, I had to tell the compiler
that this little string is a
string and not text or byte string.
Here, the compiler can did use that
automatically because of this unpacks
with nos unpick, as of type string.
So this here must also be of type
string otherwise I couldn't concatenate
the two, so this is of type string.
So it knows I'm invoking
log error at type string.
Okay, and now I need the second
argument, the contract I want to
handle errors for, so my contract one.
Now in the repl, if I
reload and do test two.
I see I don't get an error anymore.
So this contract, contract two
does not fail, but I do get
the expected log message that
I caught "the boom" exception.
Also note that this is the
only log message I get.
So I still don't get this one, so
what will happen is here in, in
contract two when I called handle
error, contract one will be run.
It will throw the exception, but this
won't lead to an exception in contract two
instead the handler kicks in, takes the
error message, which is boom in this case,
and then simply logs it to the screen.
So my contract two will run without
an exception because the exception
risen in contract one is caught.
One other thing I should mention
in the context of exceptions is
that there are other ways in which
they can arise, not just by being
explicitly thrown with throw error.
So there are certain operations that
you can do related to the blockchain
that can result in exception.
Of course, maybe internally
in the implementation of those
operations throw error is used,
but that's opaque to the user.
So for example, if you try to submit
a transaction that can fail and result
in an exception, and the reason is
that something can be wrong in the
way you construct the transaction.
So for example, I mean, the way it
works in Plutus off-chain code is, you
don't directly give the transaction,
instead you specify certain properties
that the transaction should have.
For example, you can say this transaction
should pay 100 ADA to that address.
And then the algorithm
will try to construct a
transaction with this property.
So in particular, in this example, it
will look at the UTxOs that belong to you,
that are in your wallet and find enough
inputs to cover these 100 ADA plus fees.
And if your wallet doesn't contain
enough funds to pay 100 ADA to that
address, then that step will fail.
And then when you try to submit a
transaction, you will get an exception.
Let's talk about the second
type parameter, the S next,
which specifies the endpoints.
So the way this is normally done is
that we define a type synonym call it
something with the word schema in it.
But of course that's just a convention,
so let's call this my schema.
And if I want one endpoint that takes
an int and is called foo, the type is
endpoint then a type level string and
the parameter type, so int this case.
So this is a type, it's a type and
in particular the string is a type.
So, that's why I say type level strings,
so it's a string used at the type
level, so that's some fancy Haskell
extension that's enabled by data kinds.
Okay, and now I can define my contract
three, which is now of type contract unit
again for the first, but now no longer
empty, but now I can use my schema.
I could, of course not have done
this type synonym in it at this point
directly written endpoint foo int.
Now for error messages lists use text
again, and let's say no result type.
So what can I do, we have endpoint and
that just results in a contract for
result type A provided we have this
restriction, this constraint on our
schema type S that has an endpoint L A.
So L is the label, it's the name and A is
the result type, so if our schema S has
an endpoint with parameter A, then this
endpoint computation, monadic computation
will give us a contract that results in
A, so I have to specify which endpoint.
So that's the same at here again, but now
it's specified by its label, by its name.
So foo in our case.
And so this is a monadic computation
that will block contract execution
and wait for our value to be provided
in our case a value of type int.
Once that value is provided from the
outside, this results in that provided
value and we can bind against it.
So what this will do this
contract, it will block until
from the outside, this endpoint is
invoked and provided with an int.
Int because we said it would be an int.
And at that point it will continue and N
will be bound against the provided int,
so to try it out, we can use contract log
info again N, N is serializable so we can
just use N there and the compiler knows
it's an int, so we don't have to tell it.
So in order to test this.
Now it's no longer enough to simply
start the contract, because as I
said, if it just start it will block
and wait for the endpoint call.
So this wouldn't do much, so let's
also turn this into a do block.
And in order to invoke the endpoint
from the trace, we need the handle
so I can no longer ignore the handle.
I actually need it, so let's call
it H and then as we have seen
before, I can use call endpoint.
I must say which endpoint, so at
foo then it takes the handle and
I must provide the parameter.
So an int in our case, for
example, 42 and this should work.
If I reload in the repl and call
test three, then we do see here, the
contract has started, then it would
block, but we received this endpoint
call from the outside, from our trace
monad in this case with 42 as a value.
And then we see that it works.
So the contract receives
the 42 and then logs it.
So what do we do if we want
more than one endpoint.
In that case, this type here, the
schema needs to be more complicated.
So we have to specify more endpoints
and we do that by chaining them together
with this so-called type operator.
So a type operator is an operator that
operates on types as the name suggests.
So it takes one or more types
and combines them to a new type.
And in order to do that, we need
this type operator extension.
So we can now specify another
endpoint, let's call it bar,
I don't know of type string.
And, let's just basically
do the same here with bar.
So let's call the string
S and log that as well.
And in our trace, if we want
to try it out, we also have
to call the second endpoint.
So in this execution, the contract
will run, will block here.
Then when this endpoint call
comes, this will unblock and go
to here and then block again.
So if it was second endpoint call.
And now we need the string
Haskell then this should work out.
Let's try it.
And indeed, we get two log messages now.
Here is the contract log with 42 and
here is the contract log Haskell.
I have no idea why we get the
three stars here and not here, but
nevertheless, it seems to work.
So here was the endpoint call on foo
with 42, and we get the log message.
And here is the second endpoint call
now on bar with the value Haskell.
And we also get the second log message.
Finally, let's look at the first
type parameter, the writer.
And, so this W can't be an arbitrary type.
It must be an instance
of the type class monoid.
This is a very important, very
common class in Haskell and,
it has mempty and mappend.
Mempty is something like the neutral
element and mappend combines two
elements of this type to a new element.
The prime example of a monoid is
lists where mempty is the empty
list and mappend is concatenation.
So for example, I can say mempty list
of ints will be the empty list, and I
can use mappend 1 2 3 4 5 6 and it will
combined them, but there are lots and lots
of other instances of this monoid type
and we'll probably see other instances in
this course, but for now let's with lists.
So let's try this.
So my contract four...
one first argument, and it must be
a monoid so let's use lists of ints.
We don't want any endpoints so we can
just use empty let's use text result.
Okay, so we let's start with
a wait of N slots, 10 slots.
We are not interested in the result.
So now the way we write to the
state to this log is with tell.
That comes from the monad writer class
and contract is an instance of it.
So now we need some list of ints.
So for example, the
list just contains one.
Now let's wait for another 10 slots
and do another tell, let's say
the list it just contains two and
let's wait for the final 10 slots.
Now for our trace that
exercises this contract.
It start as before by starting the
contract, now let's wait for five slots.
Now the way we read the state of a
running contract is by observable state.
And as argument that just takes
a handle which we called H.
And the result would be the state
at that time, let's call it xs and
let's log that from the trace monad.
Okay.
And let's do that two more times, the
second time let's wait now for 10 slots
let's call the result ys and log those
and the final time again 10 slots, let's
call the resul result zs and log those.
So this should be like right here
we wait five slots, that's before
the first tell happens here.
So this should be after the first tell
has happened, but before the second
tell has happened and this should be
after the second tell has happened,
but while this is still waiting here.
Oh yeah, I get the warnings because I
should ignore the result here of the wait.
Finally, again, we...
have a test four.
And test it.
And let's check what we get.
So the trace waited for five slots.
So this is the first time we call this
observable state and we get the empty
list, so before we use tell the state
will be the mempty of the monoid.
And as I explained, in the case of
lists, the mempty is the empty list.
So before there has been any tell the
state that we observed with observable
state will be the mempty, the empty list.
So now by slot 10, the first
tell happened where we wrote
the list that contains just one.
So if by slot 15, we
observed the state again.
Now we get the list just containing one.
Wait another 10 slots here in the
middle the second tell happened, the
list just containing two and now we
get the list containing one and two.
So what happens is each tell uses mappend
of the monoid that we are using as W to
mappend the thing to what's already there.
So it starts with the empty list,
then this is concatenated with the
list just containing one, which of
course is still just containing one.
And then after the second tell the
list just containing two, that is
concatenated with what we had until
then, the list just containing one and
we get the list containing one and two.
So this is how this works.
So how the contract can communicate
information to the outside world that can
then be observed with observable state.
For homework.
I created a model week four dot
homework in which I define this type
pay params which has two fields,
a pub key hash and an integer.
Then I defined a schema that has one
endpoint called pay with those parameters.
And I define a contract that has
trivial state, observable state,
uses this schema text error messages.
And how does it work?
Well, I use endpoint to wait for somebody
from the outside, invoke that endpoint.
So, this will block until the
endpoint is invoked, then PP
will be bound to the pay params.
Then I specify transaction by giving
the must pay to pub key constraint.
As the name suggests that,
it's the constraint that this
transaction should pay to a pub key.
So the pub key is the first argument,
I extract that from the first field
of the provided endpoint parameters.
And then the value is the second
argument and so I extract this integer
from the second field of the parameters
and use a function called lovelace
value of, that will return an integer
into a value given in lovelace.
In line 31, I construct
and submit the transaction.
So what that will do is it will
look at these constraints and then
try to construct a transaction
that satisfies those constraints.
So in particular, it must find an input
in the wallet that is large enough
to cover this payment and the fees.
And it might also need to a construct to
change output going back to the wallet.
And once the transaction is constructed
it will submit it to the blockchain,
and then I recursively call the
contract again, which means that you
can call this endpoint over and over.
So, what I would like you to do.
First is implement this paid trace,
so the idea of that is it takes
two integer arguments and then
returns an emulator trace, and the
behavior should be in this trace.
First start the contract in wallet
one, and then do two endpoint
calls to the pay endpoint where the
recipient in both cases is wallet two.
And the amounts to be paid are
given by these two parameters.
So first parameter first endpoint call,
second parameter, second endpoint call.
And after each of the endpoint
calls please wait for one slot.
So that's the first task you should do.
And then, I provide these two
tests where I try this trace with
different values for the arguments.
1 ADA and 2 ADA in the first case.
1000 ADA and 2 ADA in the second case.
If we try the first one, we see it works.
So here we have the two endpoint calls.
And if we look at the final balances, we
see that wallet two indeed has 3 ADA more.
One from the first payment,
two from the second payment.
If however we tried to pay test two,
there would be an exception in line 31,
because wallet one only has 100 ADA,
I'm using the default configuration
and we learned that that means 100 ADA
each wallet has 100 ADA, so it doesn't
have 1000 ADA so it can't construct a
transaction that can pay a thousand ADA.
So once it reaches this line 31 for
the first time, there will be an
exception and this contract will stop.
So in particular, the second endpoint
call from the trace will never do
anything because the contract has
already crashed at that point.
So the second thing I would like you
to do is modify the pay contract,
so that this exception gets handled.
So instead of crashing, it should
be caught and then just logged.
So just produce a log message
that shows the exception.
And once you have done that,
when you invoke pay test two,
this should something like that.
So up on the first endpoint call, we...
It doesn't crash, we just get a log
message caught error, and then the error.
So in this case, it will be
an insufficient funds error.
And the second endpoint call will then
still proceed and in the result we
see that wallet two has 2 ADA more.
So the first one with the 1000 ADA
failed, but the contract kept running,
second endpoint called successfully
transfers 2 ADA to wallet two.