Before I come to the main topic of
today's lecture, I briefly want to
talk about an important point that
was brought up by one of the pioneers
after watching the first lecture.
If you recall in the auction example
that I showed you, I created three
endpoints, start to start the
auction, bid to make a bid, and then
close to finalize the auction and
for close there were two scenarios.
Either there was a bid high enough in
that case when invoking close the token
goes to the highest bidder and the highest
bid goes to the seller of the token.
And if there was no such bid,
then on invoking close, the
token goes back to the seller.
And this pioneer asked the question,
what would happen if the close endpoint
wasn't there and surely the money couldn't
stay forever be locked in the contract.
And that is a really important point
because what you have to realize
is that the blockchain itself, the
UTxOs on the blockchain are just
data, they're absolutely passive.
So in order for anything to happen,
there must be a transaction.
So in order to make progress, in
order to change the state of the
blockchain, there must be a new
transaction being submitted from
somebody from the outside that consumes
various UTxOs and produces new ones.
So only new transactions change the
state, an UTxO it's just a passive
thing, just passively sitting there.
So it will never spring into
action by itself and do something.
So you can't have a smart contract
that sits on the blockchain.
And then at some point
suddenly performs an action.
If you want anything to happen, it must
always be triggered by a transaction
and transactions always come from the
outside from a user, from a wallet.
Therefore we really need this
close endpoint if we want
the auction to be settled.
So, of course, in my example, the
close was manually  triggered, so
I invoke that in the simulator.
Obviously you could write a contract
for the wallet that runs on the wallet
in a way that automatically does that.
So, when we talk about how to
write scripts for the wallet later,
you will see that, that you can
do quite sophisticated logic.
So you could do something that
automatically sleeps until the deadline is
reached in the auction example, that then
automatically invokes the close endpoint
and triggers the close transaction.
But from the point of view of
the blockchain, that doesn't
matter, it's always an external
trigger that does something.
So nothing happens if it's
not externally triggered.
So that's a very
important to keep in mind.
And thank you very much
for bringing that up.
I've explained in the first lecture
that they are two parts, two sides
to a smart contract, an on-chain
part and an off-chain part.
The on-chain part is about validation,
it allows nodes to validate a
given transaction and decide
whether the transaction is valid.
And when it, whether it's allowed
to consume a given UTxO and
the off-chain part lives in the
user's wallet and constructs and
submits suitable transactions.
So both are important topics and we
have to master both in order to write
smart contracts, but for now I want
to concentrate on the on-chain part.
So let's recall the extended UTxO
model where the idea was that we
introduce the new type of addresses.
So, the type of addresses used in the
simple UTxO model is so-called public key
addresses where the address is given by
public key or the hash of a public key.
And if a UTxO sits at such a public
key address, then a transaction
can consume that UTxO as an input.
If the signature belonging to that public
key is included in the transaction.
And what the (E)UTxO model does is
extend this by adding a new type of
addresses so called script addresses
that can run arbitrary logic.
And then when a transaction that wants
to consume a UTxO sitting at a script
address is validated by a node, the node
will run the script, and then depending
on the result of the script, decide
whether the transaction is valid or not.
And recall that they've
two more additions.
So one was that now instead
of just having signatures on
transactions, we have so-called
redeemers arbitrary pieces of data.
And on the UTxO side, on the output
side, we have an additional arbitrary
piece of data called datum, which
you can think of as a little piece
of state that sits at the UTxO.
Finally, we have the context and then I
explained last time that there are various
choices, what this context could be.
It could be very restricted, just
consisting of the redeemer, or it
could be very global consisting of
the whole state of the blockchain.
But as I said in Cardano, it is the
transaction that is being validated,
including all its inputs and outputs.
So there are three pieces of data that a
Plutus script gets, the datum sitting at
the UTxO, the redeemer coming from the
input and a validation and the context
consisting of the transaction being
validated and it's inputs and outputs.
So in a concrete implementation like
Plutus, these three pieces of data
obviously have to be represented by some
concrete data type, a Haskell data type.
And as it happens, the choice was
made to use the same data type for
all three of them, at least at the
low level implementation of Plutus.
So we'll look at that first, but in
real life, nobody would actually use
this low level and there are more
convenient ways to use more suitable
data types for these things and view
we'll come to that a bit later today.
But first I want to talk about this
low level implementation of validation.
So datum, redeemer, and context
all use the same Haskell data
type and we'll look at that first.
This Haskell data type is defined
in the package plutus-core in
plutus-core/src/PlutusCore/Data.hs
and it is called simply data.
And if we look at the definition
of this data data type, you see it
has five constructors and isn't run
of the mill algebraic data type.
So it has five constructors,
Constr it takes an integer and
recursively a list of data.
Then a constructor map that takes
a list of pairs of two data items.
So you can think of it as a lookup table
with key value pairs where both the
key and the value are data again, then
the list constructor that takes a list
of data, the I constructor that takes
an integer and the B constructor that
takes a string or rather a byte string.
And for those of you who are familiar
with the JSON format for example, this
is very similar to something like JSON.
I mean, the constructors are not exactly
the same, but like JSON, it can represent
numbers and strings and lists of data.
And key value pairs.
So it's what I would call, even though
that's probably not an official thing.
I would call a blop type.
So it's, it can basically represent
arbitrary data, which makes it
very suitable for, for our purpose,
because, and I explained the
extended UTxO model, I was always
talking about arbitrary custom data.
We can play with this type in the
repl, so I'm in this week's code folder
and I fire up a repl with cabal repl.
Now, in order to get access to the
data type I can import Plutus Tx.
It wasn't defined in Plutus
Tx, but it gets exported or
re-exported from Plutus Tx.
So if I do colon I for info and
ask for information about the data
type, then I basically see the same
that we just saw in the source code.
And here we also see where
it is actually defined.
Now I can play with this so I can
try to define values of this type.
So for example, I can use the
I constructor with an integer.
So, I 42 that can ask for the type,
and that is indeed of type data.
If I want to use the B constructor,
I need a byte string and the easiest
way to quickly get a byte string is to
activate an extension at GHT extension
that's called overloaded strings.
And what that overloaded strings
extension does, normally in Haskell
literal strings are of type string,
the Haskell string type, which is just
a synonym for lists of characters.
But with this extension I can
use literal strings for other
string like types as well.
And one of those string like
types is the byte string type.
So now that I have this extension,
I can now use the be constructor,
for example, Haskell, and I get
again something of type data.
And of course I can also use the
more complex constructors like map.
So if I have map, now I need a list
of pairs of data, key value pairs.
So for example, one key could be I
42 and the value could be Haskell.
And the key can also be more complex.
So I can, for example,
use the List constructor.
I don't know, I 0 and as value I 1000
and again, I get something of type data.
In order to write our first validator,
I create a new Haskell module, I called
it gift and I more or less just copy
pasted all the language extensions and the
imports from last week's auction example.
Now let's write the validator and of
course the validator itself in the end
will be a script living on the blockchain
in Plutus core, low level language based
on the Lambda calculus, but we don't have
to write Plutus core, we'll write Haskell.
And I will explain later how we convert
that Haskell into Plutus core script.
So we write a Haskell function
that represents our validator.
Let's call it make validator.
So what is the signature of this function?
As we know from the UTxO model, these
validation scripts, these validators
get three pieces of information,
the datum, the redeemer, and the
context, the datum comes from the
output that is being consumed.
The redeemer comes from the input
that is consuming, and the context
is the consuming transaction
with all its inputs and outputs.
And as I just said, at this low level,
all three types, datum, redeemer and
context are represented by the data
data type that we just looked at.
So this will be a function that takes
three arguments, all of type data.
And it so happens that the first one
is the datum, the second one is the
redeemer and the third one is the context.
So now what is the return type?
And that is somewhat surprising it's unit.
So this opening closing parentheses
it's the unit type in Haskell.
It's a built-in type and it is similar
to the void type in mainstream languages
like C# or C or Python or Java.
And this type, the unit type only has
one value, which is also called unit.
So if we go back to the
repl, start up a new repl.
And let's load this module I called gift.
So there's this value, it's
also called unit and it looks
exactly like the type unit.
And if I ask for the type and it's of
type unit, and that is the only value.
So that means this type or value
of this type doesn't carry any
information because there's only
exactly one value of this type.
Now, if you are somewhat more familiar
with Haskell, you will be surprised
about this signature because in
Haskell it's very rare that we have a
function with a return type of unit.
In other, in mainstream programming
languages, you often see functions or
procedures with the result type of void.
And the value of such functions
lies in the side effects.
The end result is not interesting
avoid result or in the Haskell
case, a unit result carries
no information as I just said.
We know what the result of the
function will be, it will be unit.
So why would you bother
writing such a function.
Now in other languages, the reason
is that in other languages functions
can have arbitrary side effects.
So a function with return type unit
in Java, for example, could write
something to the screen or do networking
or access the hard drive or whatever.
In Haskell that's not possible,
not with the signature.
That would be indicated by an IO to
indicate that it has side effects I'll
get to that a bit in a later lecture.
So this is very unusual and the
way it works is there's one thing
that a Haskell function can do
apart from returning a result.
And that is, it can have an error
or an exception, it can fail.
So the way validators work at this
low level is that if there's no
error, then validation passes and
if there's an error, then it fails.
So in order to write the simply most
validator possible, we can write a
validator that completely ignores
all three inputs and always passes.
So we can ignore by using underscores
for the inputs that indicates
that we don't care about the
value and we simply return unit.
So this is arguably the simplest
validator you can possibly write, it
completely ignores its three arguments.
It doesn't care about the datum,
it doesn't care about the redeemer,
it doesn't care about the context
and it immediately returns unit
without having or producing an error.
So that means it always passes, it
doesn't care what datum, redeemer
contexts are, it always passes validation.
And what does that mean for the
corresponding script address?
So recall, a script address is more
or less the hash of the validator.
So I'll show in a second, how we turn this
Haskell function into Plutus core script.
And then if you take the hash
of that script, you get the
address, this script address.
So what would it mean to have an
output sitting at this script address?
Well, would mean that arbitrary
transactions can use that output as input.
Arbitrary, because it doesn't matter
what redeemer is used, it doesn't matter
what datum was used at the output, and
it doesn't matter what structure the
transaction that consumes that input has.
So that's why I call this module gift,
because if anybody sends funds to
this script address, then anybody else
can immediately consume that output
and use it for their own purposes.
So if you send ADA to
this address, it's a gift.
Anybody can immediately take it.
We should check in the repl, we
should reload and let's ignore the
warnings, they are just unused imports.
So we don't get an error.
We should always frequently switch between
the repl and the editor and save our work
frequently and try to load it into the
repl to see that everything is still fine.
It's a nightmare if you write hundreds
of lines of code without ever checking
whether compiles and then you get
hundreds or thousands of compiler errors.
So ideally your program should always
compile, so I made it a habit to very
frequently save my work and checking
the repl whether it still compiles.
Now that we have defined this Haskell
function, we want an actual validator,
and that is of type validator.
And in order to get the validator,
we have to compile this function
to Plutus script and take this
script to create a validator.
So let me first write
down how we can do this.
And that uses an advance Haskell
feature called template Haskell.
And I'll explain it in a minute, but
the good news is that the pattern
how this is used in order to work
with Plutus is always the same.
So you don't really have to
understand the intricacies of
template Haskell in order to use it.
It's more or less always a
copy paste of the same pattern.
Okay, let's first look
at the types in the repl.
So I start the repl again with cabal
repl and load the module with colon
L module name, and now I need to
import ledger scripts and Plutus Tx.
Now let's first look at the
type of make validator script.
Okay, so it produces a validator, which
is what we want, but it takes something
that's of type compiled code parameterized
by data to data to data to unit.
So this already looks promising
because this is the signature
of our make validator function.
So that, I mean, as the name suggests,
this type indicates, is the result of
compiling a Haskell function of this type.
So let's check what
the type of compile is.
That looks a bit scary, but it's mostly
because of these qualifications here.
So what this says is it takes an
expression of type A and compiles it into
something of type compiled code of type A.
So in our case, we apply this way
is data to data to data to unit.
So we must somehow plug in
something of this type, the
syntax of something of this type.
And we get out the syntax of
something of type compiled code A.
So now what's this syntax business.
This is where template Haskell comes in.
So template Haskell does what
other programming languages
solve with macro systems?
So macro, what's a macro?
Macro is something that gets
expanded before the compiler runs.
So it's basically at compile time,
macros get somehow evaluated and expended
into code, that's then inserted next to
the code that the user manually typed.
And then the compiler
is run over all of that.
So the user code and the expanded macros.
So it's a way to basically
generate code at compile time.
So macros are another expression for
macros is programs that write programs.
And in Haskell, this is
done with template Haskell.
So template Haskell allows you to, to
write Haskell functions that produce
other Haskell functions or Haskell types
or general Haskell expressions and insert
those into the source code and then
run the compiler over that, to compile
the program and then actually run it.
Right, and so these expressions,
this syntax stuff this is
the type of Haskell code.
So something of type expression A, if you
have Haskell for example, of type Int,
if you have an Int then exp Int would be
a piece of code that represents an int.
Okay, so if we need a piece of code that
represents something of type data to
data to data to unit, I mean, we have
our make validator function, but that
is a Haskell function, it's not code.
So somehow having this function,
we must get our hands on the
code of that function, the
actual syntax, the syntax tree.
And this is what these so-called
Oxford brackets are for.
So they allow us to quote
the technical term is quote.
So having some Haskell expression,
we can quote it using these brackets
to get at the underlying syntax tree.
Okay, so this is the first part.
So we have our make
validator Haskell function.
We put it in these Oxford brackets.
So the result of that is the
syntax tree defining this function.
So you, in principle, you can imagine that
the result of this is something like this
string that defines the extra function.
It's not really a string, it's a more
complicated data type, but you can
sort of think of it like that, that
this is now this piece of source code.
Okay, and that is exactly what the
compile function expects, and it compiles
it and produces another syntax tree.
But now Plutus core syntax.
So outcomes, basically the syntactical
representation of the compiled make
validator function now in the programming
language Plutus core, but this make
validator script doesn't expect
syntax, it expects an actual script.
And this is now what the
double dollar is for.
That is in a way the opposite
of the Oxford brackets.
So the Oxford brackets take an expression,
a Haskell expression and convert it
into a syntax tree of that expression.
And the dollar dollar is a
so-called splice and it takes a
syntax tree and splices it into
the source code at that point.
So this here gives us basically
the Plutus core syntax tree.
And by using this dollar dollar, in the
first pass of compilation before the
actual compiler runs, this will run.
So we get the Plutus core syntax
and then you can imagine that, at
this point where the dollar dollar
is, this syntax will be spliced in.
So that is as if we had hard-coded
instead of this, if we had hard-coded
the correct Plutus core expression
at this point in the source code.
And then the make validator
script function takes this
and turns it into a validator.
But as I said, you don't really
have to understand it because
it's always the same pattern.
We will see somewhat more complicated
pattern for so-called parameterized
script in a later lecture.
But once you have seen a couple
of examples, it always follows the
same pattern, but still might be
good to understand what's going on.
So we have this  Haskell function, it
has the logic, use the Oxford brackets
to convert that into a syntactical
representation of this function.
And compiler takes its syntactical
representation of that Haskell
function, turns it into syntactical
representation of corresponding Plutus
core function, and then the dollar
dollar takes that Plutus core and splices
into the source code at this point.
And then it is as if we had manually
type make validator script, and then a
complicated expression for Plutus core.
And that then turns that into a validator.
Unfortunately, there's one
additional thing you have to do.
Normally these Oxford brackets
don't allow you to reference
definitions outside of them.
So normally you have to inline
all your code into these brackets.
So in our case with this extremely simple
validator, that wouldn't be a problem.
We could easily not have defined
this make validator function.
And just inline here in the
brackets wrote this expression.
But of course you can imagine that
realistic Plutus validators will be much
more complicated and you will also want to
use helper functions or maybe even library
functions that are defined elsewhere
in order to avoid code duplication.
And you want to maybe reuse
pieces of code also in the
off-chain part of your contract.
So you don't want to inline
everything into these brackets.
You want to have separate definitions
of the validator and helper functions.
And normally that wouldn't be allowed,
but we can fix this by adding a so-called
pragma to our make validator function.
And that's the inlinable pragma.
And as argument it takes the name
of the function we want to make
inlinable, so make validator in our
case and this curly brackets minus
hash hash minus curly brackets.
This is just a syntax how
you do pragmas in Haskell.
So by adding this, we allow the compiler
to inline the definition of make
validator inside these brackets, these
Oxford brackets, and then it's fine.
And we would do the same for helper
functions that are may be referenced
in the make validator function.
So if you look at the source
code of Plutus, then in certain
libraries, especially in the
Plutus prelude, you will see this
inlinable pragma all over the place.
Virtually every function there has that.
And that is always a good indication
that those functions are meant to be
used in validators, in on-chain code.
Because everything that's supposed to be
used in on-chain code needs this pragma.
If you go back to the
repl and type validator.
Then it seems to work, but I mean, we
don't see much because where the Plutus
core script is, it's just indicated
with this word script, but we can
ask for the definition of validator
and we see it's just a newtype repl
around the script, so that we can
get access to with get validator.
So let's try this if
we have get validator.
Okay, that's also not very enlightening,
we just see script, but if we ask
for information on script, you see,
we can unwrap that with unscript
to get something of type program.
So let's try this.
And we see something.
I mean, it looks very complicated
and those of you who have seen Lambda
calculus before spot that this is some
version of the Lambda calculus that
uses De Bruijn index for variables.
But I mean, here you can see the
actual honest to god Plutus core
script in this representation.
So it worked, we did compile something.
We did compile our make validator
function and turned it into Plutus core.
So now we have our first validator,
given this validator, we can
create values of two related
types that will also be important.
One is validator hash.
So as the name suggests, it's basically
just the hash of the validator and we can
turn our validator into a validator hash
by using this validator hash function.
So I call the result valHash
and also given the validator,
we can turn it into an address.
So this is a real address
on the blockchain.
So we no longer only
have pub key addresses.
We also have script addresses
and this is how you get it.
So we apply the function script address
to the validator and you get an address.
So let me reload and see
whether you see anything.
Okay, so the val validator
hash indeed looks like a hash.
Yeah, script address.
Okay.
And we see this is more or
less just given by this hash.
So the so-called script credential
is just this validator hash.
And then there are other informations
in a, in an address we see that
is something taken related.
So an address can also always
contain staking information so that
it steaks to a given stake pool.
But we see essentially this
script address just consists
of the hash of the validator.
And it is important to keep in mind
that most of this code is boiler plate.
So the actually business logic, the
validation logic in this example is just
in this line where we say validation
always succeeds, no matter what
datum or redeemer or the transaction
that spends it are or look like.
Then the rest you will see in this form
or very similar in all Plutus code.
So the way to take this Haskell
function that gives the business logic
of validation and turns it into an
actual validator by compiling into
Plutus core script, and then how
to take that validator and turn it
into a validator hash on address.
So this is just boiler plate, the
only interesting line is line 34.
Now, of course, in order to try
this, we also need an off-chain part.
And because the focus of this lecture
is on validation on on-chain Plutus
and not on off-chain Plutus I've
already prepared this, so this is that.
And I don't want to go into any
detail, but just briefly go over it.
So this type definition defines
the so-called endpoints.
Endpoints are ways for the user
to trigger something and enter
data, give input parameters.
So in this case, I want two
endpoints, give and grab.
Give takes an integer parameter, grab
doesn't take any parameters, which is
representative by giving a unit parameter.
So the idea is that somebody can
send money, ADA to the script address
we just defined and the integer
argument specifies how many lovelace.
And the grab endpoint is for people that
want to spend such addresses so that
will just look for all UTxOs sitting
at this give address and creating a
transaction that grabs all of those
and sends them to the user wallet.
The next I define, the actual
behavior of these two, give and grab.
So give taking the integer amount of
lovelace, I want to put at that address.
So I create the transaction
by specifying constraints.
So this says, must pay to other script.
So this transaction should have an
output at a script address, which
is given by the validator hash.
So this is our script
address that we just defined.
And this is one of the points where
you need this validator hash with a
given datum so because of how we define
our validator, the datum is completely
irrelevant, but I must specify one.
So I just picked an arbitrary one.
And then I must specify how much funds.
So ADA dot lovelace value of takes an
integer and converts it into lovelace.
So this says the transaction
must pay this many lovelace to
that script with this datum.
And this line submits that
transaction, this line waits for
confirmation of the transaction
and that line logs information.
So in the playground, for example,
we can, can see these log messages,
so that just logs the line made a
gift of so-and-so many lovelace.
Now the grab endpoint, no parameters.
This line looks up all UTxOs
sitting at this address.
So this is our script address,
so this will find all UTxOs
that sit at that script address.
Then this line gets all their
references, references to these UTxOs.
Then I need a so-called lookups in
order to tell the wallet basically
how to construct the transaction.
So I tell it where to
find all those UTxOs.
And I also inform it about
the actual validator.
Remember I explained earlier, if
you want to consume an UTxO sitting
at the script address, then the
spending transaction needs to
provide the actual validator code.
Whereas the producing transaction
only has to provide the hash.
So this grab is now a spending transaction
because I want to grab all the UTXOs.
So I must somehow include the actual
validator in that transaction.
This is what that line does.
And then I define the transaction
again, giving constraints.
So in this case I have a list
of constraints, one for each
UTxO that are found here.
So for each UTxOs sitting
at this give address.
I say, okay, the transaction I'm
constructing must spend that UTxO
and I must give a reference to it.
I must provide a redeemer.
And again, the redeemer gets
ignored by our validator, so I can
do something completely arbitrary.
So I pick this one here and that's it.
So this line basically says,
okay, construct a transaction
that spends all those script
outputs sitting at this address.
Then there's a variation of the submit Tx
I used in line 78, submit Tx constraints
with, that also takes these lookups.
So that allows the compile allow the
wallet to construct a transaction that has
a necessary information, how to find those
UTxOs and the actually validator script.
Then again, I wait for a confirmation
and I log a message collected gifts.
And finally, I put it all together
in these endpoints function.
And that basically says, okay the
select is  it offers the users choices.
So this means make available, give prime
or grab prime, and then afterwards recurs
and do the same over and over again.
And give prime in principle just uses our
give that we defined above, but recall
the give needs an integer argument.
And this endpoint give, operationally what
it does is it will block execution and
wait for the user to provide an integer.
And once that is provided, execution
will continue and will pass on this
integer argument to this give function.
And similar for grab, except that grab
doesn't expect any arguments so this
will just block until the user unblocks
it and then run the grab function.
And because of this select that
means at every point in time,
we have these two options.
We can either provide an integer
and trigger the give or we can not
provide anything and trigger the grab.
And after the give or the grab
has finished, we are again
present with the same choices.
So this wraps up all the
functionality we want for this
example in this one function.
And then there's some boiler
plate to generate schema for
that in this make no currencies.
So that in the playground
we have ADA available.
Let's test this in the playground.
So I started a local playground,
as I explained in the first
lecture and copy pasted the code
into the editor and compile it.
And simulate.
Okay.
Let's use three wallets and then give
each, I don't know 10 ADA to begin with.
So 10 million lovelace.
And let's say that first, both wallet one,
and wallet two invoke the give endpoint.
So see this give and grab that's exactly
the two endpoints I defined in my
off-chain code in the endpoints function.
And the playground picks that
up and renders a UI for those.
So I must specify how much, so let's
say wallet one gives four ADA, 4
million lovelace, and wallet two 6 ADA.
Okay, then let's wait one block
to give those a chance to be
incorporated into the simulated
blockchain and now wallet three grabs.
So grab doesn't take any parameters
and let's wait again for one block
to allow the grab transaction
to get onto the blockchain.
Now evaluate.
Ok and we see five
transactions, four transactions.
So the first one is as I explained
last time, always there that's
the Genesis transaction that
distributes the initial funds.
We can see that here.
So that gives 10 ADA
to the wallets 1, 2, 3.
Now these two are the give transactions
and they both happen in the same
slot, in slot one, because I
didn't put a wait in between those.
And the grab happens in slot two.
So let's look at the first one.
This happens to be the give of wallet two.
So the other one is
the give of wallet one.
So we see the order here doesn't
reflect the order in which
we did it in the simulator.
Which makes sense because in
the real blockchain is also
indeterministic, it depends on the
timing between those two wallets.
Okay.
So wallet two, so the input is the one
UTxO that wallet two had, the, that
comes from the Genesis transaction,
the 10 ADA, and then there are some
fees, 10 lovelace in this case, then
this is what goes to the script.
No, sorry.
This is the change, so 4 ADA minus fee go
back to the wallet and this is the script.
So this is our shining new
script address that we got.
Remember we defined the validator
and then hashed it and the hash of
that at the hash of the validator
is more or less the script address.
And we see that now 6 ADA
sits at that script address.
If you look at the other give,
it's very similar except now it's
wallet one and set of wallet two.
And the amounts are different because
here we only gave four ADA to the script.
So six ADA minus fee are change.
And finally grab, so the off-chain code
scan the blockchain for UTxOs sitting at
the script address and found those two.
And uses both of them as input
and then has to pay some fees,
in this case significantly
higher than just 10 lovelace.
This is because now scripts
are actually executed.
So script execution makes it more
expensive the transaction, but I
don't know whether those costs are
realistic yet, probably they are not.
But we do see that having
scripts that need to be
validated has an effect on fees.
The amount would probably still
change until it's fully calibrated.
And the sum, so the four and the six
ten minus fees go to wallet three.
So wallet three successfully
grab those two UTxOs.
Use them as input for this transaction.
And the output is to
wallet three's own address.
If we scroll down, let me see how
many balances are there in the end.
So we see wallet one ends up with six
more or less, wallet two with four and
wallet three with 20, the initial 10
plus the 6 and the 4 that it grabbed from
the donations made by the other players.
We also have logs and trace, I can see
some more detail about the execution.
So yes, that's the arguably a simplest
validator you can write and it's of course
a bit stupid and silly, but it might even
in some situations be useful if somebody
wants to for whatever reason give ADA
away to the community, then in principle,
this script address could be used.
For our next example, I just
copied the gift module that we
looked at just now and do a new
module and I called that one burn.
But right now the code is identical,
so everything is exactly the same.
So the first example, the gift example
was a validator that always succeeds.
It ignores its three arguments
and always succeeds by
returning unit unconditionally.
So in this example, in the burn
example, I want to do the opposite.
A validator that again ignores all its
three arguments, but then always fails.
So how do we do failure in
Plutus, in a Plutus validator,
we have error function for it.
Let me go to the repl
and load the burn module.
If I ask for the type of error, I see
that it takes a string and returns
an arbitrary type, but this is not
the error I am using in the code.
This is the standard Haskell error
coming from the Haskell prelude.
So in order to look at the error I'm
using, I must import Plutus Tx, or I must
qualify it with Plutus.Tx.Prelude error.
So this is the one I'm using.
It takes a unit and
returns an arbitrary type.
And this brings us to an important point.
I mentioned before when I explained this
inlinable pragma that whenever you want
to use, a library function or a helper
function inside the validator in order
for the template Haskell mechanism to
work, everything must be inlinable.
So this inlinable pragma has to be
edit, but in the standard Haskell
prelude, of course, that's not the case
because the standard Haskell prelude
is like decades old and nobody had
Plutus in mind when that was written.
So for that reason, the Plutus team
has provided their own version of a
prelude that's suitable for Plutus.
And this is here in, in Plutus.Tx.Prelude,
and a lot of functions types defined
in this standard Haskell prelude have
an analog in the Plutus Tx prelude.
The problem is that normally in
Haskell by default, the standard
prelude always gets imported, you
don't have to import it, explicitly
it always gets imported automatically.
And if that was the case here, then
we would have a lot of name clashes
between names in the standard prelude
and names in the Plutus prelude,
but there is a GHC extension for
that, there's no implicit prelude.
So by adding that, the standard
Haskell prelude does not
get automatically imported.
And by adding this line we import
the Plutus prelude instead.
So that's why here when we just say
error, we don't get the standard Haskell
error that takes a string, but instead
the Plutus error that takes a unit.
If you look down here, I do import
something from the standard Haskell
prelude as well, but that's for other
reasons that have nothing to do with
validation, that is for something the
off-chain code and for the playground to
work, for example, the IO I need to import
so that the playground doesn't complain.
Another thing is that it can be confusing.
I mean, a lot of the definitions that are
in the standard Haskell prelude and in the
Plutus prelude, we have the same signature
and the same behavior, but that's not
always the case and error is an example.
So the standard one takes a string
and the Plutus one does not.
So, one has to be careful, sometimes
code that should work, I mean, if you
have some experience with Haskell and use
some ordinary things from the prelude,
then in Plutus suddenly might not work
anymore or might work differently.
I also noticed that there
are issues with preferences,
sometimes operator precedences.
So arithmetic expression or some
other combination of operators that
would work fine without parentheses
in the standard Haskell prelude
suddenly doesn't work in Plutus and
you have to add some parentheses.
So we have to be a bit careful there.
Okay, but with this one change, we should
now have a validator that always fails.
And if I leave everything as is,
I can try this in the playground.
I replaced the code in the editor
with this change code where
only the one line has changed
replacing unit with error unit.
And my scenario, my
simulation is still there.
I think the playground keeps that
if the endpoints haven't changed.
And we still have the same
endpoints with the same signatures.
So let's evaluate.
Now we see, we only
have three transactions.
So the grab obviously
failed, which is expected.
The give should still work as before we
can send our funds to that new script
address, but it should be impossible
to retrieve the funds from there.
And if you scroll down, you see wallet one
and wallet two have made the gifts, but
wallet three was not able to grab them.
And if we look at the log we
see an error here, wallet error,
validation error, script failure,
so we see validation failed.
In the first example, as I said was
of a validator, of a script address
that allows arbitrary transactions to
consume outputs sitting at that address.
And now we have the opposite
where something sitting at that
address can never be retrieved.
So it's locked at that UTxO forever,
no following transaction can
ever use those outputs as inputs.
And that's why I called it the module
burn, because it's a way to burn your
funds, make them inaccessible forever.
So that also in some circumstances
might turn out to be useful.
One thing that's somewhat unsatisfactory
is that we don't see why a validation
failed, we just get this evaluation error.
So there's a way around this, a
variation on the error function.
So if we check the type of Plutus
Tx prelude trace error, that takes
a Plutus string and produces an
error and results in arbitrary type.
So one thing we can do to somewhat improve
this is to use trace error instead.
And then it doesn't take unit, it takes
a string, so we can use a literal there.
So for example, let's just say "Burnt!".
In order for this to work, we have to
use this overloaded strings  extension
that I explained earlier when we
wanted to produce a byte string.
As I said, normally string literal
only produces a Haskell string.
So if we wanted to also produce a
Plutus string, you also need this.
So let's try again.
Okay, now it compiles.
I replaced the code in the
editor and evaluated it again.
Here again only get three transactions,
but now if you scroll down we see here in
the error message that this log string,
the string we defined in the code is now
visible here in the playground trace.
So we get some information what went
wrong, at least in the playground.
As our next example, let's
write a validator that does not
completely ignore all its arguments.
So let's say we want a validator
that expects a specific redeemer.
So we do here about the redeemer
and recall the first argument is the
datum, the second is the redeemer
and the third is the context.
So the redeemer is this one.
So let's call it R and let's say
validation should pass if the
redeemer is I 42 (Integer 42).
So using this guard so we can say
if it is I 42, then we return unit,
so it passes and otherwise it fails.
Ok, let's see whether it
compiles, it does not.
Oh, yeah...
I must, again, I copied the
original gift, so I must again
have this overloaded strings.
Okay.
So far so good.
Now we should also change the off-chain
code in order to try it out, because
I would like to try it out with the
correct redeemer and also with the
wrong redeemer and see that in the one
case it passes and the other it fails.
And I think the easiest way to
do is to also provide an integer
argument to the grab endpoint.
So here, let's call that N and
then instead of hard coding the
redeemer to I 17, I just use I N.
And then I also have to change this
here, because now it also has an
argument, so I have to pass it onto grab.
Okay, that compiles.
Now, if I go to the playground and I
replace the code in the editor with
our newest version and compile, and
now we see that the scenario I prepared
for the give and the burn is gone.
And that is because now
the endpoints have changed.
Now the grab endpoint suddenly
takes an integer parameter.
So in that case, this is gone and
I have to redefine the scenario.
I think in this case, it's enough
to just use two wallets, but let's
increase this to 10 ADA each again.
Okay, let's say wallet
one gives maybe three ADA.
We wait one block.
Now wallet two grabs and let's
first use the wrong redeemer.
So for example, 100 and wait
again, and let's try it out.
And we expect grab should fail because
this now uses as redeemer I 42 and
validation will fail in that case,
it should only pass if it's I 42.
Indeed, we only have two transactions.
So this is the Genesis transaction and
the give transaction but grab failed.
If we look, so, wallet one gave the
three, but wallet two didn't get them.
If we look at the trace, we see validation
error, wrong redeemer as expected.
Now, let's go back and change
the 100 to 42 and try it again.
And now it seems to have succeeded, we
see the third transaction, indeed wallet
two able to get three ADA minus fees.
We also see this here in the
diagram, wallet two now has
13 and the error is gone.
So that's the first example of a
validator that actually looks at
at least one of its arguments.
So in the next example, I want to
show how, instead of using this
low level Plutus, the untyped
version we can use a typed version.
So I copied the example that we just
looked at into a new module called typed.
And this is just the
validator we just saw.
And all these three arguments are of the
same type data and that is really very
unpleasant and very unHaskell like it
almost feels like programming in a untyped
language like JavaScript or Python.
And what we would like
is strong types here.
So that only redeemers and datum that
actually make sense are expressible.
And it's especially bad with his third
argument, the context, because even
though it's easy to imagine that you can
somehow encode a transaction into his
inputs and outputs into this data type,
it's not at all clear how that is done.
And it would be very complicated to
understand that encoding and then use it
in the business logic of the validator.
Luckily we don't have to, and nobody
would, instead we would use typed version.
So instead of data, I just
pick a type for the datum.
Let's pick the unit type, which
makes sense because we completely
ignore it in this validator.
And here let's pick integer for
the redeemer and instead of datum
there's a type called script
context, which is much nicer.
And also I explained earlier that it's
very unHaskell like to have a unit
return type and that is also nicer in
the typed version of Plutus, that's Bool.
So it's as one would expect, if the
result is false validation fails and if
the result is true validation succeeds.
Now to convert this into this
version, the easiest would
be to simply say R equals 42.
So if, so, ah...
His Integer is no longer data.
So I can compare it to 42.
And if it is equals 42, the result
is true and validation succeeds.
And if it's not 42, then validation fails.
This however would have the
same problem that we had before.
When you just used error that in the
case of failure, we don't get a nice
error message, but there's a nice
Plutus function call trace if false.
So if...
Plutus Tx prelude trace if false,
and we see that takes a string and
a boolean and returns a boolean.
So the idea is if this boolean
is true, the result is just
true and the string is ignored.
However, if this boolean is false,
then the result will be false,
but this string will be log.
And this is exactly what we want here,
so we can use wrong redeemer again as our
string and then we use this condition.
Oh, okay...
trace if false.
Okay, and that compiles.
Next, we need to adapt our boiler plate,
and this unfortunately in the type version
is more complicated and cumbersome.
So let's look at this, first of
all, we need something that we
haven't used before, we introduce
a dummy data type equity typed
now because of the module name.
And we must provide an instance
of a class called validator
types for this dummy data type.
And the purpose of this instance
is to somehow wrap together
packing packages together, the
datum type and the redeemer type.
So if we give a type instance for the
datum type, in our case that's unit,
and we give a type instance for the
redeemer type in our case, it's integer.
So this basically just makes a
parser out of these two types.
Next we want to compile, and
earlier we use this make, make
validator script function.
Now we use something called make
typed validator, and the result is
no longer a validator, it's of type
typed validator and that takes as
type parameter this type that we
defined here, it's relatively similar.
So first we have to give as a
type argument, this type, this
line is as before more or less.
So we again use Plutus Tx compile,
make validator is again with the Oxford
brackets and the dollar dollar, but now
we also somehow have to provide a way to
interpret this typed as untyped as so the
boiler plate for this looks like this.
So we have another argument where we
again compile a wrap function at the
wrap function uses a function has
provided by the Plutus libraries,
that's called wrap validator.
And that also needs two typed
arguments, which are again, the
datum type and the redeemer type.
So this is also boiler plate
and it's always the same, so
you can always copy paste that.
Now in order to get the validator from
a typed validator, we can use a function
called validator script, and it takes
a type validator and turns it into an
untyped validator as we have seen before.
To get the hash, we could, of
course use the validator we now
have, and then turn that into a
validator hash as we did before.
But there's also more direct way,
there's another function called
validator hash, that's now in a different
module, even though it has the same
name, it's in the typed version of
the script and Ledger.Typed.Scripts.
And it takes the typed validator
and produces the validator hash.
And finally, the address that's as
before, so we take the validator and
apply the script address function to it.
So, admittedly, this example doesn't
really demonstrates nicely why we would
bother with type validation instead of
untyped as we had before, because the
boiler plate is much more complicated and
we don't really see an obvious advantage.
I mean, we save two lines of code,
but it barely seems worth it.
But of course, if you have more
realistic, more complex examples, then
it becomes more and more helpful if
you can use specific types that are
suited to your business case of the
validation logic and don't have to
bother with this block typed data.
And then it becomes much more useful.
So in practice all validation
scripts or other scripts in Plutus
will use this typed version, the
untyped version will never be used.
Finally, let's look at the
off-chain code, that is almost
identical to what we had before.
There's one slight change here in
this line, earlier we had must pay
to other script, but now that we use
typed validator, there are special
convenience functions for the common case
that one script is especially
important in off-chain code.
I mean, sometimes you deal with more
than one, but often the on-chain code
is about one specific script and then
there's this function must pay to these
script instead of two other script.
And that has the advantage that you don't
have to provide the datum as data, but
you can provide the datum with the type
that you used in the typed validator.
So in our case unit, so
I can just use unit here.
Apart from that, I believe everything
else is the same as before.
And if we check in the
repl, it also compiles.
Now we could try that in the
playground, but I think it's not
interesting because the behavior of
this code will be exactly as before.
So if we provide 42, then the grab
will succeed, and if we provide
a different value, then it will
fail, So in the playground, you
won't be able to see a difference.
We have exactly as before.
Next, let's try to understand
how this actually works.
So the typed validators are just this
thin layer on top of the untyped ones
and this wrap function, or rather
the wrap validator function converts
a function of this type of a typed
validator into an untyped version.
And in order to do that, it's obvious
that somehow you need to convert
the datum and the redeemer type
in our case unit and integer into
data and script context as well.
So this wrap basically what it does is, it
takes the data arguments that it gets in
the typed version, converts them into...
in this case unit integer and
script context, then runs the
typed make validator function.
And then if there's an
exception, it will return...
No, no...
If there's false it will throw
an exception and if the result
is true it will return true...
unit.
So we need a way or there must
be a way to convert between at
least unit and integer in data.
And this is done by a
class called is data.
This is in module PlutusTx.IsData.Class.
And this class has two
functions, to data and from data.
So to data, so if a type A is an
instance of this class, then to data
of an A will convert this into a data.
And from data given a data will try to
convert it back into an A, and this can
fail, so we have this maybe type here.
So if it succeeds, we get just the
A and if it fails, we get nothing.
You can try this in the repl,
so let's import Plutus Tx
and Plutus Tx is data class.
So we can look for is data here as well.
And we see more or less the same
that we saw in the documentation.
And in particular, we see that there
are some predefined instances, for
example, int and bool and integer, and
unit should also be somewhere, here.
So this explains why it worked
out of the box for integer
and unit as in our example.
Now let's play with this to
data and from data a bit.
So for example, we can try
to data of 42, the integer.
Just make sure it's an integer and
we get I 42, which is not surprising,
that's what we did by hand before.
So when we work with integers in...
as a data value, use the I
constructor, should also work.
The other way around, so if I do
from data I 42, now I must have the
compile and tell it what type I expect.
So I expect the maybe integer, then
it succeeds, so I get a Just and 42.
In order to see it fail, let's
take another constructor, for
example, the list constructor
with an empty list and that fails.
So this doesn't correspond to an
integer, so if we get nothing.
And we see here that there are some
predefined types that have instances.
And that's, as I said, the reason why
it worked in our example, but of course
this is still not completely satisfactory
because what we really want is we want to
use custom data types that are very sweet
suited for the validator we want to write.
And in order for that to work,
normally we would have to write by
hand instances for the is data class
for these custom types, which is quite
tedious and also quite mechanical.
So we don't really want to do that.
But the good news is we don't have
to, because Plutus also provides an
automatic mechanism to use custom types
and make them instances of is data.
So finally, let's look at how to
make custom data types work with
is data and typed validators.
So I copied the typed module under
the name is data, and let's say
instead of integer for redeemer,
we want a custom data type.
Let's use a simple newtype, my silly
redeemer that just wraps an integer.
And let's try to replace the integer here
where we have the redeemer with this type.
So in order to pattern match, we
can just pattern match against this.
So R is now an integer again.
So this should still be correct.
Here in the type instances we
have to replace the integer
with my silly redeemer.
Okay, this should be fine
here, my silly redeemer.
So that should be it for the
off-chain code, the on-chain code.
Now for the off-chain code, we must
just in the grab instance where we
give the redeemer, we must somehow
now provide the right thing there.
And actually we don't really
know what to write there.
So what we can do is to
data of my silly redeemer R.
So if we now try to load that module.
We do get, okay.
First we get the error
that that is ambiguous.
Let's call it Plutus Tx to data.
Okay.
But now we get the error message that no
instance of is data for this class, my
silly redeemer, in order to fix that, we
could write an instance for is data of my
silly redeemer by hand, which in this case
would prevent if he is straightforward,
because we could somehow reuse the
one for integer, but we don't have to.
Instead we can use Plutus Tx unstable
make is data, which is again, a function
using template Haskell like this,
let's first see whether that works.
Yes.
Now it compiles.
So this is a template Haskell function,
and it takes a type and the syntax to
provide a type is to use two single
quotes in front of the name of the type.
And this will then at compile time, write
an instance for is data for this type
and splice it in here at this point.
So this is as if we manually at this
position here in the source code
had written an instance for is data.
Now actually, we should be
able to try that out as well.
So if we, again, import Plutus
Tx and Plutus Tx is data class,
and now we do something like
to data, my silly redeemer 42.
Then it works and we see it doesn't
just what we might have expected,
reuse the instance for integer.
So in that case, it would
just be I 42, but it uses the
constructor of the data class.
So that's not obvious maybe, but
that's how it, how it's done.
Okay.
So, and this of course works
for other custom types as well.
So using this Plutus as the template
Haskell function unstable make is
data, we can turn custom data types
into instances of is data and then
use them in our validator scripts
and now are typed validators.
In case you're wondering why it's called
unstable, there's also a stable version,
which you should use in production code.
So this is about constructors,
we saw that in this case, the my
silly redeemer constructor was
translated into constructr zero.
I suppose if there's only one constructor
for a data type, it will always be zero.
But if there are several constructors,
it's not so clear in how they are ordered.
And the difference between the
unstable and the stable version is
that the unstable version does not
make any guarantees that between
different Plutus versions, the
constructor number corresponding to a
given constructor will be preserved.
And that of course would be bad because
if you use an older version of Plutus
to serialize something to data, and then
a new version of Plutus makes it in a
different way, that's it in a different
way then it would be incompatible
and you would have version problems
and if you use the stable version,
then you can explicitly specify which
constructor corresponds to which index.
So then it's guaranteed to work between
different versions of Plutus, but
for now for quick and dirty trying, I
always use the unstable make is data.
So let's quickly try this out
in the playground whether it
still works as before it should
be exactly the same behavior.
So I pasted the new code into the
editor and compiled and same scenarios
before first with the wrong redeemer.
And here we now get two transactions
and wallet two didn't successfully
grab, now let's provide the
right redeemer and try again.
Now we have three transactions,
so the grab worked and the
balances are also correct.
So we see that both, the untyped
and the typed version behave
exactly the same, but the typed
version is much nicer to work with.
So to summarize in this lecture
have looked at simple examples of
validators first untyped and typed.
And we started with a validator
that always succeeds, completely
ignoring its arguments.
Then a validator that always fails
again, completely ignoring its arguments.
Then at one, that actually looks
at the redeemer and checks whether
it has a certain predefined value.
Then we turn that into a typed version,
which is the one that will be used in
practice, first with built-in data types.
Then we saw how we can also use
custom data types, but we haven't
looked at examples where the datum
or the context is actually inspected.
Which of course in realistic
examples will mostly be the case.
So we will do that in next lectures.
Finally, let's look at
some homework for you.
I prepared two models,
homework one and homework two.
So in homework one, I changed the
redeemer type to a pair of booleans.
And as it says, in the comment, the
logic should be that validation should
succeed if these two booleans are the
same, true true or false false, and it
should fail if they are not the same.
And so everything should compile,
but I left lots of undefineds here.
And here the logic is wrong, so where it
says fix me, you have to do something.
And the off-chain code which
is not focus of this lecture, I
already implemented correctly.
So, if you look at the playground for
this homework one, then here in the grab.
So this case false, true.
If I evaluate the grab should fail,
but if I have true true or false
false the grab should succeed.
Finally, the second homework is very
similar instead of a pair of booleans, I'm
now using a custom data type, my redeemer
is a record type with two fields called
flag one and flag two both have type bool.
But the logic again should be the same.
Validation should succeed, if these two
booleans these two, flag one and flag
two are the same and fail otherwise.
So in the playground, this looks
very similar, except now the UI
is rendered a bit differently.
So the field names appear here,
but same behavior so this should,
the grab should succeed should also
succeed if both are true, but if one
is false and the other is true or
the other way around, it should fail.