In this lecture I want to talk about
native tokens and how they are supported
by Plutus, how you can use Plutus to
define a so-called minting policy to
determine under which conditions native
tokens can be minted and also burned.
But before I get to that, I have to
explain what value means in Cardano.
When I talked about the
extended UTxO model.
I explained that each UTxO,
each unspent transaction output
has an address and the value.
And then when it was extended
to the extended UTxO model,
additionally UTxO also has a datum.
And we have seen examples of
such datums in previous lectures.
But in almost all the examples we
have seen so far, the value was always
simply an ADA value or lovelace value.
And exception was the first contract
I showed you as an example, namely
the auction contract, because
in that example the item that
was auction, the way was a NFT.
So this NFT was also a
value, which was not ADA.
But we just created this NFT out
of thin air in the playground.
So we just used this playground
feature that makes it possible to start
with other native tokens, other than
ADA that are already in existence.
In the real Cardano blockchain, however,
in the beginning, they are only ADA.
There are no other native
tokens apart from ADA.
So you have to do something to create new
native tokens or to burn existing ones
and in this lecture we'll see how to do
that, but let's first talk about values.
The relevant types are defined in package
plutus-ledger-api and the modules of
interests are Plutus dot V1 dot ledger
dot value, and then special support for
ADA in Plutus dot V1 dot ledger dot ADA.
Let's look at the value module
first a value is defined as a map
from currency symbols to maps from
token names to integers, which
sounds a bit weird and complicated.
So the first thing to notice that
each native token, including ADA is
identified by two pieces of data, a
currency symbol and the token name.
And if we go to the top of the module,
we see that a currency symbol is just
a newtype wrap around to byte string.
And the same is true for token
name, token name is also just a new
type wrapper around byte string.
So we have  these two byte
strings that identify a coin or
in also called an asset class.
We have this newtype asset class, which
is a wrapper around a payer consisting
of a currency symbol and the token name.
So ADA or lovelace will be one
asset class and custom native
tokens will be other asset classes.
And this map from currency symbol
to map token names to integers is
equivalent to a map from asset classes
to integers, which means that a value
just says how many units of each
asset class are contained in it.
Let's start the repl and let's import
the two relevant modules plutus V1
ledger value, and plutus V1 ledger ADA.
Let's also activate the overloaded
string extension so that we can end
up byte strings as literal strings.
Incidentally, both currency
symbol and token name also
implement the is string class.
That means we can enter both of
those as literal strings as well.
Now let's look at some values,
let's start with lovelace values.
In the ledger dot ADA module.
There's a function called ADA, ADA symbol
and this is of type currency symbol.
And that gives us not surprisingly the
currency symbol of the ADA asset class.
And that's just the empty byte string
and there's similarly a function ADA
token, which will give us the token name.
And that is also the empty byte string.
So taking both symbol, currency
symbol and token name as the empty
byte string gives us ADA or lovelace.
And so how do we construct the
value containing just lovelace.
We have seen that before in the
examples, there is a function
lovelace value of, that given
an integer, it gives us a value.
So for example, to have 123
lovelace, we can just do this.
And we get the value and by the way, you
would never construct a value directly
by constructing these maps, instead there
are always helper functions you can use,
one of those being lovelace value of.
So here we see this map, so the
outer map, the map where the keys
are currency symbols has one key
and we don't really see it here,
that's because the currency symbol
of ADA is just empty currency symbol.
Okay, and the value is now a map
from token names to integers.
And we see this inner map here, again
has just one key, the empty string,
that's the token name of lovelace
and finally the value is 123, so
this value represents 123 lovelace.
One thing we can do with values
is we can combine them, add them.
So in the case of lovelace, so let's take
another example lovelace value, I don't
know, 10 and how do we combine them?
Wait, turns out that the value class
is an instance of monoid, we briefly
mentioned monoids in the last lecture
when we talked about the writer monad.
So monoids are things that you can
combine neutral element called mempty,
and you can combine two elements
to a third element with meppend.
But there's also an operator for
that, that's writen like this,
that comes from semi-group,
which is a superclass of monoid.
So doing something like this,
I can combine two values.
So having the value of that represents 123
lovelace and the value  representing 10
lovelace I get a value with 133 lovelace.
So how do we create values
containing native tokens?
There's a very useful function called
singleton, and it's a function that
takes three arguments, currency
symbol, a token name and an integer.
And that will construct a value consisting
of just one asset class given by the
current symbol and the token name and
the integer specifies the amount, how
many coins of that asset class are there.
So we can construct a value with the
native token, by now first giving a
currency symbol and as I mentioned before,
because we have the overloaded string
extension activated, I can just give
the currency symbol as a literal string.
However that can't be an arbitrary
string, it must be a string
presenting a hexadecimal value for
reasons I'll explain in a minute.
So for example, we can do something
like a8ff, just as an example.
So next comes the token name, that
can be an arbitrary byte string.
And I can just do
whatever for example, ABC.
Okay, and now I must give the
amount, how many coins let's say 7.
And indeed get the value, now we
see the inner outer map, the map
where the keys are currency symbols.
I have one entry, my a8ff and
then the value is an inner map
given in this case only the one
token name ABC and the amount 7.
Now of course I can also combine as
before with this mappend operator.
So for example, I can take this and
combine it with lovelace value of 42.
And let's say I can combine it
with another singleton, maybe
using the same currency symbol
a8ff but a different token name.
100, let's see.
So now we get to somewhat interesting map.
So now in the outer map, we have
two keys, one as the empty currency
symbol, so that's for the lovelace.
And then a second entry that
has the a8ff currency symbol.
In the lovelace case the inner map,
there's only the one token name, the
lovelace token name with the value 42,
but in the a8ff currency, in theinner
map there, we have two entries for the
two token names we now have ABC and
XYZ with amount 7 and 100 respectively.
Let's give this value a
name, let's call it V.
And another useful function is given
a value to extract the amount for a
given asset class that is called value
of, and that, it takes a value and
the currency symbol and the token name
and gives us the corresponding amount.
So if we try that with our V, value of
V and take currency symbol a8ff and as
token name, for example, XYZ, then we
get the 100 back if we take ABC, the 7.
And if we take a token name,
that's not contained in the
value, ABC lowercase, we get zero.
Another useful function is flatten
value, that takes a value and
returns a list of triples, currency
symbol, token name, integer.
So as the name suggests, it's
flatten this, this map of maps
into a flat list of triples.
So if we apply this to our example value
V, we just get a list with three entries.
The first two are these native
tokens, both with the same currency
symbol but different token names.
And the last entry here is
the lovelace, the 42 lovelace.
Now the question of course is why?
Why do we both need a currency
symbol and the token name?
Why don't we just use one
identifier for an asset class?
And why does the currency symbol have
to be built from hexadecimal digits
and can't be an arbitrary string?
And this is where a so called
minting policies come in.
So the rule is that in general, a
transaction can't create or delete tokens.
So everything that goes
in, also comes out.
The exception is the fees, so there's
always a fee and lovelace that has
to be paid for each transaction.
Fees depend on the size of the
transaction in bites, not in value
and on the scripts that need to be
run to validate the transaction.
And the script takes more fees
if it consumes more memory and if
it needs more steps to execute.
So, but if that was the whole
story, then of course we could
never create native tokens.
And this is where minting policies
come in and where the relevance
of the currency symbol comes in.
So the reason that the currency
symbol, the byte string giving the
currency symbol has to consist of
hexadecimal numbers is that that
is actually the hash of a script.
And this script is called the minting
policy and if we have a transaction where
we want to create native tokens or burn
them, then for each native token that we
try to create or burn that currency symbol
is locked up, that's the hash of a script.
So the corresponding script must
also be contained in the transaction.
And that script is executed along
with the other validation scripts.
And similar to the validation scripts that
we have seen so far that validate inputs,
the purpose of these minting scripts
is to decide whether this transaction
has the right to mint or burn tokens.
And ADA actually also fits into this
scheme because remember the currency
symbol of ADA is just an empty string,
which is not the hash of any script.
So there is no script that
hashes to the empty script.
So there is no script that would allow
the minting or burning of ADA, which
means that ADA can never minted or burned.
All the ADA that exists come from the
genesis block, the genesis transaction,
the very first transaction and the
total amount of ADA and the system
is fixed, it can never change.
So only these custom native
tokens can have custom minting
policies and can be created and
burned under certain conditions.
So we'll look at an example of a
minting policy next and see how it
works and see that it's very similar to
validation scripts, but not identical.
Before we write our first modeling
policy, our first minting policy,
let's briefly recall how validation
work that we have seen so far.
So when we don't have a public key
address, but a script address and a
UTxO that sits at such a script address
and a transaction that tries to consume
that UTxO as an input, then for each
such script input, the corresponding
script is run the validation script.
And that validation script as input
gets the datum which comes from
the UTxO, the redeemer, which comes
from the input and the context.
And here we can see the context again.
Recall that's in package
plutus-ledger-api as well in
module plutus.V1.ledger.context.
And so it's defined here and it
has two fields, the Tx info field
and the script purpose field.
And we saw that for script purpose,
everything we have seen until now
always had the purpose spending Tx
out ref, the Tx out ref is a reference
to the UTxO we try to consume.
And this Tx info has all the
context information about the
transaction that is being validated.
Now for monetary policies,
for minting policies.
This is triggered if the Tx forge field
in this one here, Tx info forge of the
transaction contains a non zero value,
in all the examples we've seen so far,
this was always zero, which means in
the transactions we've seen so far,
we never created or destroyed tokens.
But if this is non zero, so we
have a value here, then this
value, as we have seen just now
can contain a bag of asset classes.
So different asset classes
for different currency symbols
and different token names.
So if this is non-zero then for each
currency symbol contained in this value
that is being forged, the corresponding
minting policy script is run.
So each currency symbol is the
hash of a script, of a policy
script, a minting policy script.
And for each value that the piece
here for each currency symbol that
appears in this value in the forge
field of the transaction, the
corresponding script that belongs
to the currency symbol is executed.
And where the validation scripts had
three inputs, the datum, the redeemer,
and the context, these minting
policy script only have two inputs, a
redeemer, and the context, no datum.
That would make sense because
datum sits at something that's
being spent in the output.
And in this case, there is nothing
like that, there's no place where
the datum could possibly sit, so
the transaction will provide the
redeemer as it also provides the
redeemer for all script inputs.
So, for each currency symbol in
this value, with the non-zero
amount, the corresponding minting
policy script will be run with
the redeemer and with the context.
So the context would get as Tx info
the transaction that's being validated
and as script purpose, it will get
minting with the currency symbol that
is currently checked, so who's minting
or burning is currently checked.
So in principle, in this forge field,
in the value of the forge, there
can be several currency symbols.
And then for each of those, the
corresponding minting policy would be run
and the purpose would change accordingly.
So with the appropriate currency symbol.
So let's look at an example of
a minting policy and let's start
with a very simple one, similar
to what we did for validators.
I created a module free and as for
validators, we first define a Haskell
function that represents the policy, and
then will compile it to Plutus core..
So a validator takes the datum,
the redeemer and the context.
And as I explained, there is
no datum for policies so we
just have redeemer and context.
And for this simple one as redeemer,
we can use just unit and then
script context as before and again
bool, so this is the typed version.
So I mentioned before that there's
low level Plutus, which just uses data
or built-in data for all arguments
and then returns unit and failure
is indicated by thrown exception.
But we won't bother with that here
and immediately use the typed version.
And normally for the redeemer
I would need is data instance,
but unit has one already.
So the simple most policy we can write
as the one that always returns true.
So no matter the script
context, we just return true.
So this represents a minting policy
that allows all sorts of minting
and burning for the currency
symbol given by this policy,
Recall the currency symbol
is the hash of the script.
Next, we have to compile this
policy to Plutus script and
I called the result policy.
So it's of type minting policy, and very
similar to what we do for validators.
There's a function called make
minting policy script, and
then comes template Haskell.
And again, we use compile and Oxford
brackets and he had slightly different
to what we do for validators.
So we take our policy, our Haskell
function, but that still has to
be converted to the untype version
that just uses built-in data for the
arguments and a unit return type.
And this is what wrap minting policy does.
So, as before this wouldn't work,
because in these Oxford brackets,
everything has to be inside them.
So we can't have external definitions
except if they can be inlined.
So again, we have to add
this inlinable Pragma.
So let's do that, inlinable make policy.
And once we have the policy, we
can get the currency symbol by
using the function script currency
symbol, applied to the policy.
I should mention that similar to how
we have parameterized validators, we
can also have parameterized policies.
So there could be additional
arguments here in front of that,
the parameters of the policy.
So if I start the repl and load that
module, then the currency symbol should be
available and I can actually look at it.
So this is now the hash of the script
that we got from compiling the Haskell
function that represents the policy.
So that's the first currency
symbol, that's not ADA that we see.
Going back to the editor, this
completes the on-chain part, so
we define the policy as a Haskell
function, compiled to Plutus script.
And we can also derive the
currency symbol from that.
But in order to try it out, we
also need an off-chain part.
So I prepared that already, and the
idea is that we will have one endpoint
called mint, that takes as parameter
the token name and the amount we
want to forge respectively burn.
So if the amount is positively forged
and if it's negative, we will burn.
We only have to specify the
token name because the currency
symbol is given by the script.
So the off-chain function in the
contract monad, it takes these
parameters, then first we compute the
value that we want to forge or burn.
So we use the singleton function
that we saw before, currency symbol
is our shining new currency symbol.
And we extract the token name from
the parameters and the amount.
And as lookups, we have to specify
the minting policy, so the transaction
has to contain the actual script,
the minting policy, the policy itself
for validation to be successful.
And the only constraint we put on our
transaction is using something called must
mint value, which is self explanatory.
So this transaction must mint
the value we computed before.
Then when we submit, so when we use
submit Tx constraints with, with these
lookups and that Tx, then the algorithm
will automatically take care to find an
input in the wallet to cover the fees.
And it will automatically transfer
the minted value to the wallet if it's
positive, if it's negative, it will try
to find sufficiently many tokens in the
user's wallet that can then be burned.
So we wait for confirmation and log
a message that we forged this value.
So then we define the endpoints as
before, so we just call mint and
then recursively endpoints again.
And mint prime is just using
our mint, but using the endpoint
function to actually expose an
endpoint and then feed the parameters
using bind into the mint function.
So this is boiler plate so that we
could try it out in the playground and
additionally, I also defined emulator
trace since the last lecture we know how
to do that, so we don't have to test it
in the playground, we can also just run
it from the console using emulator trace.
So I define a token symbol, TN token name.
Then I run these endpoints, so the
endpoints contract in wallets one and two,
so I start them, then I call the endpoint
mint on wallet one where I use this token
name and I mint 555 coins of that token.
Then wallet two mints
444 coins of the token.
I wait one slot and then I on
wallet one burn 222 tokens.
So in the end wallet, one should
have 333 and wallet two should
have 444 and I wait another slot.
I should still mention that here in
the must mint value function, I'm just
mentioning the value and not the redeemer.
And that is because the case that the
redeemer is of type unit is very common,
so there are special treatment for that.
Let's try this out in the
repl, I have to reload.
Let's try it out.
And we see in the end, indeed,
wallet one now has some ADA bit less
than before because of transaction
fees and indeed 333, this currency
symbol, and that token name.
And wallet two has 444, so as expected.
Let's now try out the same
scenario in the playground.
So two wallets and the
beginning both mint.
Then we wait for one block and
then wallet one means again rather
advanced, but of course the endpoint
is the same and another wait action.
So token name was ABC
and 555, 444 and -222.
Ok, let's see.
Okay, so as always the genesis
transaction distributing the initial
funds, then here we have our two mints.
This is the one by wallet two.
So the UTxO coming from the genesis block
goes in to pay for the fees, which in this
case are 8027 lovelace, wallet two gets
the change and wallet two gets 444 of this
newly minted tokens that didn't come in.
So they have really been forged
in this transaction as is also
indicated here in this forging block.
This is the same for wallet one, exactly
the same, except everything is for
wallet one and it's 555 instead of 444.
And finally, this should be
the burning by wallet one.
So in go some ADA to cover the fees
and the UTxO we got in the previous
transaction with the 555 tokens.
Then in the forge field we see the -222.
And...
so the fees are paid and the
change and the rest of the
token go back to wallet one.
And we also see that wallet
one ends up with 333 and wallet
two with 444 of those tokens.
So the same result that we
saw in the emulator trace.
So this concludes a complete through
of our first monetary policy script.
One that doesn't put any
restrictions on minting or burning.
And we saw in our simulation and in
the emulator trace that indeed wallet
one and two can both mint the token.
And we also saw that wallet one
can burn it again, but of course,
wallet two would also be able to.
So this is a maximally permissive policy
that doesn't impose any restrictions.
Anybody can freely mint and burn.
Any transaction can freely mint and burn.
After the first example where there was
no restriction whatsoever on minting
or burning a token, let's look at
the somewhat more realistic example.
And I copied the free module
to a new module called signed
and want to modify it now.
And the idea for more realistic example
is that minting and burning can only
happen if the transaction that tries to
do that is signed by a specific signature,
by the owner of a specific pub key hash.
So in order to do that, we need
a parameterize minting policy
where the parameter is the pub
key hash we are checking for.
So let's add that here and then we have
additional argument, let's call it PKH.
And now we can't ignore the
script context any longer.
And we can just use the Tx signed by
that we have seen before, which takes
the Tx info and that we can get by
script context Tx info of the context
and the public key we are looking for.
Now, of course, these other definitions
have to change accordingly to
take the parameter into account.
So policy is no longer constance,
it becomes a function that
depends on the parameter.
This is now similar to what we
did before, so we have to apply
this to the lifted parameter.
So this now, because make policy
is now also function, so I must
compose it with wrap minting policy.
Now, again, I can use plutus
Tx dot apply code as before,
and Plutus Tx lift code PKH.
So finally for the currency symbol,
this now also becomes a function that
takes the pub key hash as argument.
And I can simply compose here.
So this is very similar to before
now for the off-chain code.
We don't have to change very much, for
example, the parameters we can leave
as they are, we don't have to add the
pub key hash here to the parameters,
because one of the features of the
contract monad is that you can lookup
your own pub key and minting calling
this mint function only makes sense.
If you actually want to, I mean,
the currency that's given by your
own pub key because otherwise the
minting policy would forbid it anyway.
You should rename this to sign schema.
Okey and now here, so we do have to
lookup our own pub key, we can do that
with contract own pub key, and then we
can align here where we compute the pub
key hash from that, pub key hash pub key.
However that can be shortened, it
doesn't have to, I mean, this is
perfectly fine, but I would probably
combine these two lines to one using
the fact that contract is a monad,
and hence in particular a functor.
So recall functor has this F map function.
So if F is functor and we have a
function from A to B and an F A,
then you can turn that into an F B.
Also, remember the prototypical example
of functor is lists in which case
F map is just a usual map on lists.
So if I have map plus one of
the list one, let's say ints 2,
3, then I get the map 2, 3, 4.
So that's the usual map, but four
lists map is the same as F map.
So I can just as well do F map.
And there's also an
operator version of F map.
So you can write this identical,
like, so using this dollar in angular
brackets, which is often nicer and
reads nicer and particular the dollar
looks similar to the usual dollar
which is just function application.
So that somehow shows  that this
F map is a bit like function
application just lifted into a functor.
So I want to apply that to F being
contract and this F A being own pub key.
So we have something of type
contract pub key, and we have the
function pub key hash, which goes
from pub key to pub key hash.
So using F map it gets something from
contract pub key to contract pub key hash.
So I can immediately get the
pub key hash here if I F map pub
key hash over this own pub key.
And then after all I don't
need this line anymore.
Okay, now that I have the pub
key hash, I can apply it to
the currency symbol function to
get the actual currency symbol.
That depends on this parameter
and I can do the same for policy
here, which now also is a function
that takes the pub key hash.
The rest should be fine, here I just have
to rename to signed schema, here as well.
And I believe the trace
is still perfectly fine.
One thing I forgot is here, I also
have to rename to signed schema.
Let's try the trace.
So everything seems to work, we
get the three forges where the
last one is actually a burning
cause it's negative amount.
And we get the same amounts
again, so 333 in the end on
wallet one, 444 in wallet two.
However, note that now
these are different tokens.
They have the same token name
ABC in both cases, but the
currency symbol is different.
And that is because now we had the
parameterize minting policy and each
wallet applies its own pub key hash to it.
So the parameter is different, so the
resulting script will be different.
So the hash of the resulting script
will be different, which is the currency
symbol, so we get different tokens.
Wallet one can only mint this token and
wallet two can only mint this token.
Because wallet one can only sign for
this one and wallet two can only sign
for that one, the wallet only has its own
signature to use, to sign transactions.
So this is more realistic example, which
might actually be useful in practice.
It's a bit like a central bank where the
pub key hash identifies the central bank.
So it's similar to fiat currencies
like USD, Euro, or Yen where supply
is determined by a central bank.
The central bank can decide to mint
more money or take money out of
circulation to control the total supply.
And this is somewhat similar,
this parameterized minting
policy that we have seen here.
So, wallet one is in
control of this currency.
And can mint then burn and freely, but
nobody else can and wallet two is in
control of this currency and can mint
and burn it freely, but nobody else can.
So it's a bit analogous to, I mean,
this being something like USD and
wallet one is the us central bank.
And so this is like the Euro,
this currency in wallet two is
the central bank for the Euro.
Let's talk about NFTs
next non fungible tokens.
That is tokens that can only exist once
where there's only one coin in existence.
The examples of native tokens that
we have studied so far are definitely
not NFTs because we could easily
mint as many as we wanted of those.
Both in the first example, the minting
was totally uncontrolled, but also in
the second, as long as you are the owner
of the specified public key hash, you
can mint as many tokens as you like.
Now in order to produce an NFT, maybe the
first naive idea would be to actually,
in the policy, look at the forge
field, which we haven't done so far.
All we did look at in the last example
was the signatories of the transaction.
But if you actually look at
the forge field, we could add a
condition to the policy that the
forge value has an amount of one.
But that wouldn't help us, that would
only mean that during one transaction,
you can only mint one token, but nobody
could stop us from submitting as many
of these transactions as we like.
And then again, mint
arbitrarily many tokens.
So that won't do, that won´t
enable us to guarantee that the
given token can only exists once.
A second option, that is actually
been used already on the Cardano
blockchain because native tokens
are available since Mary, which
predates Plutus is to use deadlines.
So we saw in previous examples
and previous lectures, how time
can be incorporated into Plutus
script, and we can do the same,
of course, in policy scripts.
So the idea here would be to, to have
a deadline that only allows minting
before the deadline has passed.
Then if you want to do an NFT, you mint
one coin before the deadline has passed
and then allow the deadline to pass.
And then it's guaranteed that
after the deadline, no new
tokens will ever be minted.
But in order to check that before the
deadline, you only minted one, you need
something like a blockchain explorer.
You must check on the blockchain
that only one of these tokens was
ever minted before the deadline.
You are guaranteed that after
the deadline, no new ones can be
minted, but in order to make sure
that only one was minted before
the deadline, you actually have to
check with the blockchain explorer.
So in that sense, the NFTs that are on
Cardano right now, are not true NFTs in
the sense that the currency symbol by
itself guarantees that they are NFTs.
In order to check that only one exists,
you have to look on the blockchain.
Now using Plutus, it's actually possible
to mint true NFTs, where if you know
the policy script that corresponds to
the currency symbol, you can be sure
that only one such coin can be in
existence without having to resort to
something like a blockchain explorer.
And if you think about how to do
that, you must prevent from there
ever being more than one minting
transaction for the token in question.
So, whatever you write in your
policy script, it must only result
in true for one transaction.
And it must be impossible to do the
same again in another transaction.
And at first, that sounds impossible.
Because why can't you simply do the
same transaction again later, and then
validation should again succeed and it
should be possible to mint token again.
At least if you do it in the same slot,
I mean, we mentioned deadlines before,
so of course times plays a role, but
why can't you simply at one slot issue,
the same transaction several times?
And the key here is that we
need something that's unique.
We need something on the Cardano
blockchain that we can refer to
in our minting policy that is
unique, that can only exist in
one transaction and never again.
And that is a very important
trick, something to keep in mind.
And the idea is to use UTxOs.
Because for the reason how a
UTxO works, UTxOs can only exist
once, every UTxO is unique.
You can never have the same UTxO again,
a UTxO is there and at some point it may
be consumed as input to a transaction
and there can never ever be the same UTxO
again later in the life of the blockchain.
Of course, there could be another UTxO
that goes to the same address and has
the same value and has the same datum.
But that will still not be
the same UTxO in the sense
that will have a different ID.
So what is the ID of a UTxO?
Well, a UTxO is the output of a
transaction, so in order to pinpoint
a specific UTxO, you must pinpoint
the transaction it came from.
Via its transaction ID, and you must say
which output of that transaction it was.
The outputs of a transaction are ordered.
So by specifying the transaction
that produced it and saying which
item it was in the list of outputs,
you can uniquely identify an UTxO.
And transactions are unique, that can
never be the same transaction again.
And because transaction and index
determine the UTxO, this implies
that UTxOs are also unique.
So now of course you can ask
why are transactions unique?
And that is a bit subtle
because they wouldn't be unique
necessarily if it wasn't for fees.
If it wasn't for fees, you could have
a transaction that has zero inputs
and only outputs without value.
So, transactions with no
inputs and outputs where each
output doesn't have a value.
Such a transaction could exist
several times, you could have the
exact same transaction and it would
have the exact same hash enhanced
the except same transaction ID.
But in a system with fees like Cardano,
you can't have such a transaction
because you always need an input
that provides the fees to pay the
transaction fees for the transaction.
And as soon as you have an input,
that input must come from somewhere,
it must come from a previous UTxO.
So basically by a simple induction
argument, you see that as soon as
you have fees, transactions can never
be repeated, you can never have two
identical transactions in the sense
that they have that same transaction ID.
Because they must spend fees and
these fees, because double spending is
impossible, must be different UTxOs for
different transactions and the inputs are
incorporated into the transaction hash.
So if you have two transactions with
different inputs, those two transactions
also will have different transaction IDs.
So that means that every transaction
in the history of the blockchain
is unique, has a unique ID.
And that implies that also every
UTxO in the blockchain has a
different ID, a different combination
of transaction ID and index.
And this is a very important fact
and that is a fact that we can
use in order to create true NFTs.
So the idea here is to name a specific
UTxO as parameter to our minting policy.
And then in the policy check that
the transaction that does the
minting consumes this specific UTxO.
And because of what we just said
once a UTxO has been consumed in this
transaction, it can never exist again.
So there can't be another transaction
that consumes the same UTxO, and this
guarantees, this strategy guarantees
that with a minting policy like
that, there can only ever be one
transaction that consumes this UTxO.
And that is what we want to achieve
in order to guarantee that we have a
true NFT that can only be minted once.
In order to demonstrate the
idea, I created the module NFT.
And in the make policy function, I
now have two parameters, one of type
Tx out ref, one of type token name.
So Tx out ref as the name suggests
references Tx out, so transaction
output UTxO, and token name will
be the token name of the NFT.
There would be various other choices,
for example, I could turn those two
pieces into one parameter, but I also
wanted to demonstrate how to have
scripts with more than one parameter.
So how does it work?
So all ref is the reference to the output
we want to consume in this transaction.
To make sure that this can only
happen once in one transaction
and TN is the token name.
Again, we don't use the
redeemer and the context.
So we have to check two things, that the
UTxO specifies by oref is indeed consumed.
So that's the first condition here that I
delegate to has UTxO, the helper function
and the second condition is that we indeed
only mint the token once, exactly once.
So let's look at the helper functions,
first just the Tx info, because I
need that in both helper functions,
in both checks, now the has UTxO.
If you look at the documentation for
Tx info again, this is now the first
time that we don't just use global
field that applies to the transaction
as a whole, but have to actually look
at the inputs at individual inputs,
because we have to make sure that this
transaction, this minting transaction
indeed consumes the specified UTxO.
So we will use this Tx info inputs
field, which a list of type Tx in info.
And if we check this, we see that
a Tx in info has two fields and one
is called  tx in info out ref and is
indeed of the right type of Tx out ref.
So as you recall, an input consumes
an output from a previous transaction
and this specifies which output.
So going back to the code, any is a
standard Haskell function that checks
whether any, that is at least one
element of a list, satisfies a condition.
So for example, I can
check any even 2, 3, 5.
That will be true because two
is even, but if I changed it
into a one, it will be false.
Okay, so we check that any of these and
this we just looked at, so that as an
input of the transaction, so I is now
the input and we use this function we
looked at in the documentation just now.
So this is now the output reference
that this input I consumes and we check
whether this equals that given UTxO.
So this line checks, whether there's
any input that consumes this output.
So that's the first condition and the
second condition, we actually look
at the Tx info forge field, which
tells us which value has been forged.
Use the flatten value function I explained
earlier, which will turn the nested map
of the value into a flat list of triples,
currency symbol, token name amount.
And we expect that there's
exactly one such triple.
So in this transaction, only this one
NFT should be forged, nothing else.
So in all other cases, if we don't
forge anything, or if we forge more than
one token, we immediately return true.
But if there's exactly one triple,
then we want to check that this is,
the currency symbol is the currency
symbol we are currently validating.
The token name is the given token
name and the amount should be one.
So now there is a slight chicken and egg
problem because in order to check that the
CS, the currency symbol is the currency
symbol we are currently validating,
how are we supposed to do that?
Because what is this currency symbol
we are currently validating, well it
will be computed from first taking
this Haskell function, compiling it to
Plutus script and then taking the hash.
That will be the currency symbol,
but we are in the process of
writing this Haskell function.
So how can we possibly inside this
function already know what the
result of hashing the script, which
is compiling this function will be.
And for this purpose, there is a
special function that works on the
context on the script context, and
that's called own currency symbol.
And this is made for exactly this purpose.
So that when we are in the process
of checking a minting policy, that
we have access to the currency
symbol we are currently checking to
solve this chicken and egg problem.
So this is the currency symbol
that this policy is all about.
And we check that the value we are
forging indeed uses that currency symbol.
And we check that it has the
right token name and we check
that the amount is exactly one.
However, even though this
is very useful in general to
have this own currency symbol.
In this case, it's actually not
necessary because we made sure that
there's only exactly one currency symbol
in the value that is being forged.
Otherwise we would run into
this other case in line 48.
So we know we are in the situation
where there's exactly one
currency symbol being forged.
So we know without even looking at
it, that the policy we are running
right now, will be for this symbol.
So we can actually simplify this
and don't even look at it and
just skip this condition because
that's automatically true.
But only because we are in this special
case where we know there's exactly one
currency symbol in the forge value.
So that completes this function,
the make policy function.
Now we need to compile it to a policy, so
given the two parameters, the Tx out ref
and the token name, we must compute the
minting policy by compiling this function.
This is more or less as before, the only
difference is that now for the first time
we have something with two parameters.
But that just means we
have to apply code twice.
So giving this we have for
function with two parameters, we
apply the first argument here,
the lifted reference to the UTxO.
So we are left with the function with one
parameter, the token name, and then we
apply the lifted token name, and we are
left with something of the right type,
type redeemer to script context to bool.
So once we have our current, our
policy, we can can compute the
currency symbol also as before.
So given the two parameters, we use
the policy function we just defined
and then get the policy and then can
apply script currency symbol to it.
So that concludes the on-chain
part, the policy itself.
Now, in order to try it out, let's
write a off-chain code contract
that can actually mint an NFT.
So let's define a schema with one
endpoint mint, which just takes
one parameter, the token name.
And now we define the contract
that mints given the token name.
So, first we lookup our own public key.
Now we must find a suitable UTxO that
we can consume, that we can pass as
parameter to the policy, and that will
then be consumed in the minting policy.
So we use a function that's available
in the contract monad called UTxO
at and that takes an address.
In our case, we are interested in UTxOs
that belong to us that sits in our wallet,
and there's a function pub key address
that takes a public key and then computes
the corresponding public key address.
So using UTxO at that address,
we now have all UTxOs, list of
all UTxOs that are in our wallet.
And I simply take the first one.
Maybe there could be some optimization
to take one that's large enough to
also cover the fees so that we only
need one input, but I ignore this.
So, if there is no UTxO in our wallet,
then we can't proceed, so I log an error.
If there is one, at least one, I just
take the first one, the head of the lists,
ignore the rest, and now I can proceed.
So this first UTxO that I find in my
wallet will be the one I'm using in
the policy as a parameter for the NFT.
So first I compute the
value that I want to forge.
So I use the singleton function again.
Now I need the currency symbol, for
that I have my cur symbol function.
And now I have both parameters,
the UTxO and the token name.
Token name will be the token
name and amount will be one.
Now for lookups, I need two, first
the minting policy which I provide
here again with these two parameters.
And secondly, I also need
to lookup for the UTxO.
So I indicate that I want to use unspent
output, make the algorithm that balances
the transaction aware of this and spend
output and I just use all of them.
It wouldn't be necessary, it
would be enough to just provide
this one, the oref one, but it
doesn't matter to provide more.
Finally the constraints
from my transaction.
So I want to mint this value val, and I
insist that the UTxO I have picked, the
first one in my wallet must be spent.
So that can be done with
my spent pub key outputs.
Then as before I can submit
the transaction, wait for
confirmation and log a message.
Now the usual thing to define endpoints,
where I use the endpoint function
and then call the function I just
defined, the mint function, then the
usual boiler plate for the playground.
And finally, a simple
emulator trace to test this.
So as token name I use ABC again
and now I activate the endpoints
contract for wallets one and
two with handles H1 and H2.
And call the mint endpoint on both
of them, on both wallets and wait
for one slot and see what happens.
If I reload and run test.
I do see that both wallets end up
with a token, token name ABC, but
the currency symbol is different.
And that is because those two wallets
necessarily have to use different
UTxOs specified as parameter for
the currency symbol, for the policy.
So wallet one will use a
UTxO it finds in his wallet.
And wallet two will have to find
another one, in wallet two as wallet.
So, both are NFTs, but they
are different NFTs because the
currency symbols are different.
And we also get the expected log messages.
So just as a recap, the idea of the
NFTs, the idea to enforce that only one
transaction can mint, is to use a UTxO
as input to insist in the policy, in
the minting policy, that the minting
transaction uses a specific UTxO as input.
And because UTxOs can never exist
again, once they've been consumed,
the same UTxO will never exist again,
this would guarantee that such a
transaction can only happen once.
And if in addition, we enforce that in
this transaction that can only happen once
a value of exactly one coin is minted.
Then we get a policy that guarantees
that we have a proper NFT, where
there's only one coin in existence.
For homework, first I want you to look
at the homework one module, and there,
I want you to implement a Mary era
style monetary policy, minting policy.
So in Mary, it's already possible
to use native tokens, even though
we don't have Plutus and you can
specify minting policies, but
only of a relatively simple type.
And what you can do, is you can
specify signatures that have to be
present in the minting transaction,
and you can specify deadlines.
So you can say that minting must not
happen after the deadline has passed.
And there's more you can do, you
can also combine several such
policies with logical end or.
What I want you to do here in the
homework is to implement a minting
policy that has two parameters,
a pub key hash and a POSIX time.
And the idea is that minting should
only succeed if the transaction is
signed by the corresponding signature,
and if the deadline has not yet passed.
Then you have to implement the
depending things like the policy
and currency symbol accordingly.
Now for the off-chain code,
I already implemented that.
So as parameters for minting, you must
provide the token name, the deadline
and the amount you want to mint.
And then in the mint contract, I
first lookup my own public key hash
as I explained before, then I use
current time to lookup as the name
suggests the current POSIX time.
I lookup the deadline from the parameters
and if the deadline has already passed,
then I just look an error message.
So I don't even bother submitting a
transaction because I know it will
fail any way during validation.
However, if the deadline has not yet
been passed, I compute the value I want
to mint, so just using the currency
symbol, the token name and the amount.
Then in the lookups I must
specify the minting policy.
And finally, in transaction, I need
two constraints that I combine, so
that I want to mint the value in this
transaction and the validity interval.
And recall, normally the rule of
thumb is to make it as large as
possible, but not too large, of course.
So, because in the validation
it will be checked that the
deadline has not yet passed.
The largest interval I can
basically use is to deadline.
And then I submit the transaction,
wait for confirmation and log a
message that I forged the value.
Then the usual, I define the endpoints
in terms of this mint contract
to the playground boiler plate.
And then I also provide an
emulator trace, token name ABC,
deadline beginning of slot 10.
I only need one wallet, I start
the endpoint on wallet one and I
immediately call mint 555 tokens.
And then I wait until
slot 15 or four 15 slots.
So now the deadline wich is
slot 10 should have passed.
So the second minting should fail and
I wait another slot to see the effect.
However, when I try this trace in the
repl and check, then I get an error
for the first minting, and this is
not coming from the log message, but
it's really coming from validation.
So we see evaluation, error,
deadline missed, which is the error
message that I use in validation,
so I was puzzled a bit by that.
And then I finally understood what the
problem is, so the off-chain code is
wrong and the reason is the switch from
using slots to measure time, to using
POSIX time to measure time in Plutus.
So recall that validation works by
checking that the validity interval is
contained in the two deadline interval.
So that's what it means, we must check
that the deadline has not yet passed,
no matter what the current time is, we
don't know for sure we just know it's
somewhere in the validity interval.
So the whole validity interval must be
before the deadline, which means it must
be contained in the two deadline interval.
And that's why here, when I set the
validity interval, I use two deadline
and I thought that's obviously
correct because obviously two deadline
will be contained in two deadline.
However, what I forgot for us that
the underlying transactions, the
Cardano transactions still use slots.
So even though Plutus switched to POSIX
time, the transactions still use slots.
So for example, if the deadline is
the beginning of slot 10, somewhere
in the beginning of slot 10 or
the very beginning of slot 10.
Then this here, this interval to beginning
of slot 10 in the real transaction must
be translated into a slot interval.
And that will be the interval
that goes to slot 10 inclusive.
So all of slot 10 will be in the validity
interval of the actual transaction.
So now during validation that is again
Plutus, this validity interval will
be translated back into a POSIX time
interval, but now because the slot
base interval includes all of slot 10
and that's converted back into POSIX
time, will get the end of slot 10 as
the POSIX time, not the beginning.
And that means validation will fail
because now suddenly the validity
interval is larger than the two deadline
interval, because the two deadline
interval stops at the beginning of
slot 10, but the validity interval
now only stops at the end of slot 10.
So that's a bit unfortunate and
might lead to subtle errors.
So one really has to be aware of
that, that this conversion happens.
So Plutus works in POSIX time,
transactions are based on slots.
So when we go from off-chain to on-chain
code, this conversion happens twice,
the POSIX time gets translated into
slots in the transaction, and then
during validation get translated back
end because lots are of course much
coarser grain than POSIX time,, this
conversion is not perfect, so it's lossy.
So that means if we start with a
POSIX time convert slot and then
back, we won't necessarily get
the original POSIX time back.
So that's what I overlooked.
And let's try to fix that.
I honestly don't know
what the best way is.
One way is instead of using two deadline
to just use a time, that's a bit in
the future from now, and then hope that
we are not too close to the deadline.
So that, that goes past the deadline.
So for example, what I could do is
I use now and add, I don't know,
two seconds, something like this.
So this gives the transaction two
seconds to get to the validating
nodes, which should be enough, I think.
Maybe we could make it five seconds,
I don't know actually, how long it
would take and the larger we make it
the higher, the risk that if you're
close to the deadline, then there's
now plus 5,000 just after the deadline.
But the smaller we make it, the
faster the transaction has to
be distributed to all the nodes.
So I'm not exactly sure what
the best number here is.
Of course not for now, if we just
simulate it, it doesn't matter
because there is no delay, no
network delay, so we could use this.
So I made the same change
in my sample solution.
And if I run the emulator trace in the
repl again, then I get the desired result.
So here in slot one, I mint and it works.
And when I try and slot 15, It
doesn't, but the transaction doesn't
even get submitted, I just get the
log message from my mint contract
that the deadline has already passed.
But now, because I used five seconds,
slack basically, if I tried minting
too close to slot 10, when the
deadline passes, for example, in
slot eight, it would also fail,
it would fail you in validation.
But of course, in a realistic
scenario, the deadline wouldn't
just be 10 seconds in the future.
It would be, I don't know, a day
in the future, so to give you
enough time to mint what you want
to mint before the deadline passes.
As second homework, I want you to
slightly modify the NFT contract
that I demonstrated by making the
token name fix and just fixing
it to the empty byte string.
So we don't need the token name as
parameter any longer, we just need the
UTxO that's supposed to be consumed.
So I want you to implement this and
also the corresponding minting contract,
which you can just adapt from the one we
had in the NFT module, or also provide
a test emulator trace where I just
activate the contract for wallets one
and two, and then call the mint endpoint.
The advantage of this way fixing the
token name is that you don't need any
arguments for the mint endpoint, because
the only argument we had before was
the token name, so now it's just unit.
And if you try this out in the
repl, It works as expected.
So we get the two minting transactions and
wallet one and wallet two end up with a
shiny new NFT, but it's a different one.
The two are distinct because the
currency symbols are different.
And you see the token name in both
cases is the empty byte string.