In today's lecture I want to talk about state machines.
State machines can be very useful to write shorter and
more concise contracts, both on chain and off-chain.
And their support for state machines in the Plutus
libraries that is higher level and builds on top
of the lower level mechanisms we have seen so far.
As a running example for today, I want to implement
a little game played between Alice and Bob.
It's a bit like a rock paper scissors, but even
simpler because there are only two options.
So Alice and Bob both have two options.
They can either play zero or one.
And if they play it while being physically in the same
room, it would be played just like rock paper scissors.
So at the same time they raised their hand and
there's one gesture for zero and one gesture for one.
And depending on what they play, one of them wins.
So if they both use the same gesture, both
choose zero or both choose one, then Alice wins.
And if the choices are different than Bob wins.
Now let's imagine that Alice and Bob can't meet
in person, but they still want to play the game.
So they decide to play it via email
or snail mail, doesn't matter.
Of course, we will later implemented
on the blockchain using Plutus.
But how could that work?
So Alice can send a mail with her
choice, let's say zero to Bob.
But this of course gives a very unfair advantage to Bob
because now he opens Alice's mail and see if she picked
zero and he can simply reply sending one and he wins.
And of course, if Alice instead picks
one, Bob can simply choose zero.
So Bob would always win at least if he's unfair.
So what can we do about that?
And there's a very clever trick that's
often used in cryptographic protocols.
And that's about humid schemes.
So the idea is that Alice doesn't reveal
her choice to Bob, but she commits to it
so that she later can change her mind.
And, one way to make that work is using hash functions.
I mean, hashes are all over the
place in the blockchain world.
I mean, we have seen that, for example, addresses
script addresses are just the hash of the
Plutus core script and a we've seen lots of
examples of using public key hashes and so on.
And what hash functions are?
There are so called one way functions.
So it's difficult or impossible given a hash
to reconstruct the original document or the
original byteString that was hashed to this hash.
So one way we could try to make this work is
that instead of sending her choice to Bob, she
instead send the hash of her choice to Bob.
So she sends the hash of zero.
Which is just some, I don't know, cryptic byteString.
So now Bob sees this cryptic byteString and he
has no idea whether Alice picked zero or one.
So he maybe picked zero and there's
no need for him to use a hash.
So here can just send the zero in Kia text.
And, so now Alice would have won,
but maybe Bob doesn't believe her.
So there's then one additional step that
Alice has to send another message to Bob
where she now sends her actual choice.
And then what Bob has to do is he has to
check whether hash of Alice's claim choice
is indeed the hash he received earlier.
And if it is, then he knows that Alice is not lying
and that she indeed picked zero and that he lost.
But if this hash doesn't match up, then he knows
she's cheating or trying to cheat and he would win.
And of course, if Alice instead picked
one that would work exactly the same,
except that the hash would be different.
So this sounds promising, but there's one
big problem with this, because in this game,
there are only two choices, only zero and one.
So there are only two possible hashes.
They may look very cryptic to
Bob the first time they play.
But, I mean, sooner or later you noticed
that he always sees one of these two hashes.
And then he knows which choice Alice made.
And that's almost as bad as if she
directly sent her choice out in the open.
But what we can do here is that Alice doesn't
simply send the hash of zero, but that she
first concatenates zero with some arbitrary
byteString so called nonce that she picks.
So the way this would work is first
Alice picks a nonce, some arbitrary text.
And then she sends the hash
of the nonce and her choice.
For example, zero to Bob, which
is some other cryptic byteString.
And now it's not always the same byteString,
if you pick zero provided she always
chooses some random unpredictable nonce.
So Bob receives it and then it proceeds as before.
So he sends his choice, for example, zero.
And now in the third message, Alice has
to not only reveal her original choice,
but she has to send the nonce as well.
So in this case, she would send the nonce and zero.
And then Bob checks that hash of Alice's
claimed nonce concatenated with zero is
indeed the hash she originally received.
And if it is, he knows he lost.
And if it does not, then he
knows she tried to cheat him.
So this works very nicely and this is what we
will try to implement in Plutus on Cardano.
So first we'll use what we have seen so far
and then we'll see how by using state machines,
the code can be much clearer and much shorter.
Now, what will this look like?
So first Alice opens the game by posting the hash of
a nonce combined with the choice she makes to play.
So we have the hash.
Then if Bob plays along, he will post his own choice.
So Bob will play, and now we have the hash
and Bob's choice, let's call it C Bob.
If at this point, Alice realizes that she has
won, depending on Bob's choice, she can reveal
her secret and the game ends and she has won.
Let's assume that when Alice plays in Bob plays,
they both put down certain amount of money.
And in this scenario where Alice has won
Alice gets Bob's claim and her own back.
If however, after Bob made his move, Alice sees
that she has lost, there's no need actually for
her to do anything because she has lost anyway.
So after a certain deadline has been reached.
And Alice just doesn't reply.
And then Bob claims his win.
And there's another option that we haven't considered
it, it could be that after Alice starts playing,
Bob simply is not interested and doesn't reply.
So in that case, there must be a way
for Alice to get her own money back.
And that's basically all the things that can happen.
So the different stages of the game starts
by Alice opening with the hash of the
concatenation of a nonce in her move.
Then if Bob doesn't reply, Alice gets her money back.
If Bob does reply, he puts down his choice
and then there are two possibilities again.
Alice realizes she has won and she needs to
prove it to Bob by revealing and she wins
or she doesn't do anything and after some
time has passed, Bob can claim the win.
And he gets both Alice's at his own stake.
So let's implement this in Plutus now.
First, just using the techniques we already know about.
So let's look at the implementation,
it's in the module even odd.
And if you're wondering about that name, it's just
because if the sum of the two choices of the two
numbers that the players pick is even then the first
player wins and if it's odd, the second player wins.
Which is the same as what I said earlier, that
if they agree, the first player wins and if
they are different, the second player wins.
And I called the first and second player first
and second, instead of Alice and Bob here.
So the data type game is used
as a parameter for the contract.
So G first and G second are the two players
identified by their public key hashes.
G stake is an integer that denotes the
number of lovelace that are to be used
as stake in the game by each player.
And then there are two deadlines,
play deadline and reveal deadline.
So play deadline is by what time the
second player has to make a move before
the first player can claim back his stake.
And the reveal deadline is in the case
that the second player has made the move.
How much time the first player has to
claim victory by revealing his nonce.
And finally, we have a token
represented by its asset class.
And this will be the same trick that I used
last time for the oracle, that will be NFT
in arbitrary NFT use to identify the right
instance of the UTxO that we are using.
So the idea is, again, similar to what we did
with the oracle who use the datum of a UTxO
sitting at the address of this contract, this
script address of this contact to keep track
of what has happened, where we are in the game.
Then the type game choice.
So that's just the two moves the
players can make, zero or one.
And, I derive equality in the normal Haskell sense
and an ord instance, but unfortunately for the
Plutus equivalence of eq and ord that's not possible.
And I need eq for Plutus eq so I
do that by hand in the usually way.
So, I mean zero equals zero
and one equals one and all other
combinations are not equal.
And for this to work with template Haskell,
you have to put this inlinable pragma
there as well for the equals operation.
And game datum is what I will
use as state for the contract.
And byteString is the hash that the
first player submits and maybe game
choice is the move by the second player.
It's a maybe because in the beginning,
the second player hasn't yet moved.
So then it will be nothing and once the
second player has moved, it will be a just.
And same thing I also need a
Plutus equality for game datum.
And just also the obvious one that two
are equal if both components, the hash
and the maybe game choice are equal.
Now we come to the redeemer and for that, I also
implemented the custom type that called game redeemer.
And that corresponds to the transitions
we saw in the diagram I drew just now.
So, play is when the second player moves
and as argument, it has a game choice.
So the second player can play zero or one.
So that will be play zero or play one.
Reveal is for the case when the first player has
won and must prove that by revealing its nonce.
So the byteString argument here would be the nonce.
We don't need to also provide the move that the
first player made, because he will only reveal in the
case he has won and we know what move makes him win.
So that would be redundant and therefore I left it.
And finally claim first and came.
Second claim first is in the case when
the second player doesn't make a move.
So the first player can claim back his stake and
came second is for the case that the first player
doesn't reveal because he knows he has lost.
So the second player can get his winnings.
Then same helper function I use last time.
That I think is for some reason
missing from the Plutus libraries.
So given a value extractor number
of lovelaces content in it.
And then similar last time I had oracle datum
function, and now I did the same for game datum.
So given an output of a transaction and
some way to given a datum hash, maybe
get the datum, give me a game datum.
And it's the same as with oracle last time.
So it's these three steps.
First I get the try to get the data hash
from the output, which may fail second
year, use the second argument function
to turn this hash into a data and value.
And lastly, I try to pass this datum
as a something from of type game datum.
So that's exactly what I did for the oracle last time.
Now we come to the core business logic
in the make game validator function.
The first argument here is the parameter
of the game type that I just explained.
The second and the third
argument, somewhat of a nuisance.
And I just need them due to the fact that as
we have already discussed on Discord, it's not
possible to use string literals to get byteStrings
in Haskell that is compiled to Plutus core.
And I want, string literals representing
the zero choice and the one choice.
So this will just be the byteString with the
digit zero and the byteString with the digit one.
But because I can't use string literals,
I passed them in as auxiliary arguments
we'll see how we pass them in later.
Then the usual datum, redeemer and context.
Let's look at some helper functions first.
So info as before own input
and own output also as before.
So this should never fail because we are in
the context of validating the usage of a UTxO.
So there should always be own input
the input via presently validating.
Own output if you're in a case where we are
not done yet, where the game isn't over.
We want that there's a new UTxO
carrying the NFT with the updated datum.
So for that case, we will use this own
output function and it checks all the
outputs that go to the same address.
And only succeeds if there's exactly one such.
Output datum makes use of this game
datum function that we defined earlier.
And given the case where we have exactly
one output to the same script address gives
us the datum tries to gives us the datum.
And that could fail or otherwise we return the datum.
So check nonce is for the case that the first
player has won and wants to prove it by revealing
his nonce and improving that the hash submitted
in the beginning of the game fits this nuance.
So the first argument is the hash he submitted.
The second argument is the nonce he now reveals.
The third argument is the move that both players made.
It's called C second here, move of the second
player, but this function would only be involved or
only be relevant in the case where the first player
knows he has won, which is only the case when he
made the same choice that the second player made.
So I could just as well called
at sea first in principle.
And in order to do this check, I mean, how did
the computation of the hash work where I take
the nonce and concatenated with the choice.
But the choice of course here is, is some abstract
data type game choice, but in order to concatenate
with the nonce I needed in byteString form.
And the idea is, I just use this BS zero for
the zero choice and BS one for the one choice.
So this is just as conversion.
And I called the byteString C first.
So C second is of type game choice,
but C first is of type byteString.
And if the choice was zero, I'd take
the byteString representing zero.
If it was one, I take the bites strong
representing one, then to compute the hash I
take the nonce concatenated with this byteString
and apply the sha2_256, a hash function to it.
So this is the hash that I get giving this nonce
then check is to make sure that that is indeed the
hash, the first player committed in the first place.
And finally, I haven't mentioned that before,
but we now have this state token, this NFT that
identifies the correct UTxO and the question is
what happens to this NFT after the game is over
and there is no UTxO at the game address anymore.
And the way I've implemented.
Now, I've wanted to go back to the first player.
The first player needs to have it at the
beginning in order to kick off the game
and put the NFT into the correct UTxO.
So I think it's, it's only reasonable to give it
back to him in the end, no matter who won the game.
So this just checks, there's a function
called value paid to and gets the
context or the info from the context.
And pub key hash and then it basically adds
up all the values that go to that pub key
hash in some output of the transaction.
So I want that, so this just means
that the first player gets the token.
So now we can look at the, at the conditions.
There's one condition that applies
to all cases simultaneously.
And that is that the input I'm validating
must be identified by the state token.
So that's what I'm checking here.
That the own input, the input I'm presently
validating, contains the state token.
And then what the, the rules, after
that depend on the situation I'm in.
The first situation is the one
where the first player has moved.
The second player is moving now.
So this is the transaction where the
second player moves and chooses to move C.
So the datum, the second component must be nothing.
Remember that just means that the second
player hasn't moved to is moving now.
And in this case, what do I have to check?
I have to check that this move is
indeed made by the second player.
So he has to sign the transaction.
This checks that the first player
has put down the stake for the game.
Then this checks that now in this transaction,
the second player, it's his own stake.
So in the output, we now have twice the G stake game.
Then we know exactly what the
datum of the output must be.
It must be the same hash as before, but now
the nothing is replaced by just C where C is
exactly the move, the second player is making.
Then the move has to happen before the first deadline.
That's exactly the point of this first step by the
play deadline until then the move must have happened.
And finally, the NFT must be passed onto
the new UTxO to identify that again.
Okay, the second situation is both players have
moved and the first player discovers that he has won.
So in order to prove that and get the win
winnings, he has to reveals his nonce.
So in that case, it has to be
signed by the first player.
The nonce must indeed agree with
the hash he submitted earlier.
He must do this before the reveal deadline.
The input must contain the stake of both players.
And finally, what I just said, the
NFT must go back to the first player.
First case is second player hasn't moved
yet and also doesn't move in the deadline.
So the first player wants his stake back.
So this must be signed by the first player.
It must only happen after the deadline has passed.
The first player has provided his
stake and he must get the NFT back.
And the last case is, both players have
moved, but the first player has realized
that he didn't win and therefore didn't
reveal his nonce or he got disconnected or
whatever, in any case, he missed the deadline.
So in that case, the second player wins, but
the second player must sign this transaction.
So it must not happen before the deadline,
he can only do that once the reveal deadline
has passed to give the first play enough time
to reveal the nonce if the first player won.
We check again that the input, the
consumed UTxO has the correct stake.
So in this case, both players
must have provided their stake.
And even though the second player has won and gets
the money, the NFT must go back to the first player.
And that's all legitimate transitions we can have.
So in all other cases, we don't
validate, we fail validation.
So now let's look at the rest of the on-chain code.
As always, we define this helper type
that just bundles information about what
the datum and what the redeemer type are.
Here we define the byteStrings we actually
going to use for the two choices zero and one.
This is completely arbitrary.
I could pick any two byteString there.
Typed game validator, it compiles de code as before.
So it's parameterized now by game and these
two byteStrings, this make validator function.
So I have to apply all of them, but
I just use these constants here.
So now, I only left with this one
game parameter as one would expect.
And the usual boiler plate for validator and address.
Now as preparation for the on-chain
code, sorry for the off-chain code, we
will always need to find the right UTxO.
So the one that carries the NFT.
So I write this helper function find game
output that gets the game and then in the
contract monad tries to find the UTxO.
So it could fail, the UTxO or could not be there.
So therefore maybe, and then I return the
usual things, the reference and the output
itself and additionally, the game datum.
And that's called straightforward to implement.
So first I get all the UTxOs at the game address.
Then I use this find function.
This is in data dot list.
And it's more general, doesn't only work for
lists, it works for more general containers
of type T, but you can think lists.
So it gets a predicate on elements and
the list of As and returns a maybe A.
And the logic is if it finds an element in the
list that satisfies the predicate, it will return
it as a just and otherwise it will return nothing.
So if we do find even 1, 3, 5, 8, 11, 12.
It will pick the first even
number from the list just eight.
But if I remove the even elements,
then it will return nothing.
So using this find.
After we have all the UTxOs turn them into
a list of pairs, then as F we take such a
pair, ignore the reference, just take the o.
And check whether this output contains our token.
So this line, which by the way,
happens in the maybe monad.
Will...
If it exists, find us the UTxO that contains the token.
And then we use the earlier defined
helper function game datum to get the
datum to this UTxO and return the triple.
Now there's a second helper
function, wait until time has passed.
The idea is it gets a POSIX time and
then it waits until that POSIX time
has passed and we are in the next slot.
So how do I do that?
I get the current slot, I just log it.
Then I use something provided by the contract
monad called await time which does what it says.
So it gets a POSIX time and waits blocks
the contract until the time has come.
And then just to make sure that I'm in the next
slot, I wait for one slot using wait N slots.
And I just for information, ask for
the now current slot and also log that.
Okay, so now we have two contracts for the two players.
One for the first player to play the game.
The other one for the second player,
second player plays the game.
And with corresponding parameters
first params and second params.
So, first params we don't need the first player.
The first player will be the owner of the wallet
that invokes this contract, but we need the
second and the other things we need to define
the game, the stake and the two deadlines.
Then we need the nonce that the first
player wants to use to conceal his choice.
And then the NFT which we split
into currency symbol and token name.
And finally the choice, the move
that the player wants to make.
So in this contract, first get our own public key hash.
Then we can define the value of the game type.
So we put our own public key hash as first player and
then use the parameters we got from the first params.
And for the token we just assemble the currency
symbol and token name into an asset class.
And this V value is just our stake that
we must put into the . UTxO plus the
NFT that we must put into the UTxO.
C is our choice.
Now we compute the hash that we must
put there, our commitment to our choice.
So we take the more nonce and concatenate
it with, well, if you want to play zero.
There's zero byteString, and otherwise
the one byteString and hash the results.
The constraints for the transaction are very simple.
All we have to do is we must produce a script output
at this address with the datum that contains the hash.
We just computed nothing for the second player,
because obviously the second player hasn't played yet.
And the value we computed.
And we wait for transaction and log a message.
So now, the second player has a chance to move,
but it must happen before this play deadline.
So what we do now is first player is
we wait until this deadline has passed.
And then there are several cases.
So we check whether we find UTxO containing the NFT, if
we don't find it, then something has gone very wrong.
That can't actually happen,
because this can't just disappear.
We know we just produce the UTxO at this address
and all anybody else at the second player can do
is, make a move, but that doesn't destroy the UTx...
I mean, it's removed, UTxO that produces
a new one at the same address again.
So we should find it.
There's no way we can not find it.
But nevertheless, if that happens then...
throwing an exception, but normally we will find it.
So we have this triple the UTxO And the datum.
And in this case, the second player hasn't moved.
So the deadline has passed.
The second player hasn't moved.
So what we can do is we can invoke this
claim first redeemer to get our stake back.
So as constraints, we just say, we must
spend this UTxO we found with this redeemer
and as lookups we need to provide the UTxO.
And we must provide the validator of the game.
And in that case, we log that we reclaimed the stake.
Second case is that the second player did
move and they are then in turn again, two
cases that the second player moved and won
or that the second player moved and lost.
So this is the case where the second player
choose the same move that we played, so we won.
And in the other case, the second player won and
we can't do anything so we just don't do anything.
But if we won, we must now reveal
our nonce to get the winning.
So we use the reveal nonce redeemer.
And we must also submit this transaction
before the deadline for revealing has passed.
And we, again, need lookups, we again need to specify
the UTxO and we must provide the gain validator.
And then we submit and wait and have won.
Now for the second player, the parameters are
very similar, except that now we don't need to
provide the second player because that's us.
But the first player stake and the two
deadlines as before currency, symbol
and token name for the NFT as before.
And the choice, the move we want to make.
We don't need the nonce now because the
nonce was only for the first player.
Okay, so if we start by looking up our own public
key hash and can then define the game value,
similar to as what you did for the first player.
And now we, try to find the UTxO that contains the NFT.
So if we find it and...
BS is the commitment of the first player, the hash.
And nothing, because we haven't moved yet.
So in that case, we found the game, so this
is the most interesting case, but let's look
at the second case that it's not like that.
Well, in that case, we just didn't find the
game where we can move, so we can't do anything.
So it's enough to concentrate on this case.
So if we found the game and now we want to
make our move, so invoke the play redeemer.
So token is the NFT, now V is the value
that we must put in the new output.
Remember if we do the play transaction,
we must consume the existing UTxO and
producing one at the same address.
And, the old one should contain the
stake that the first player put in.
And now we must add our own stake
and we must keep the NFT in there.
And the NFT of course is also contained
in the, in the input side already.
So, what we must put in the output
is, so X is just local variable here
to, so that's the steak in lovelace.
So we must into the output, put
twice the stake and the NFT.
C is our choice, let's look at the constraints first.
So we must spend the existing UTxO
with redeemer play our choice.
Then we must create a new UTxO with the updated datum.
So same BS, but now just C, just our move.
And this V we computed, which now also
contains our own stake in addition to
the first player stake and the NFT.
And we must do this before the
deadline passes to make the play move.
And we need lookups, so we must provide the UTxO.
And because we are consuming script
opportunity the validator, and because we are
producing one, we need the script instance.
Then we do the usual things.
So we submit, we wait for confirmation, we log.
Now it's the first player's turn again.
So we wait until this reveal deadline has passed.
And we, again, try to find the UTxO which
will now or could now, be a different one.
That's I called M prime So if we don't find an UTxO
any more, that means that in the meantime, while
were waiting, the first player revealed and won.
So, in that case we have lost, we can't do anything.
If we still do find the UTxO, it means the
first player didn't reveal, which means either
the first player left the game for whatever
reason or he lost and couldn't reveal.
In any case now we can claim the winning.
So we must spend the UTxO we found.
We must do this before and after the reveal deadline
has passed, because until then the first players
still would have time to, to make his revelation.
And we must hand back the NFT to the first player.
And as lookups, we again need this
UTxO, and we must provide the validator.
And we do the usual thing and log the message.
And that's it, that's the two on-chain contracts.
But now to make them more accessible, we defined
schema, game schema which has two endpoints.
One for the first player taking the first params.
One for the second player taking the second params.
And we define a contract called endpoints that
offers the choice between these two endpoints.
And no matter what is chosen, after that is then
run it recursively again, offers less choice.
And first and second is simply our first game in
second game where we first block and wait for user
input or external input to provide the parameters
and then bind the contracts we defined earlier.
And that concludes the first version of the game.
That doesn't use state machines.
Now let's test this using the emulator
trace monad, So the code is in module test.
And let's look first look at the test prime
function, which is parameterized by two game choices.
So the idea is that we'll run or simulate a
game where the first player makes this choice
and the second player makes that choice.
And then in the test function, I just
run all four combinations in sequence.
And, as before with the oracle I'm using this
run emulator trace IO prime variant, because
I want to specify an initial distribution.
And I just want to provide wallet one with this NFT.
So, I just make up a currency symbol and
some token name, I call it state token.
And, of course, in a real scenario in the production
code, we would have to generate this NFT, for
example, using this mint contract from the currency
use case, or also using our own contract that
we discussed when we introduce minting policies.
But, and if these are now not the focus of
this lecture, so I just use this feature
that I can conjure one out of thin air
in this emulator trace configuration.
Okay.
So now let's look at the trace.
So it takes these two parameters,
the two choices, C1 and C2.
I just locked some information that later in the
output, it's easier to identify what was going on.
And I start two instances of the endpoints contract
one for wallet, one, one for wallet two h1 and h2 to
lookup the two public key hashes of the two wallets.
And now I define the parameters that they will use.
So first player is first wallet, second player
has The second wallet stake is five ADA deadline.
The first deadline is after five
slots, second deadline after 10 slots.
this of course should be some random string in
reality, but now I just fix one secret nonce.
And, I used this token that I provided earlier as
the NFT And of course the choice of the first place.
Just see one parameter from here.
And, the choice of the second player is C2.
Okay.
And with these definitions phase simple, I
just called the h1 at the first endpoint on
void one with these FP parameters I had just
wait three slots and then I call the second
endpoint for wallet two with the SP parameters
that I defined here and wait another 10 slots.
So by that time you should be in slot 13 or something
to both deadlines should have been passed and there
should have been enough time for everything to settle.
And if we run this, okay, so I'm in module tests now.
And if I invoke this test and
then let's go through the output.
So the first scenario is, that both play zero.
So the first bullet should win.
so here the first bullet, it creates the initial.
UTxO with its stake and knocks
this message that made them move.
Now, the first wallet is waiting now the second
fall, it kicks in and it looks for the UTxO
or finds it and sees that it can make a move.
So it makes it smooth zero.
And now the first bullet sees this move and realizes
that it has won because both have played the same move.
So now the first file, it must reveal
and that's that here and, has won.
So the first wallet has won and we see
in the final balances that wallet one
does indeed have the state token back.
This NFT and now has almost five, eight, or
more than it started with the differences
of course, due to transaction fees.
And the second wallet, it has a bit more than
five, eight, or less than at the beginning.
So wallet one, one.
Now the second case is what add one again,
plays zero, but for the two plays one.
So the beginning is the same.
So the first wallet creates this.
Initially UTxO, now with the second wallet
again, finds the game and makes its move.
But now the move is one.
So now the first one that realizes that
it has lost and doesn't do anything.
So the second wallet detects it, that the first
fall, it hasn't made a move and now invokes
this claim second endpoint to get the money.
So now if you look at the final balances, Situation
is reversed again, wallet one, got the stake
token back, but now wallet one has 500 or less
and wallet two has five eight more than before.
And the other two cases are more or
less the same, just the other way round.
So if it's one zero, then wallet two will win again.
And if it's one, one, then wallet one give it
again, so this all seems to work as expected.
So what is the state machine?
The state machine?
first of all, normally it has nothing
to do with blockchain particular.
So it's just some sort of system you start
in a certain state, and then there are
one or more transitions to other states.
And so you can transition from the
initial state into this one or that one.
And that goes on.
So basically it's just a directed graph.
And then there may also be some states that are
special in that they're so-called final states
from which they are no possible ways out anymore.
No transitions that lead out of the final state.
And, what does it have to do with
blockchain and with our examples?
So if we look again at the diagram we
had earlier for how our game works,
then we can consider that state machine.
So the initial state would be this one here, where
the first player has made the move and the state is
basically characterized by the state owned by the hash.
And in this state, there are two possible
transitions, one where the second player plays.
Bob place.
And the second one where it doesn't
play and the first player can reclaim.
So all the notes in this diagram, cause
point 2 states and all the errors, the edges
of the graph correspond to transitions.
And in particular, in the blockchain, the
state machine will be represented by UTxO
sitting at the state machine script address.
And the state of the state machine would be the
datum of the UTxO and the transition will be
a transaction that consumes the current state.
That's current.
UTxO using a trend redeemer that characterizes the
transition and then produces a new, UTxO at the same,
address where the datum now reflects the new state.
So that's the relation and that fits
lots of situations very nicelly.
And there's special support in the Plutus
libraries to easily implement such state machines.
And then we'll see when we use this
approach that our code will be much shorter.
The support for state machines is in package Plutus
contract in the module Plutus contract state machine.
And let's first look at what a state machine is.
So a state machine is, has to type parameters
S and I that stands for state and input
and that corresponds to datum and redeemer.
So in the actual implementation and the manifestation
of the state machine on the blockchain S will be
the datum type, and I will be the redeemer type.
And, so a state machine is a
record type with four fields.
So the most important one probably is the
transition that defines from which states using
which transition you can change into another state.
And this state S type is defined here.
So that is basically the datum, the
state itself and also the value.
Remember I said that this would be represented,
the state machine would be represented by a UTxO.
So the state of the state machine is a
UTxO, and that has a datum into value.
So we have access to both in this state type.
So given the state types, so the present datum
and value of the UTxO and a transaction that
tries to consume this UTxO with a redeemer I.
We can indicate that this transition is not
allowed by returning nothing in this function.
And if it is allowed, we returned a tuple.
And the second component is the new state.
So this transaction will consume the existing
UTxO and produce a new one at the same address.
And this here will be the new datum and
value of the new output, the new UTxO.
And then we can have Tx constraints that until
now we've only seen in off-chain code that specify
additional constraints that the transaction that does
this, that does this transition must have must satisfy.
So that's the transition function.
Then we have a function, just a predicate
on datums basically on states that tells
us whether it's a final state or not.
So final states are special in
debt in this transition function.
If we transitioned into the, into a final state,
Then there mustn't be any value attached with it.
And then this output that normally gets produced.
So we normally consume the UTxO
representing the old state and produce
a new output representing the new state.
But if this new state is, is final, then we don't.
So then we don't produce a new UTxO.
So basically the machine instead stops.
So that's this SM final, SM check is
very similar to this transition function
except it doesn't have the value.
So it just gets the datum and the redeemer
and context, and a reverse a bool.
So this is basically an additional checks that
can't be expressed in terms of these Tx constraints.
Finally, we have this SM thread
token, which can or cannot be there.
And the purpose of this is to solve
the same problem that we already had
with our oracle in the last lecture.
And also now with our game that as I have said
many times before you can't stop anybody from
sending anything to any arbitrary address.
So there can be many UTxOs sitting at an
address that you have no control over.
But in cases like these, like the oracle
last time or the game in the previous
example, we want to identify a specific UTxO.
And the trick we used in the last lecture and
also just now was to mint and NFT and insist
on it being present in the UTxO and because
an NFT by definition can only exist once, this
allows us to pinpoint the right UTxO and ignore
other UTxOs that may sit at the same address.
And the thread token here serves the same purpose.
So if you look at thread token, it is basically
a reference to a UTxO and the currency symbol
and this UTxO will be the one that uniquely
identifies the minting transaction of the NFT.
So this is like a weird way to specify an NFT.
So we don't have to use this mechanism, but if
we use this, so if we put a just thread token
there in the state machine, then the mechanism
will automatically take care of minting.
This NFT, that corresponds to this thread token,
and then threading it through the state transitions.
So in all these checks in validation will always make
sure that the corresponding NFT is present in the
UTxO and also if it's not the final state and there
is a UTxO at the same address in the output that
this NFT will then aslo be present in that output.
So we don't have to worry about that.
That will automatically be taken care of the
minting and eventually burning in the final
state of this NFT that corresponds to this
thread token will be handled automatically.
And it also doesn't appear in the value.
So we sit here, the state
bundles the datum and the value.
And of course this NFT will be part of
the value, but it won't be visible here.
So we can ignore that, we don't have to worry about it.
I have implemented the same game now using the
state machine approach in module state machine.
So the beginning is exactly the same.
So the game parameter, the
game type is exactly the same.
Game choices the same, this is all the same.
Game datum has slightly changed because I have
added a second constructor that I called finished.
That we didn't need before and that is supposed
to represent the final state of our state machine.
So it won't correspond to a UTxO, but we need
that for the state machine mechanism to work.
So this first construct is as before hash
provided by the second player, maybe...
sorry has provided by the first player.
Maybe move by the second player and then
this additional constructor to represent
the final state that the game has ended.
That makes a definition of equality slightly
more complicated because now I have to take
this second constructor into account as well.
But nothing serious going on there, the
redeemer is this exactly the same as before.
These two helper functions are
exactly the same as before.
Now, this is now the transition function of the state
machine, which sort of corresponds as we will see in a
moment to the make game validator that we had earlier.
So this is basically the core business logic.
And so it takes the game, the parameter and now as we
saw in the definition of state machine, state datum.
So remember that's a pair basically
consisting of the datum and the value.
And the redeemer and then we must return
nothing if it's not allowed and just a pair of
new state and constraints on the transaction.
Now let's try to compare the transition function
of the state machine to the make game validator
function of our first version of the game.
So the first thing, I mean, of course the signature
is different, but in spirit it's a very similar thing.
So in both functions try to determine
whether basically a combination of datum and
redeemer and transaction is valid or not.
So we we'll see the correspondence now.
The first difference we notice is here in our old
version, we first had to check that the input we
are consuming, the UTxO we're consuming, actually
carries the NFT, and that is missing in the state
machine formulation because the state machine
mechanism automatically takes care of that.
If these set this last field in the state NFT
to sub thread tokens, then the mechanism will
automatically check that the NFT is present in the
consumed UTxO and also in the newly created UTxO.
If it's not a final state.
So let's look at this first case
where the first player moved.
So the component for the second
player was still nothing.
And now the second player wants
to make a play with choice C.
So we checked these six conditions here
and let's see how they are reflected
in the state machine formulation.
And in the state machine we have this, the
state S which remember is a combination
of datum and value, and you can access
those two with state value and state data.
So state value as is now the value in
the UTxO that we're consuming state data
S is the datum and R is the redeemer.
So we have this triple.
And here I checked that the value
is actually the stake of the game.
So the value contained in the consumed
UTxO and that's the condition that was
the second condition that we checked here.
Now, the result of the transition function,
if recall if it's valid, it's just the pair.
And the first component of the pair is constraints
on the transaction formulated using this
constraints module that we know from off-chain code.
And the second component of the pair
is the new state of the resulting UTxO
which again is given by datum and value.
So here we are specifying with this
transition of the second player makes a move.
The new datum will be BS just C.
And the new value will be twice this stake
of the game because it's now the first
player stake and the second player stake.
We leave the NFT out of here, even
though it should be present in the UTxO.
And that is again, because the state machine implicitly
takes care of that NFT that it's pass through.
So we don't mention it here.
So this here corresponds in the old
one to this check that the datum is
BS just C and that the value is right.
This is this one here.
And we don't need the last check, as I said.
Here we check that the output again contains the NFT.
We don't need that because the state
machine does that automatically.
So now what is missing?
So here we have these two constraints must be signed by
second and must validate in before the play deadline.
And this corresponds here to the first
condition must be signed by the second player.
And the deadline thing is here.
And if you check exactly all these conditions are
covered here as well in slightly different form.
An actually shorter form.
And we don't have to worry about the
NFT that already makes it shorter.
Now let's look at the second interesting
case where the second player has played
and the first player sees that he has won.
So now the first player has to reveal.
So in the old version, we'll check
it's signed by the first player.
This is here.
Then we check the nonce.
That is no way here.
And the reason is that that condition can't
be expressed in terms of a constraint.
And that is exactly what this other component of
the record type of the state machine is for the
check functions that we will see that in a bit.
So this is missing for now.
We don't have this nonce check.
Then the deadline check is here.
This just checks that the input value is right.
So we have that here on the left-hand side.
And finally, we check that because the game is
over the NFT should go back to the first player.
So that the game is over we specified
here by specifying the finish state.
And that the NFT goes back to the first player we
don't need to check, because there's NFT and the
state machine gets automatically taken care of.
And gets burned when the state
machine finishes reaches final state.
So all we have to say is that we enter
final state after that reveal has happened.
Now, the third interesting case is the
case where the second player doesn't react
and the first player wants his stake back.
So this is here.
So let's see what we checked in the old quote.
First of all, the transaction must be signed by the
first player, and this is here, the first constraint.
And secondly, the first clear must give
the second player enough time to react.
So he can only reclaim a stake after the play
deadline has passed, so that's this condition.
Then the incoming state must be correct, so the
first player must have actually put down a stake.
This is here on the left-hand side.
And then finally, in the old code we wanted, the
NFT goes back to the first player that has no
equivalent here because that is taken care of
automatically by the state machine mechanism.
But we do transition into the finished
states will be indicate that the game
is over the state machine is finished.
Finally, the fourth case.
That is when the first player has
played, the second player has played.
And the first player realizes that he has lost and
doesn't react anymore, or he gets disconnected.
So in any case, the second player has won and
can claim both his and the first player stake.
So that must be signed by the second player.
That's here.
It must only happened after
the reveal deadline has passed.
That's here.
And the incoming state must be correct.
It must be both the first and the second player stake
it's again, here, checked on the left-hand side.
And again, this is a final state.
So in the old version we insist the
NFT goes back to the first player.
This would be taken care of automatically here.
We just indicate that we are
transitioning into the finished state.
Okay.
And these are the valid transaction, these four
transitions and everything else is invalid.
And we indicate that by returning
nothing in all other cases.
So that means only those transitions are valid.
So the conditions themselves are maybe not
really shorter than in the old version,
but we don't need any helper functions.
So this, in our own input own output and so
on, we don't need, this is all taken care of
by the state machine or by these constraints.
And we don't need to worry about the NFT.
That's also automatically taken care of.
So this is already significantly shorter
than in the old version, but we are not
done yet defining the state machine.
There are other fields in the record.
One is final.
So we must specify what final states
are and that's just this finished state.
So final finished is true and everything else is false.
Then we left out the nonce check in
the transition function because we
couldn't express that as a constraint.
And for that's exactly what this check function is for.
Then we have have two auxiliary arguments, these two
byteStrings that we also had in the other version
zero and one, for the same reason, we need that here.
And then datum and redeemer and context and much just
return whether this additional check is satisfied.
We ignore the context, we don't need it here.
And the only condition we have to put into
this check function is the one with the nonce.
And that wasn't the situation where
the second player had played, just see,
and where the redeemer is reveal nonce.
And this line here is just the old check
we had in the first version as well.
We compute the concatenation of the nonce and the
byteString corresponding to the move, hash that,
and compared with the originally provided hash.
And all other situations we don't need an
additional check and therefore can return true.
Now we can define our state machine and
we give, so for now it has these three
parameters, the game, and these two auxiliary
byteStrings, and it returns a state machine.
And we just provide the four
fields that we just defined.
So transition game, that was the important one,
and this final check, the additional check.
And finally, the thread token, which
we just take from, from the game value.
Now there is machinery provided by the
state machine to make a game, a validator.
So what our old make game validated function can
now be replaced by using the state machine and
using the make validator game state machines.
So gave them same machines is our state machine here.
And there's a make validator function that turns
that into something of this type, which is exactly
the type we had before in our handwritten version.
So this is similar to before, I mean, we had
this other mechanism to bundle datum type
and the redeemer type, the state machine...
that's the same basically.
So now our type gaming can just be
state machine game datum, game redeemer.
Our two strings and are provided a second
version of game state machine, where we only
have to specify the game and not these two
strings and that won't work in on-chain code.
So it doesn't have this inlinable pragma
because of the literal strings here.
But in off-chain code it works perfectly fine.
And then we don't have to provide
this two additional parameters.
Now this is exactly as before.
So the same boilerplate we had before.
Except now this make game validator has
been defined here using the state machine
mechanism, instead of doing it explicitly.
And a game address, game client,
no, game address is the same.
Game client is a new thing.
Game client is a state machine client, and this
is basically what we need to interact with state
machine from our wallet, from our contract monad.
If you look at the definition of state machine
client, is here, it has two fields, a state
machine instance and then this chooser.
So the state machine instance it's again
a record type with two fields and it has
a state machine and the typed validator.
And both of those, we already have defined.
So we can make a state machine instance.
So what's this chooser all about?
Well, in general, if we don't use the thread token
mechanism, the NFT mechanism, we could have several
UTxOs sitting at the address of the state machine.
And the chooser is a way to pick the right one.
So in general, we will find a list of UTxOs, I mean,
it's a different type, the on chain state that, but you
can think UTxOs sitting at the state machine address.
And this chooser function
given such a list, picking one.
So either producing error.
Or picking one of those, but there's a default
implementation for such a chooser, which if
we use the thread token mechanism just picks
the one UTxO that holds this thread token.
So in order to make a state machine client, we
can use the make state machine client function,
which just takes a state machine instance.
So not a chooser because the
default chooser will be used.
So to make our game client given a game.
We can just use this make state machine client.
And now we need the state machine instance.
And we must provide the state machine
for which we can use our game state
machine prime with the game as parameter.
And the type game validator we also have to find here.
So this gives us our game client.
And now the client can be used to interact
with the state machine from off-chain code.
First parameters are exactly the same.
There's one small nuisance that these state machine
contracts, that the state machine module provides.
They use a specific error type or they have
a specific constraint on the error type.
And one error type that works is SM contract error.
But I want to do what I did in the last
lectures and always use text as map error type.
So in order to make those two fit together,
I define this map error prime function, which
use the map error we have discussed before.
And it turns an SM contract error into a text
by showing the SM contract error and then
picking the resulting string into a text.
I also, again, have this helper function wait until
time has passed that I already used in the even odd
the example, which given a time first waits until
this time is reached and then waits for another slot
to make sure we are in the slot after this time.
Now the first game becomes much nicer,
much shorter, much more compact.
It starts the same.
So we lookup our own public key hash.
Now there's something new.
We need to get this thread token.
So we must identify a UTxO in our wallet
that can be used for the minting of the
NFT to make that a true NFT as I explained
in the lecture on native tokens and NFTs.
So that's what this get thread token function does.
And I have to apply the map ever prime in order to
convert it to text error messages, as I explained.
And there's in the documentation for this
get thread token it says you mustn't do any
transactions after you have invoked that
before you use it for a state machine, because
that could change the UTxOs in your wallet.
So then the situation could change.
Okay, so now we have our public key hash, in our
thread token, and we can define the game using public
key hash and thread token at the appropriate spots.
And taking the rest from the parameters we got.
Now we can define our game client
using the game client function.
These three are as before.
So it's the stake, our choice and the
hash that we reveal that we commit
to, that we use to commit to our move.
And now in this one line, a lot happens under the hood.
So this run initialise given the
client, a datum and the value.
First, it will mint the NFT
corresponding to this thread token.
And then it will create a UTxO at the state
machine address to start the state machine.
Put the NFT in that UTxO to uniquely
identify it, and the datum and value of
that UTxO are given by these arguments here.
So we put it in the initial state we want
whether first player commits using this hash.
And the second player hasn't moved yet.
And the first player puts down his stake.
And again, we have to use the map error
prime in order to adjust the error messages.
And we just log that we made the first move.
Now, this is also new.
And if you look at the type,
this has also slightly changed.
Earlier, I didn't use the tell mechanism,
the writer mechanism of the contract monad.
Now, I need to communicate the thread token.
Because the second player wants to find the game.
So the second player must define this game.
And part of that game is this thread token.
So the second player otherwise would have
no way of knowing what the thread token is.
So in order to communicate that, I tell it here.
Okay, so this is all to set it up.
And now if you recall, we have to wait and then
we needed this helper functions find game datum or
game output in order to after we have waited for
the second player to move, to find the UTxO again.
This is now much simpler, because we can
use something called get on-chain state.
So get on-chain state takes the client and
returns something of type maybe on-chain state.
So if it finds the state machine, then it will
return just on-chain state and if not, then nothing.
So what is on-chain state?
On-chain state is a tuple.
Consisting of typed script Tx out and typed
script Tx out ref.
This is similar to what this UTxO at gives us.
I mean, there we always got this map from
orefs to Os from Tx out refs to Tx outs.
And this is similar, it's also basically
the UTxO itself and the reference to it.
But it has this typed, it's this typed
version that we have seen before.
And all that does is, it basically bundles
what we know from before, this Tx out.
But additionally it provides the datum.
If you recall, we always in our off-chain code, we
always had to scramble and write helper functions
to access the datum once we had found a UTxO.
We had to lookup the datum hash and
that could fail, and then we had to
lookup the datum to this hash and so on.
And all of this is basically hidden from
us by using this typed script Tx out type.
Which we get by using this get on-chain state.
So by using get on-chain state client, we have
this M and this M it could be nothing if no output
is found as before, this should never happen.
But if it does, we throw an error
and now we get this on-chain state.
We are not interested in the
reference only in the o itself.
And then we use this tyTx out data
o to directly access the datum.
So no need to lookup hashes, that's
all, some wrapped in this tyTx out data.
So now we immediately have the datum.
And as before we have the two cases that the
second player hasn't moved or that the test moved.
So if it hasn't moved we must reclaim an
earlier than we had lots of code to set up
the lookups and the constraints that we need.
Now, we only need this line.
So the important function here is run step.
So run step creates a transaction and submits
it, that will transition the state machine.
And it takes us input the client again.
And then simply the redeemer, that's all,
all the input we need is the redeemer.
And then we will get this transition result
and I'm not using it in this example, but that
basically encodes whether it failed and for
what reason it failed or whether it succeeded
and if it succeeded what the new state is, but
I don't really need this in, in this example.
So this is all, this is really dramatically simpler.
So all I have to do is I tell it,
okay, in this case, the first player...
the second player hasn't moved, I just
do a step with the claim first redeemer.
No constraints, no lookups, no submissions or waiting.
This is all ended by the run step.
And this is really need, I think.
This is dramatically simpler than before.
And the way it works of course, is
that in the transition function.
These conditions use these constraints.
So all the constraints are available to the state
machine mechanism, and that allows it to handle
all of this automatically and to automatically
assemble the compose the transaction that is needed.
So this is where the state machine
approach really, really plays out.
So basically it's just this one line.
And in the other case where the second
player has moved, and if you think we won
or if we know we won again, now we have
to reveal and it's just this one line.
So again, run step client with the
reveal FP nonce FP redeemer, that's
all, no constraints, no lookups nothing.
So this is much much simpler now.
And we don't need any helper
functions as we did before.
And same for the second player, it's just as short.
So a second game, the beginning is the same.
We lookup the public key hash.
We define our game parameter, we
defined the state machine client.
Then we use this get on-chain state again
to check the or the, UTxO that represents
the state machine, represents the game.
If we don't find it, that means no game is running.
If you do find it all this other piece of
information we could use, we don't need only the o.
And again, we use this typed version to grab the datum
and this case would mean that we haven't played yet.
So now we should play and other cases are unexpected.
So we expect that we can play and in order
to play, again, it's just one line of code.
We use run step and then the play, our choice redeemer.
And we wait as before until
the reveal deadline has passed.
We again, check the new state.
And now if there is none, that
means the first player has won.
So we don't do anything.
But if there is something that means
the first player hasn't won, and again,
just one line of code to claim our win.
And that's it.
So here it really shines the state machine approach.
It was already, I think, a bit shorter here in
the on-chain code, a bit more concise we needed
particularly we needed less helper functions.
We didn't have to worry about this
handling of the own input own output
and of the NFT that it's passed through.
But in the off-chain code it's really
dramatically simpler now and much more readable.
And the rest is exactly the
same, it's just copy paste it.
And what is particularly nice about
the state machine approaches is that we
don't have to replicate logic anymore.
I mean, earlier I explained that the on-chain
validation checks whether a transaction
is valid, whereas the off-chain code has
to construct a transaction that then will
pass these checks that validation does.
So on-chain and off-chain logic
has slightly different purposes.
On chain has to check, whereas
off-chain has to construct.
But by using this trick to specify the state
machine using the constraints, that can be used
for both for checking and for construction.
We now don't have to replicate this logic anymore.
So we only use the constraints and they
can be used to construct the transaction,
but also to check the transaction.
So in principle we have the
amount of code we need to write.
And we removed a lot of duplication.
In order to test this, I create this module
tests, state machine, and it's almost an
exact copy of the test module we saw earlier.
There's one small wrinkle.
First of all, of course, instead of importing
even on time now importing state machine.
But then there's one other difference.
And that is with the deadlines.
Earlier I use slot to begin POSIX time,
and now I'm using end and that is due
to a back in the state machine library.
And that has to do with this thing I mentioned,
I think two lectures ago already that the
underlying transactions use slots not POSIX time.
So when you go from off-chain to on-chain code,
you have to convert the validity intervals
into slots, and then back into POSIX times.
And because slots have a smaller granularity.
So I mean, one slot is one second.
You can't faithfully convert back and
forth, and that leads to problems.
So what I said earlier about constraints that
they self this dual purpose of specifying
validation in the on-chain part and
constructing transactions in the off-chain part.
This unfortunately at the moment is not
true due to this problem with a conversion.
So, if you're not careful, if you use a POSIX time that
lies at the beginning of a slot, then the transaction
that the state machine produces won't validate.
And I hope that will be fixed soon, but for the
time being, we can work around that by using
POSIX times that lie at the end of a slot.
So I had to change that, but everything
else should be exactly the same.
And if we try it out in the repl, then we should
get exactly the same result that we got before.
But with now using state machines.
So state machines are not always appropriate.
But when they are, you should definitely use them
because they dramatically reduce the amount of code
you have to write and also remove sources of error
because you avoid code duplication, basically the
state machine automatically takes care of guaranteeing
that the on-chain and the off-chain code fit together.
So the off-chain code will produce transactions
that then will be validated by the on-chain code.
And until now we always had
to take care of that by hand.
So big source of errors or backs is
removed and everything is much shorter.
Because a lot of the machinery to find, to
identify the right UTxO and to pass through
the state token is taken care of for you
automatically by the state machine mechanism.
Of course it's not always appropriate,
but when you have this module...
model that there's basically one specific UTxO that
carries some state in its datum and that transition.
So there are transactions that consume this
UTxO and produce a new one at the same address
with the possibly updated datum and value.
Then you should definitely ask yourself
whether you can model that as a state machine
and then use this state machine mechanism.
For homework.
I recommend that you modify this state machine
module and implement the rock paper scissors
game instead of this game we implemented.
And so the game definition can stay exactly the
same, but then for choices instead of zero one,
we have three choices, rock paper, and scissors.
And then the implementation of equality changes, of
course, rock equals rock, paper equals paper, scissors
equals scissors, nothing else equals anything else.
And I suppose it will be helpful to implement a
beats function that takes two of these choices and
then says whether the first one beats the second.
So rock beats scissors, paper beats rock,
and scissors beat paper, and that's all.
And I want you to reimplement the
game with these additional options.
So a lot is very similar.
The only difference of course is that
now there's also the possibility of a
draw if both players make the same move.
And in that case, of course,
this state should be split.
So each player should get his or her own stake back.
There's one more change you need
to make to the redeemer type.
Earlier, in the reveal case, we
only had to provide the nonce.
We didn't have to provide the actual
move that the first player made,
because he would only reveal if he won.
So if he made the same move
that the second player made.
So this was redundant information and we didn't
need it, but now we do need it because there are two
possibilities, what the first player could have done.
If he knows he lost, he won't reveal.
But he could reveal if he won, but also if it's a
draw, because if he doesn't reveal, even if it's a
draw, then the second player would get everything.
So the first player now must reveal
if he won or if it was a draw.
So in order to write down the correct conditions,
we now need the choice that the first player made.
And with that you need one more case in the
transition function to take care of this draw case.
And there are some slight modifications.
For example, now you need three of these
byteStrings instead of zero one, you need three
choices for how to represent rock paper scissors.
And also in the off-chain code there's a slight
change when you check what to do if there's a draw.
But everything is very similar.
So there are not a lot of changes needed.