Welcome to the second to last lecture of the
second iteration of the Plutus Pioneer Program.
This lecture is not about Plutus, but about
Marlowe, which is a domain specific language
for financial contracts built on top of Plutus.
And even though Marlowe has also changed
a little bit since the recording of
this lecture for the first iteration.
The changes are much smaller than
those that happen Plutus all the time.
So I decided to not update or edit this lecture
because I think it's still mostly accurate.
In the previous lectures we have learned about
all the important ingredients for writing
And in particular, the demo
at the end still works.
a Plutus application, we have first looked
at the extended UTXO model, the accounting
model that Cardano uses, and the addition
that Plutus brings to it, then we have talked
about on-chain validation about minting
policies, about writing off-chain code.
We have seen how to deploy smart
contracts and also how to test them.
And Plutus is a very powerful language,
so powerful in fact that you can
implement other languages on top of it.
So you can write an interpreter
in Plutus for other languages.
And one such language is Marlowe, which
is a so-called DSL (domain specific
language) for financial contracts.
And because this is the second to
last lecture of this course, I thought
you should do something special.
So I invited professor Simon Thompson who
is a very prominent figure in the Haskell
community and who leads the Marlowe team.
And one of his colleagues, Alex Nemish
to give guest lectures and tell us
a bit about Marlowe in this lecture.
And afterwards I will do a small demo of
the Marlowe playground and demonstrate
playing with a simple Marlowe contract.
Hi, I'm Simon Thompson from the Marlowe team.
And we are here this afternoon to
give you an introduction to Marlowe.
Let's get started.
So Marlowe is a special purpose language
for writing financial contracts on Cardano.
Now, why do we build special purpose languages?
Or sometimes we call them
domain specific languages?
One reason is that we want to build languages
that are closer to the language of the user
and not so much a language of the system.
So they're designed to be in a
specific domain of the application.
So a financial language
you're talking about payment.
For example, when we write a special
purpose language, we get some advantages.
You, we can write down things in that
domain, but we can't perhaps write as much
as we could in a general purpose language.
And if we do.
Work in this more specialized context, we have
the advantage of being able to give people better
feedback, better error messages, but also we
can give more guarantees on program behavior.
And that's one of the things I'm
going to stress in this lecture.
Okay.
What sorts of assurance can we give?
We can give two kinds of assurance really.
We can say, we can make sure that contracts
do what they're supposed to do, great?
But we can also make sure they
don't do what they shouldn't.
And we'll see both aspects of that as we go along,
we've designed the language to be as simple as
it can be and the implementation reflects that.
And I'll talk a bit about that in some more
detail later on, contracts are nice and
readable and also we can easily simulate them.
And so we can present to users a
very clear picture about how their
contracts in Marlowe will behave.
And in fact, if we can do more than that,
because they're particularly restricted, we
can, before a contract is executed, actually
explore every possible behavior path it can take.
So we can give complete guarantees
about how contracts will behave, not
just on one or two tests, but on the
every possible execution sequence.
And also it's more straightforward
to actually write mathematical
proofs of various kinds of safety.
So that's, if you like the strongest criteria
that we can hit in this kind of world, that we
have a mathematical proof that the system will
do certain things won't do wouldn't do others.
Okay.
But let's start by asking the question,
what does a financial contract do?
And let's think, let's step
back from what we see in the...
So what can a contract do?
Well, let's take a look at what various
things a contract can engage it.
It can accept payments from participants in
the contract, and according to things, choices
perhaps made by one of the participants,
it can evolve in different directions.
Do I sell or do I stick with the contract
for example, or it can make decisions
based on external information, such as the
information coming from an exchange, a stock
exchange or a currency exchange, for example.
So information coming from an Oracle can
determine the future behavior of a contract.
And finally the contract
can also make payments out.
If money has been deposited in the contract, it
could also make payments out to, to participants.
So we have payments, flows of money, we
have choices according to external factors.
And one final thing we have, the roles in a
contract are themselves things that can be owned.
So we represent that in Cardano, in Marlowe,
by minting tokens that represent those roles.
Now that means that we can use those
tokens as evidence that somebody
is meant to be playing a role.
So we can, there are a form of security,
a validation that the person submitting
a particular transaction is meant to be
able to submit that transaction it's fits
with their role, but also it means that
these roles can become themselves tradable.
So we can trade roles in a running contract.
I could transfer a role in a contract that I
have to you, perhaps for some money or indeed,
that role could be that token, could be traded
by another Marlowe contract or a Plutus contract.
So we use the native tokens to
represent roles in contract.
So we have roles, we have payments,
we have external choices, external
information coming in through Oracles,
so those are the general ingredients.
Now let's think about how to design a
language based on those ingredients.
And remember when we design
a language of contract.
What we're really doing is
designing a programming language.
A contract is just a smart contract is
just a program running on a blockchain.
So a contract in principle could run forever
and also more subtly, it could for example,
just get stuck waiting for an input forever.
If it's waiting for me to make a choice,
it could potentially wait forever.
It could also, as a program holding assets,
it could terminate holding onto those assets,
so we could lock up those assets forever.
And potentially, it could double spend I guess,
in principle, a program could try and do that.
So there's a whole lot of security issues that
a program might have, a contract might have.
So what we chose to do was design for safety.
So we designed first of all, for contracts
to be finite, their life will be finite,
there is no recursion or loops in Marlowe.
We'll come back to that a bit later
on when we talk about Marlowe being
embedded in other languages, but
Marlowe contracts themselves are finite.
More over, we can be sure
that contracts will terminate.
And we do that by putting timeouts on
every external action, every choice or
deposit of money into the contract comes
with a deadline, comes with a timeout.
And so Marlowe contracts cannot wait forever for
somebody to make a choice for an action to happen.
If you hit the timeout, then
an alternative course is taken.
And reading from a contract, because
we have these timeouts in the contract.
Each role contract will have a defined lifetime,
we can read that off from the timeouts.
So we have a very clear constraints on what
we can do, but that gives us safety built in.
And finally, we've designed the semantics of
the language so that when a contract reaches its
close at the end of its lifetime, any money left
in the contract will be refunded to participants.
So we built into the semantics into
the way the language is defined that no
money is retained when things terminate.
So we got those safety properties.
Your money is always going only going to be
committed for finite length of time, it will
always, if money is not spent by the contract,
it will be returned to its it's rightful owner.
Now conservation of value is something that we get
really for free from the underlying blockchain.
We can't, the underlying
blockchain guarantees double spend.
And because we're using the transaction mechanisms
of the underlying blockchain, we can be sure
that we are getting conservation of value.
Okay, so that's giving us a whole
lot of guarantees just after the box.
And these are not guarantees that there
are for Plutus contracts in general, in
general this is contract could go on forever.
It didn't need not terminate.
And it could terminate with having
control of a whole collection of assets,
which are, then become unreachable.
Okay.
So those just distress these, these properties
I'm highlighting here, are safety properties are
assurances that we can give to Marlowe users.
Now, what does the language look like?
Let's cut to the chase.
So Marlowe is at heart it's a represented
as a Haskell datatype and you can think
of, I'm sure you're familiar with datatypes
in Haskell, data types in Haskell, we can
think of a syntax of, of simple languages.
And let me just talk you through the
constructs that we have in the language.
We have a pay construct, and in that a party,
one of the parties in the contract makes
a payment to a pay of a particular value.
And then the contract continues.
We've  got what we call the continuation contract.
We can go in two separate directions, we
can observe whether or not a particular
observation is true or not, if the observation
is true, we follow the first contract, if the
observation is false, we follow the second.
So simple payment and then a simple
conditional the most complex construct
in Marlowe is the when construct.
And you can see it takes three arguments.
And the first of those is a list of action
contract pairs, a the list of cases.
And let's look at what that list represents.
Let's think what it represents,
what the when construct does, is
wait for one of a number of actions.
And when one of those actions happens,
it performs the corresponding contract.
So it could be waiting for a deposit, which,
if I have a case where the first part of
the case pair isn't deposit, then we will
execute the corresponding second part.
Similarly, with making a choice.
Similarly with getting a value from an Oracle.
So we, here we're waiting for external actions.
And of course the contract
can't make those actions happen.
A contract can't force somebody to make a choice,
it can't force somebody to make a deposit, but
what we can do is say, well, if none of these
actions takes place, no action taken place, no
corresponding contract, we will hit the timeout.
And when we hit the timeout, what
we'll do is perform this contract.
So we can guarantee that something will happen in
this construct, either because one of the actions
triggering a success of contract, or we simply
hit the timeout and go to that continuation.
So we know by the time we hit the
timeout, something will have happened.
We can't sit there waiting forever.
And then finally we have the close,
which has the semantics defined so
that nothing is retained when we close.
So there is the Marlowe language, a very
simple set of constructs, but we'll see
that we can use those in a variety different
ways that we can construct a Marlowe
contract in a variety of different ways.
Okay.
So there's the language, what
is the Marlowe product itself?
Well, what we have, is a suite of things.
And what I'm describing here is
the, the overall vision for Marlowe.
And I'm going to describe that and then
tell you where we are with fulfilling that.
So at the moment, what we have is you might have
seen, and I'm going to show you a demo shortly.
We have a prototype for Marlowe run, and that is
the system through which an end user will interact
with contracts running on the Cardano blockchain.
So if you like Marlowe run is the Marlowe Dapp.
It's the thing that allows
Marlowe contracts to be executed.
We're also building a market where
contracts can be uploaded, downloaded...
where we can provide various kinds
of assurance about those contracts.
We allow contracts to be simulated, interactively,
and then we call Marlowe play and we allow
contracts to be built in various different ways.
And we call that Marlowe build.
Now, in fact, what we've done at the moment
is bundle those two, Marlowe play and build
into what we call the Marlowe playground.
So as this, as things stand at the moment
,you can, it's been available for awhile.
Use the Marlowe playground to simulate
and construct Marlowe contracts.
We're in the process of redesigning the
user interface of that, the user experience.
On the basis of what we'd done with Marlowe run.
So we're able to build and
simulate Marlowe contracts.
What we're releasing very shortly
is the prototype of Marlowe run.
And this is the prototype of how
end users will interact with Marlowe
fine, with Marlowe on the blockchain.
And our intention is that we'll
have all these products available.
When running on the Cardano blockchain,
when we have the full support for this
on Cardano, which will involve having the
Plutus application backend and a wallet
backend and so on working as it should.
Okay.
Now what I'm going to do now, is just take a
short break and show you a demo of what we have
in Marlowe run to give you a sense of what we
can do with, at the moment, with giving users,
the experience that they will have when Marlowe
is running on blockchain, this will be the
app that is going to provide that experience.
At the moment it's running locally.
We will, in a few weeks time be releasing a
version that runs in a distributed version on a
simulated blockchain and then as we go into the
end of the end of the year, we expect to have this
running for real on the Cardano blockchain itself.
So let's go to the demo now.
Marlowe run runs in the browser, and what it
does is provide the end user interaction with
contracts running on the blockchain, for the
moment we're simulating a blockchain inside the
browser, but eventually this will be the tool
you'll use to run contracts for real on Cardano.
Now to interact with the contract, your
wallet needs to be involved to control
your signature and to control your assets.
So we link up Marlowe run with a wallet,
let's link it up with Shruti's wallet.
So in this window we see the world from
Shruti perspective and let's open up another
window and link in that window, the world
with Charles's perspective and at the moment,
neither of them has any contracts running.
They have a blank space there, but
let's take, let's start a contract up.
Let's setup a zero coupon bond,
which is a fancy name for a loan.
And let's suppose Shruti is
making a loan to Charles.
She's an investor, he's the issuer of the bond.
And Charles wants to borrow one ADA from
Shruti and he's promised to pay back 1.1 ADA.
So we set it up, we've said who
the issuer and investor are.
We said what the price and
the eventual value will be.
And we're now going to create the contract.
In order to do that, we have to make a payment
of 30 lovelace to get the contract started.
So let's pay and we've asked to approve
that and the payment goes through.
And you can see now in Shruti's Marlowe
run, we've got the zero coupon bond running,
but also if you look at Charles his view of
the world, it's running there too for him.
Let's see what it looks like for him.
We're at the first step and it's
saying it's waiting for something
from the investor who is Shruti.
So let's see what's happening in her view.
Yes, she's asked to make a deposit, so let's click
on that to make the deposit and click to confirm
with her fee of 10 lovelace and make that deposit.
And then you can see her view has changed.
Now she's waiting for the issuer to pay her back.
And Hey oh!
We look in Charles's view, he's incidentally
in the mobile view of Marlowe run.
He's asked to pay his 1.1 ADA.
Let's make him do that now.
And he'll also have to pay a 10 lovelace
transaction fee and let's make that deposit.
And you see now from both their
perspectives, that loan is completed.
You can see the history of what's gone on.
You can see at particular points,
the balances that the contract holds.
And in fact, we can, we close that.
We can see the history of all the
contracts that Shruti has taken part in.
And so I think that pretty much covers the
basics of what you get from Marlowe run.
It's a intuitive interface to a
contract running on the blockchain.
And you see that each participant in the
contract gets their view of the contract in real
time, updated from what's in this case, in the
browser, but eventually what's on the blockchain.
Okay.
So that's giving you an idea about what
Marlowe run looks like and let's now take
a look under the hood and see how it is
that Marlowe would be executed on Cardano.
Well, here's the diagram, just to give
you the context, I'm sure you understand
most parts of this diagram already.
We have a Cardano run node on which
Plutus is running and as you know, Plutus
is a dialect of Haskell more or less.
Now Marlowe is embedded in
Haskell and Marlowe compiles...
is executed using Plutus.
So Marlowe sits on top of Plutus, but it's
also linked to, in this Marlowe run and
attachment to a wallet, you'll be able
to, we'll be able to interact with as an
end user with a running Marlowe contract.
And also it gets linked to Oracles and so
on, sitting out there in the real world.
Now, what does it mean to
execute a Marlowe contract?
Again, I think this will be familiar to
you from your work with Plutus, but let's
just talk through precisely how it works.
Executing them on a contract will produce
a series of transactions on the blockchain.
And obviously what Plutus running on
cardano checks the validity of transactions.
We have a validation function and what's the
validation function for these Marlowe transactions
is essentially is a Marlowe interpreter, it checks
that the transactions indeed conform to what...
conform to the steps of
executing the Marlowe contract.
And that's done using the UTXO model.
So, we pass the current state of the contract
and some other information through as datum.
So the Marlowe interpreter uses that to ensure
that the transactions that are submitted, meet
the criteria for the particular Marlowe contract.
So that's the on-chain part.
Now will see off-chain.
There's a component as well,
so we have to have Marlowe run.
We'll have to build the transactions
that meet the validation step on-chain.
And if then when the contract requires crypto
assets, it will have to, we will have off-chain
to ensure that transactions are appropriately
signed so that we will have authorization
for spending crypto assets effectively.
So, using Marlowe run and a associated wallet,
we construct the transactions and we get a flow
of information in both directions, Marlowe run
will submit transactions to the blockchain that
then can be checked, validated by the Marlowe
interpreter, which is itself a Plutus contract.
It's the, it's one of the largest
Plutus contracts that exists.
But there's also information flow another way.
Cause suppose that the transaction I've submitted
is a deposit of money into a running contract.
And suppose the contract also
involves Charles Hoskinson.
So my instance of Marlowe run has submitted
that transaction, but Charles has also to
be notified about that and the information
flows in the other direction using the
companion contract to ensure that every
instance of this client, the Marlowe run,
gets informed about activity in that contract.
Alex, will talk some more about the details of
the implementation, but here you're seeing the...
here you're seeing an outline
of how it all, how it all works.
Transactions are validated on online through
the interpreter, but they have to be built
offline and in some cases have to be authorized.
And we use essentially the blockchain
is the central synchronization
point for the distributed system.
That is the collection of instances of
Marlowe run that are interacting to make
the contract, to execute the contract.
And you saw in the demo just before
that we could see in those two separate
windows, we were sharing information.
Now that was simulating it locally, but
in production, this will be information
that's stored on the blockchain.
Okay.
Now let's talk a little bit about how the
system is designed in a high-level way.
Here is a piece of the semantic of Marlowe.
And as you can see, It's a Haskell function.
We take an environment, current environment,
the current state take a contract we executed.
And based on what contract that is, is it a close,
is it a pay we can reduce, we can take some steps
of computing that the results of that contract.
And we do that in a way that uses Haskell in a
quite straightforward way to advance the contract.
And what we have is that this
specification in Haskell is an executable
specification of the semantics.
And this is..
This gives us some very nice consequences.
We've got, if you like, we've got the denotation
or we've got a high level description of what
the semantics is, and we're doing that through
something that is effectively an interpreter.
So we're defining at a high level,
this interpreter which an interpreter
in Haskell for Marlowe contracts.
Now, one really nice thing about writing
it in this sort of way is that we can be
sure we, we cover all cases because it's
a it will be obvious if we're missing
some cases, writing it as something that's
an interpreter ensures that we will hit.
We'll hit all cases we need to
in describing the semantics.
And also it really helps us
to understand the semantics.
So this a...
it's a really...
when you're designing a language, Okay.
You have an, you have an abstract idea
about how you're going to, what it's
going to mean, but there's nothing
like having an implementation of it.
So you can actually run the semantics.
You say, well, what would it mean
if we were to add this construct?
What would it mean if we were to
modify the semantics in this way?
Now, if you'd written it in a purely, purely
logical format, it's difficult to unscramble
just from the rules as they're laid out,
what precisely a change in rule might mean.
Here, it's straightforward
we can run the semantics.
So we got this specification in Haskell,
and what's even nicer is that we can reuse
this semantics in a number different ways.
So in the theorem prover Isabelle, we can
use the semantics for reasoning and proof.
And we use pretty much the
same semantics, Isabelle uses a
functional language as it's subject.
We can run the semantics in Plutus.
It was written in Haskell initially, but
Plutus is more or less Haskell, perhaps
not with all the libraries but, we can in
principle, at least build our implementation
on blockchain from our semantics.
And also we can translate the semantics into
pure script for simulation in the browser.
Now pure script is not the same,
exactly the same as Haskell.
Isabelle's language is not
How can we be sure that all
these versions are the same?
Well, one way of doing it, is to extract
Haskell code from Isabelle and test the
original against this extracted code.
And we do that on random contracts and
that's, it gives us a pretty high level
of assurance that the two are the same.
And down the line in our in our roadmap,
we certainly expect to be using a Haskell
in JavaScript implementation at some point
to replace pure script in the frontend.
So we don't have to write a pure script
version of the semantics when we're doing
the off-chain interpretation, building the
transactions to be submitted, we can use the
actual real Haskell implementation by coding
it, compiling it into JavaScript and running
that in Marlowe run, in the client code.
So building a language in Haskell has
given us these consequences that we use
various different versions of the semantics.
We can be...
we can get a high level of assurance that
these are all the same, and indeed we can
in some situations replace things like the
JavaScript by the pure script by JavaScript.
Okay.
So that gives us a picture about
how the system is put together.
Let's go to another aspect of Marlowe, which I
talked about it being a special purpose language
about it being a DSL and that promoted usability.
Let me say a bit more about that.
One way we promote usability is that we
provide different ways of writing contracts,
different ways of authoring contracts.
And another way we promote usability
is to be allowed people to explore
interactively how contracts behave before
they're actually run in a simulation.
So let's talk about those now.
Again, emphasizing these are another
facet of assurance for the language.
We want to write a Marlowe
contract, how can we do it?
Well, we can write Haskell...
Marlowe, the Haskell Marlowe datatype as checks.
That's one way we can do it and that's fine
and we have an editor for that inside the
playground that gives that has completion that
has holes, which will, will support completions,
will make suggestions and so on.
So we can build a Marlowe contract as pure
Marlowe, but there are other routes as well.
We have a visual editor for Marlowe, so that
you can produce Marlowe contracts visually with
putting together blocks in a way that doesn't
require you to be a confident programmer.
You can start off by using the visual
version as a way of learning Marlowe
as a way of, of engaging with it.
If you are a coder perhaps in Haskell,
perhaps in JavaScript, Marlowe is
embedded in Haskell and in JavaScript.
So we can use facilities in Haskell like recursion
or JavaScript to describe Marlowe contracts.
So we can say in Haskell let's...
we want to do this particular pattern of behavior
and times, and we can write that in Haskell.
And then for a particular contract,
we convert the Haskell into Marlowe.
We, as it were compile this Haskell description
of a Marlowe contract into pure Marlowe.
And we can also do that for JavaScript.
So we have that, that facility.
And then finally something I'm not going to
talk about any more in this talk is that we
can generate contracts from initial conditions.
And we've been looking at that for the
actor standard of financial contracts.
So we generate on the basis of simply
contract terms we generate code in Marlowe.
So we write functions whose
output is Marlowe code.
So we provide users with as well as simply writing
pure Marlowe, we provide them with a variety
of different approaches, leveraging knowledge
of JavaScript, for example, or leveraging a non
code based approach for describing the contracts.
And.
Also, we allow people to simulate
the behavior of contracts.
Now, this is something that you can see in
the current version of the Marlowe playground.
I've taken a screenshot of that.
That's something you can play with yourselves.
What I would say is that I, we
are looking at different ways of
describing the results of a simulation.
So at the moment we have a transaction log,
we are allowed to choose an action, the next
action to perform, you can perform that.
You can undo the last step to take
you back and then try another path.
So you can step interactively backwards
and forwards through the source code,
through the application of the contract.
What we're looking at is changing the user
interface, changing the UX for the Marlowe
playground, Marlowe run and Marlowe play.
So that we'll use something
rather more like the Marlowe run.
Description of a running contract, so that
you'll see the steps as a series of cards
like this, but that's work in progress.
Okay.
So we talked about usability.
What about the sort of assurance
that Marlowe can give users?
There are two gen apart from the things
we've seen already, we've seen that
making the system transparent, making
code readable is itself an advantage.
We've seen that there's simulation to
give people the ability to understand, to
validate their intuition about a contract,
but rather more formally, we can use the
power of logic to do two things for us.
We can do what's called static analysis.
So we can automatically verify
properties of individual contracts.
So that means we can guarantee this
contract will behave as it should
checking every route through the contract.
And also we can do machine supported proof.
So not automatic any longer written
by written by a user, but we can prove
properties of the overall system.
Let's talk about those two now.
What about static analysis?
Well, what static analysis allows us to
do is check all execution paths through a
Marlowe contract, all choices, all choices
of slots for a submission of a transaction.
So every possible way in which the
contract might be executed, we examine.
And the canonical example here is the example
of whether a pay construct might fail.
Is it possible a pay construct could fail.
And the answer is that we will, we have,
we use what's called an SMT solver.
It's an automatic logic tool that you
have powerful logic tool called Z3 is
the one we use, others are available.
That effectively checks all execution paths.
And what it does is, if the property is
satisfied, that's fine, we get the results.
Yes, it's satisfied.
If it's not satisfied, we get a counterexample,
we get told here's a way, here's a path through
this contract that leads to a failed payment,
a failed payment that can't be fulfilled.
So here's an example of how it can go wrong.
And that's really helpful because it means that
you can debug if you don't, if, if you really want
to make sure that failed payment can't happen,
then this gives you a mechanism to understand,
and to debug how that eventuality happens.
And so gives you a chance to
think about how to avoid it.
So very powerful and entirely push of a  button.
You push a button and you get the results
and here you can see just again, to
emphasize these here's the assurance.
We can do this high-level check
through all execution paths.
So here you see a fragment of a Marlowe
contract, a escrow contract, where the
contract starts with a deposit of 450 Lovelace.
And checking the analysis in the playground,
we got the results, static analysis could not
find any execution that results in any warning.
So that's saying you're okay, it's not going
to give you a warning, whatever you do.
But if we change that deposit of 450 lovelace
to a deposit of 40 and analyze, we then get
this warning, we get a transaction partial
payment, and we're told we get to a payment where
we're meant to pay 450 units of ADA Lovelace.
But there are only 40 available and we get
given a list of transactions that take us there.
So we're able to see from
that, how we got to that.
And the problem is that we didn't put
enough money in, and then we reached a place
where we needed to make a payment for 150.
So it's easy for us to see that we need to
either make a payment smaller or the initial
deposit bigger, but it's entirely pushed buttons.
So, we do get that sort of
assurance for free as it were.
But thinking about verification, we can do
rather more than that, we can do proof things,
prove properties of the system once and for all.
So for example, just looking on the left-hand
side here, we can prove accounts, local accounts
inside a Marlowe contract, as it execute.
We can prove from the semantics that
these accounts never go negative.
You can't ever overdraw an account in a
Marlowe contract, and we can also prove
this theorem of money preservation.
We can prove that if we look at all the money
that's gone into the contract so far, that's
equal to the sum of two things, the amount of
money that's in accounts held inside the contract,
plus the amount of money that has been paid out.
And that's, that gives a clear
picture of money preservation.
So we're able to we're able to write proofs of
these very general properties of the system.
Now we're also able to prove other
more technical things about the system.
So for example, that a close construct
will never produce any warnings.
So if we're analyzing for warnings, we
don't need to worry about close constructs.
So that allows us to optimize the static analysis.
And we're also able to prove that the
static analysis, the way it works, which
is makes a number of simplifications to
speed things up is sound and complete.
That means the static analysis will give us an
error warning when the real contract can generate
an error warning, and it won't give us an error
warning if the real contract can't do that.
And one thing that we haven't done, but
we'll, you know, is again on our roadmap.
Is what we can do these sorts of proofs
for individual contracts or individual
contract templates to, things that we can't
necessarily prove with static analysis,
we can prove by proving that by hand.
So.
High-level assurance we get, you know, if
you're prepared to write proofs, the system
is amenable to being, having these proofs
written about it, and they give us the
highest level of assurance about how it works.
So, I think I've said enough for the moment
about Marlowe, where can you go to find out more?
Well, there's a Marlowe GitHub repository that
has the semantics and the basics about Marlowe.
Quite a lot of the implementation of the
tools for Marlowe are in the Plutus repository
because it has that repository as a dependency,
so we include it in that repository.
So that's where you can find
out, find the code itself.
If you look in the IOHK online research
library and search for Marlowe, you'll
find a number of research papers.
We've written about how the system works.
You'll also find an online
tutorial in the Marlowe playground.
And finally, Alex is going to give some more
information in his presentation coming up next.
So just to summarize what we have in Marlowe,
is it a DSL, a special purpose language for
financial contracts running on top of Plutus
because it's a DSL, it gives us assurance.
It allows us to give the assurance that it's
harder to give for a general purpose language.
And also it allows us to orient its
designed around users as well as developers.
And also we get assurance of contracts behave
as they should and don't do what they shouldn't,
that's some of that is built into the way
that the language is designed, the language
is simple and therefore we get readability,
we also get simulator ability and
we get these stronger assurances of
static analysis and verification.
So, okay.
Thanks very much for listening.
And here's the link to go and see the Marlowe
playground in action, thanks very much.
Hello, my name is Alex Nemish,
I'm one of the Marlowe developers.
And today I'm going to show you a bit
of Marlowe semantics and a part of
PAB contracts, Marlowe PAB contracts.
That'd be I'm going to use, I'll start with
a brief description of Marlowe semantics.
That's implemented in this semantics dot HS file.
And then I'll show you the PAB contracts.
I assume you're familiar with Haskell, you're
familiar with Marlowe semantics in a high level.
And I expect you to see the Lars presentations.
So I expect you to know how PAB works and in a
nutshell, and how state machine library works
and state machine library based contracts.
Well, get started.
Here are the main datatypes for Marlowe.
It's a contract, essentially those
are six constructors that you
construct Marlowe contract with.
And here is the state that is going
to be ah stored on a blockchain.
So we have a state of
balances of accounts by party.
Here we start the choices.
Part is made here we start bound variables
that are essentially let bindings.
And here his main slot is essentially
a first slot that the contract sees and
this just to prevent to go back in time.
The input datatype contains essentially actions
for a Marlowe contract, it's either deposit or
choice or any notification of a slot change.
And here is the.
Here is the transaction input data type.
That's what we give as an input.
So we have a slot interval, so everything's
action must be, must have a defined
slot interval and the list of inputs.
So you can combine multiple inputs within a
single transactions, you can make multiple
deposits or choices and notifications and
we get the transaction output which contains
the payments that we expect to happen.
The output state and the output contract
result in a state and result in a contract.
Here's the Marlowe data.
That's essentially, what's going
to be stored on a blockchain.
So it's a current state of a
contract and the external contract.
So the main function, the main entrance to
the semantics is compute transaction function.
That's, that gets transactional inputs...
current state, current contract,
and gives the transaction output.
First of all we fix the interval, we
check the slot interval for errors.
For example, we disallow slot interval
to contain any timeouts inside.
So for example, if you have a contract
with a when construct with a slot 10, for
example, you cannot produce a transaction
that has a slot interval from 5 to 15, because
it's going to contain a timeout inside of
it, is going to be invalid slot interval.
So here we check this, then we apply all inputs.
If it's successful, we return the
transaction output with warnings.
We found the payments we expect,
new state and say continuation.
So what happens in apply all inputs?
Essentially, it's a loop that first of all
reduces current contract until is quiescent.
And then when we get this quiescent
state, we take first input and try
to apply it until we get applied.
And, essentially continue with this loop.
If it's applied successfully, until
we get an empty input list, then we
return current state and continuation.
Reduce contract until quiescent is essentially
function that again goes through a loop and
tries to apply reduce contract step function
which essentially evaluates a contract.
So if we get a close, then we
are in the quiescent state.
If we get a payment, we have eval value that
balances and return that the contract was reduced.
Do the same with if, let and assert but
for when we only evaluate it if it's timed
out, otherwise we say it's not reduced.
So when we get this not reduced, then
we say that the contract is quiescent.
So, in a nutshell Marlowe contract
evaluation consists of two steps.
We reduce current contract until it's
quiescent, so essentially it's either closed
or we get to a when that's not timed out yet.
And second part, we try to apply inputs
and evaluate the contract further.
Okay.
Let's see how it works from the client side, as
you might have noticed, the Marlowe semantics
code is quite abstract and it does not
depend on the Cardano transactions and stuff.
So let's take a look at the actual Marlowe
validator and that's been executed on-chain.
So here's the script instance, essentially
it just calls this make Marlowe validator
code, that uses the state machine library
makes that machine call and provides two
functions state transition function, and
finally to check for a state machine.
So finally to check is very simple.
We just check the current contract is
close, then the state machine is done
and the state machine transition function
is the actual meat of the validator.
So it receives some Marlowe params data type,
we're going to talk a bit later, current
state of the state machine, Marlowe data.
Marlowe input, this is essentially a
transaction input expressed in Cardano types.
And it's going to return either nothing in
case of an error or a set of transaction
constraints that must apply to validate the
transaction and in you state a new Marlowe
data, continuation contract and completed state.
So here we check that valid
as the balances are valid.
So we require balances in a state
to be positive, here we produce an
input constraints given these inputs.
So in case of deposits, we expect money go
into a contract and case of choices we expect
signatures or witnesses of respective parties.
We calculate the total balance that the
contract claims that contains and we check
that it actually contains these values.
We construct in turn section input, given this
slot interval and list of inputs, and we call
the computer transaction functions that we
saw in semantics that we choose and we given a
computed result, we can start in Marlowe data
with a new contract continuation and our data
state and produce an output constraints that
contain payouts to the respective parties.
And we calculate new balance, a new total balance.
Given the income and outcome
of a transaction and inputs.
And we combine all those
constraints with a range validation.
When validating inputs, we check that there
are signatures from parties presented by public
key hashes, and there is a spending of role
tokens for parties that represent it by arrow.
Payments to parties go either by checking the
result transaction output goes to a public
key for all, for all the four parties that
presented by public hashes or the payment goes
to role payout validator hash that is a custom
validator that you can provide on your own
within Marlowe params, or we have a default one.
This is the role payout validator that
is used by default, it simply checks
that a transaction contains a spending
of a role token given a currency.
For off-chain execution we provide three Marlowe
PAB contracts, Marlowe follower contract, Marlowe
control contract, and Marlowe companion contract.
Let's go through all of those.
Let's start with Marlowe follower contract.
It's a very simple one it contains the
only one endpoint called follow and it
basically subscribes to a validator address,
a Marlowe contract address, essentially.
And it subscribes to all changes to this address.
So we get all the transactions that span, span
transaction output with this Marlowe contract.
So we can store all the inputs, all the
inputs that are applied to a Marlowe contract.
So here you can see that we call
the update history from transaction
that in a nutshell finds an input.
Marlowe inputs in the transaction and if
it finds it, it constructs a transaction
input datatype and update the PAB
contract state with this transition.
So if you're connected to a web socket of this
contract, you will be notified about state
transition changes and this state of this
contract called contract history, it essentially
stores an initial Marlowe params, initial
Marlowe data, and the list of all transaction
inputs that were applied to this contract.
And you can always restore the
latest state by applying list of
transaction inputs to an initial state.
This contract is used by Marlowe run to
show a Marlowe contract execution history.
And you can use it for same purposes on your own.
This Marlowe Plutus contract is essentially
a control contract, it allows you to create
a Marlowe contract, an instance of Marlowe
contract apply inputs to the instance.
Auto execute the contract if it's possible.
Redeem tokens from payments to roles,
to your role, by spending transaction
output protected by role pay out validator
script, or just close this contract.
Let's go through Marlowe contract creation.
So when you're calling the create
endpoint, you provide an actual Marlowe
contract to be created and a map of roles
to public keys of role token owners.
So what happens here is we
need to setup Marlowe params.
Let's take a look at this data type.
So Marlowe params is a way to parameterize
a Marlowe contract, and the following
way you can specify your own role
payout validator by providing its hash.
So you can write anything you want, we have
a default one that checks that the role token
is spent within transaction, but you can
do whatever you like, and you can do this
by specifying this hash in Marlowe params.
Also when your contract uses roles we need
to know a currency symbol of a role currency.
So you specify it here.
So when we create a new contract that uses
roles as parties, we need to create new currency
and distribute role tokens to their owners.
That's why we need this map of role
tokens to their, to their owners.
So let's take a little bit a look at
the setup Marlowe params function.
So what happens here?
We get roles that are used within this contract.
And if we have roles and we have
owners or provided for these roles,
we create tokens with role names.
By default, we create a one token per role.
Then we use these forge contract function.
That's essentially we reusing other PAB contracts.
This one is from currency contract
that trades in you new currency, and
all these tokens go to the creator.
So whoever creates a Marlowe contract
gets, initially gets all the roles for this
contract, but we get roles symbol from that.
And we immediately within the same transaction,
send transactions that creates Marlowe contract
with distribute role tokens to their owners.
So I give them to respective parties and
we create Marlowe params that contains
the role symbol, a currency symbol of
currency we just created for role tokens.
Currently we use the default role payout
validator hash, so this is how, this is a
setup constraints that create a new currency
and distribute all tokens and create
transaction output with the Marlowe data.
So we use state machine library to create state
machine client, and we construct a transaction
that distribute tokens and create a transaction
output with the Marlowe data and pay value.
And this is a deposit value currently zero,
but at later point is going to be a some value.
I believe it's going to be one ADA.
All transaction outputs must contain some ADA.
And it's just to...
essentially it's preventing the DDoS attacks
and we submit this transaction, that's the
way we create a Marlowe contract on-chain.
Apply endpoint it's very simple, apply
inputs endpoint, just calls this apply
inputs, which is very very straightforward.
We construct this slot range and we use
state machine library or run step to
run a state machine transition function.
When we provide Marlowe input, which
is a pair of slot range and list of
Marlowe inputs, a list of inputs.
Redeem endpoint allows you to get money from
the that has been paid to a role payout script.
So we get this address, given a roles currency
and spend all this outputs to a token owner.
Auto is quite interesting
little complicated thing.
There is a set of contracts that
can be executed automatically.
Imagine any contract that contains
only deposits and payouts.
So if this contract is eligible,
so no participant needs to provide
choices or any like interactive stuff.
So only scheduled payments.
These contracts can be executed automatically,
this is, this endpoint allows exactly that.
So if the contract can be executed automatically
for a party, we call auto execute contract.
This is essentially a state machine
that pays deposit or wait for
other parties to do their part.
The last interesting contract
is Marlowe companion contract.
This is a contract that monitors a
participant wallet and notifies when
a role token goes to your own address.
So with trans, it listens to transactions that
go to your own address and if there is a token
and this token is generated by Marlowe contract
creation, it tries to find the Marlowe contract.
And if it succeeds, it notifies this
contract need updates its state.
And again, if you're subscribed to
this contract web socket, you'll get a
notification about a role token and you'll
get Marlowe params and Marlowe data.
So if you check this Marlowe companion,
the state, this essentially a map
of Marlowe params to Marlowe data.
So it can always get notified
about receiving their role token.
Hope this helps.
Thank very for much for listening.
Thank you very much Simon and Alex for these
very nice introductions and explanations to
Marlowe, they thought it would be nice if we
play a bit with Marlowe in the playground.
And when you go to the playground, by the
way, I went to a different version than
the one Simon showed in his lecture on his
slides, because there was a problem with
that one right now, but this one works.
So it's alpha dot Marlowe dot IOHK dev dot IO.
And when you go there, you first get presented
with three options in which language you
want to write your Marlowe contracts.
So you can do it in Haskell.
You can do it in JavaScript, or you can
do it in Blockly or directly in Marlowe.
So let's first look at this option because
this is very nice and you don't need
any programming experience to do this.
So I start a new project and pick blocky,
this is a graphical editor, so we can just
click and drop a Marlowe contract together.
And as an example, I want to write a
contract where there are three parties,
Alice, Bob and Charlie, and the idea is
that Alice and Bob deposit an amount of
ADA into the contract, let's say 10 ADA.
And then Charlie decides whether
Alice or Bob gets the total amount.
And depending on Charlie's decision,
either Alice gets 20 or Bob gets 20.
I know, of course there's always the possibility
that one of the three doesn't play along.
And Alice doesn't make her deposit
Bob doesn't make his deposit, or
Charlie doesn't make his choice.
In which case everybody should just get
reimbursed what they have paid up to that point.
So when we start with Blockly, there is a
contract and it's just a close contract which
in this case doesn't do anything, if there
was money in internal accounts, it would pay
back the money to the owners of the accounts.
But you want to do something else.
So let's first wait for a deposit by Alice
and because that's a external action, that's
triggered by one of the parties in this case
Alice, we need this when construct that Simon
mentioned, and we can slide that into here and we
see all the slots where other things need to go.
And we see some fields that we have to set,
so let's start here, so we can set a timeout.
So let's say this deposit by
Alice has to happen until slot 10.
And if it doesn't happen, we can
say what should happen afterwards.
And there's not really a good choice to
do anything except close in that case.
So in that case, nothing will happen.
So we can slide that in there.
So now here we say what
external actions we wait for.
Let's say we only wait for one action,
namely that Alice makes her deposit
so we can check for actions and pick
the deposit one and slide it in here.
And we see a couple of slots we have to fill.
First of all, who has to make the deposit?
That's a party and there are
two choices, public key or role.
Let's take role, because then I can just say Alice
normally this would be the name of the role token.
So whoever owns the token
can incorporate that role.
Okay.
So Alice makes a deposit.
Now the amount that's a value, and let's say
we just pick a constant amount of 10 ADA.
So the amount is 10 and that it is ADA we
must specify here in the currency slot.
There's also the option to use other
tokens than ADA, but let's stick with ADA.
Okay.
Now there are these internal accounts
that also belong to one of the parties.
So let's say Alice pays it
into her own internal account.
I just copy pasted this, and now
we must save what happens next.
If Alice makes this deposit.
So afterwards we want Bob to make a deposit.
So I can just copy this whole when block
here and slide it in here and now change.
So, first of all, I changed the timeout to 20.
So to give Bob also 10 slots to do something,
and then wherever I said, Alice, I now say Bob.
So at this point, if both these actions
happen, Alice has deposited 10 into
her internal account and Bob has
deposited 10 into his internal account.
So now we want Charlie to make a choice.
So we need...
and this is again an external action.
So again, we need a when.
And I put the thing here, but
this time it's not a deposit.
So let me delete the deposit, but
let's change the timeout to 30 to give
Charlie 10 slots to make his choice.
And now I need a different
action where earlier had deposit.
Now I pick the choice action.
I can give it a name, let's say
winner,  I must say who makes the choice.
So that's supposed to be Charlie.
And now I must specify what
values this choice can have.
And that's numeric.
So somehow, because Charlie is supposed to choose
between Alice and Bob so that's two choices.
So I can pick arbitrary values like one
and two, one for Alice, two for Bob.
So that's already the default, so that's fine.
So this allows Charlie to only choose one or two.
And then after he has made the choice,
if he has made the choice, we continue.
And now it depends, of course,
on what choice Charlie has made.
If he chose Alice, then Alice must
get all the money if she chose Bob,
then Bob must get all the money.
So here in this continue contract, we now
can use if simple conditional slided in here.
So first we need the observation.
So we must somehow check whether the
choice was, let's say one for Alice.
So this is an observation and there is
value, equality is one of the options.
So we want to compare the choice that Charlie made
with one or two doesn't matter, but let's say one.
So value.
There is this one, which gives
us the value of a choice.
So here we need the name.
Again, so winner was her name for that
choice because there can be several choices.
So we must be able to distinguish between them.
And we again need who made that choice.
So this is now either one or two, and
we can compare to, for example, one,
so we can use the constant value one.
Okay.
And in this case, so if this is
true, then Charlie chose Alice.
So we want Alice to get all the money.
So in the then branch, we can now take a pay
contract, the payee is who gets the money.
And now we have two choices that can be an
internal account, or it can be an external party.
And in this case, it doesn't matter because
in the end, when we close all the parties get
the money from the internal accounts as well.
So I, it doesn't matter, I can just pick the
internal account, Alice's internal account.
So let's do that pick Alice.
So this now means that the payee
is Alice's internal account.
Now how much, is this constant 10, the amount
that Bob paid in currencies ADA and now who pays.
And that must be an internal account because
this is something that this pay contract is
something that contract has control over.
So that's not an external action.
So payments are triggered from internal accounts
that are under the control of the contract.
And that in this case is Bob's account.
So this now says if Charlie picked one, which
stands for Alice, then pay from Bob's internal
account 10 ADA to Alice's internal account.
And afterwards we can just close and
when we close all the internal accounts
will be paid to the external owners.
So at this point Alice's internal
account will have 20 ADA.
And when we close, she will
get the 20 ADA paid out.
Okay.
And else, this is now if Charlie didn't
choose Alice, if he chose Bob where then we
must do the same, but with reverse roles.
So let me copy paste this whole pay
thing and just exchange Bob and Alice.
And this should do it.
Now we can, for example, look at the pure Marlowe.
So this is now the value, what I did graphically
as a Marlowe value, a value of the Haskell data
type called Marlowe or called contract, actually.
And I can send it to the simulator
and I can start the simulation.
And now whenever there is a when, so
when they are available actions, I
get prompted, which of those to take.
In our case, we always only had one
available action at every point.
So in the first when, there are only two
possibilities, either Alice makes her deposit
or she doesn't until the timeout is reached.
So in this case, if we wait for the timeout,
it's very boring, the contract is over,
it's reduced to close and nothing happened.
So if she makes the deposit,
then this contract simplifies.
So it's now reduced to what happens after she
made the deposit and we see now when in the second
when, where we're waiting for Bob's deposit.
And again, he can choose not to deposit.
So if he does that, then we see here the
actions, Alice deposits a 10 and then
after the timeout, because Bob din't do
anything, the contract paid 10 back to Alice.
Okay.
Of course it's more interesting
if Bob also makes his deposit.
So we see that logged here as well.
And now we are, the contract has simplified again.
So now we are in the when where the only
available action is that Charlie chooses.
So Charlie can not choose one or two,
if he chooses or don't do anything.
If he doesn't do anything, Bob and Alice,
both get her money, the money back.
If he picks Alice.
So choice one, then we see that the
contract pays 20 units of ADA to Alice.
So she gets all the money.
And if instead we pick two, then
the contract pays 20 units to Bob.
So it seems to work.
Let me reset this now and let me copy this
Marlowe contract and do a new project and go to
the Haskell edit once that, and let's not save.
And here in this Haskell
editor, there's a template.
Basically all this Haskell program does, is it
takes a contract, this is a Marlowe contract.
And then it's a simple executable, a Haskell
executable that just pretty prints the contract.
So all it does is it basically produces
a nicely printed value of type contract.
And this is then used to, for
example, running the simulator.
So we should be able to simply instead of
close pastes, this expression here that we got
from our Blockly, probably I should indent.
Okay.
And that should compile so I can compile
this and I can send it through the simulator
and it should behave exactly as before.
So Alice makes a deposit, Bob makes his deposit.
Let's say Charlie picks
Bob and Bob gets the money.
So, there we don't really see
a benefit of do it in Haskell.
We could just do it in Blockly.
Although I find that Blockly is really
only useful for learning and for writing
extremely simple contracts, because this
is arguably a simple contract and already
it was quite unwieldy in the blocky editor.
And if you do something slightly more complicated,
it gets really very confusing in the editor.
But the point is we can do other
things in this Haskell program as well.
We don't have to literally define a contract.
We can use the whole power of Haskell
to help us write this contract.
So for example, if we see there's lots
of repetition, because we always have
these roles, Alice, Bob and Charlie.
So for example, we can define them separately,
let's just say Alice, Bob, Charlie.
The type is party and the role constructor we
can just use this overloaded string here to skip
the role constructor and just write it like this.
So party implements is string and the from
string method uses the role constructor Charlie.
Okay.
And now I can replace this everywhere with those.
Yes.
Well, and I can do the same for Bob and Charlie.
Okay, I think I have all the places.
Now I can do the same, this
constant tennis all over the place.
So let's give that a name as well, let's
call it deposit and that's of type value.
Okay, this token empty empty is
the ADA abbreviation for that.
Okay, and there's slightly more computation...
duplication this choice ID, so let's also
give that a name choice ID type choice ID.
And that takes two parameters, the name, which was
winner in our case and the role which is Charlie.
Okay, now it's already cleaned up quite a bit.
And now it's also easy to do more
sophisticated things, for example, our
contract is slightly asymmetric, even
though it sounds like a symmetric situation.
I mean, Alice and Bob are completely symmetric,
but in our contract, Alice has to deposit first.
And what we could do instead is
allow Bob to deposit first as well.
So in the outermost when we have two cases, one
where Alice deposits and one where Bob deposits,
so we can of course just now copy this case
here and paste it below and change Alice and
Bob where appropriate, which is not everywhere
because in this choice thing here, Alice keeps
being choice one and Bob keeps being choice
two, so would have to concentrate on that.
But of course it's much nicer to
extract that into a helper function.
So this is of type case.
So let me just copy paste or copy this
until there and now make a local definition.
And I don't know what to call it.
Let's just call it F and it takes two
parties, the party that deposits first
and the party that deposits afterwards.
And it gives us a case, let's call it X and
Y and just paste this whole thing there.
Okay, and now of course, I
am not using the X and Y.
So in this case, Alice was first.
So Alice is X and after Alice
is deposit, we wait for Bob.
Okay.
And this here can stay the same, this choice.
And now I can replace this whole thing with
my helper function and write F Alice Bob.
And the advantage is that I know
it's not easy to also add a symmetric
case that Bob can deposit first.
So I just add a new line
with another case, Bob Alice.
And if all goes well, that should still compile.
And if I now send it to the simulator and
start the simulation, now I have two possible
actions that can happen in the first step.
Alice can deposit 10 or Bob can deposit 10.
So let's Bob start this time.
So Bob deposits 10 and now it's Alice's turn.
And if Charlie picks Alice
then as before Alice wins.
So the point I'm making is that, it's of
a big advantage to use the Haskell editor,
to write Marlowe contracts in Haskell.
So basically you write a program that
produces something of type contract, and
you can use all the features of Haskell
like local functions or whatever to make
your life easier and avoid code duplication.
And in the Blockly editor, there's no such option
if we had wanted to do the same in Blockly because
there are no local definitions that you can do.
You can't define local contracts
or something like that.
So we would have to paste,
copy paste this whole big case.
And then manually change Alice to Bob in
Bob to Alice in the first two deposits.
And we would have lots of code duplication because
this choice thing here the third when, would have
been copy pasted, and there would have been no way
to abstract that the way and only write it once.
And of course you have other options, for
example, we could also parameterize our contract.
So for example, we could use the Leaf, the
deposit variable, so we could, instead do a
contract is a function from value to contract.
And the first parameter is deposit and I delete
this here and now in the main program I can
pick a value for the parameter, for example, 50.
And now if I compile, oh,
sorry, it must be constant 50.
So now if I compile.
I have a version of the contract when now
Alice and Bob have to deposit 50 ADA each.
And then the winner gets 100 and obviously
I could do the same for the parties.
So I could parameterize it over the
three parties, party, party, party.
And then if I call those Alice, Bob and Charlie.
Delete this here.
Then I must also be careful and
this must not depend on the party.
It's called P and at the appropriate
spot here where the choice happens,
I must say choice ID Charlie.
Here as well and now the contract is
parameterized by all the participants.
So instead of Alice, Bob and Charlie, I can
use Charles, Simon and Alex and a constant 100.
Do now.
Oh yes, just a parenthesis problem.
Okay.
And now I have Charles and
Simon and deposits of 100.
And Alex picks the winner.
And it works as before.
So it's just very nice and easy to using
Haskell parameterizing contracts and saving
a lot of code duplication by just using
usual Haskell thing features like local
definitions, helper functions, and so on.
I could even relatively easily generalized
this to more than three participants.
Maybe there are three people, I could even write a
contract that's generic in the number of parties.
So I get a list of parties and
then each of them has to deposit.
And that would be very inconvenient if
I had to do that by hand, but just using
Haskell, it's quite straightforward.
And what is also noteworthy here is that Marlowe
in contrast to Plutus is extremely basic Haskell.
So the Marlowe team made a point of only using
very basic Haskell functions when features.
So you don't need lenses, you
don't need template Haskell.
You don't even need Monads type level programming.
All of that is not present in Marlowe,
it's extremely basic standard Haskell.
So after what you have learnt while learning
Plutus about Haskell, Marlowe should be a walk in
the park for you and a very relaxing and simple.
Of course Marlowe is not always appropriate
because it's specifically for financial contracts.
But if it is appropriate, it's a very nice
option because of all the safety assurances
that Simon mentioned and because it's much
simpler and easier to get right than Plutus.
For homework, I would like you to modify
the contract that I wrote as follows.
Charlie should put down a deposit
in the very beginning of twice the
deposit that Alice and Bob put down.
And if he then doesn't choose
when it's his turn to choose.
Alice and Bob get half of 40 put down.
So, Alice and Bob each end
up with 20 in this example.
So in the very beginning,
Charlie supposed to put down 20.
And then it proceeds as usual.
So if all goes well, Alice and Bob, both put down
10 and Charlie makes his choice, for example,
for Alice, then as before Alice gets the 20
and Charlie gets his originally deposit back.
But if Charlie does not make a choice
and the deadline is reached, then
his 20 split amongst Alice and Bob
so Alice and Bob both end up with 20.