In today's lecture, I want to look at a
case study to see how what we've learned so
far can be turned into an actual application,
a complete executable or several executables
that even come with a little front-end.
And it will be a fully fledged Dapp
apart for the fact that we don't
have a real blockchain available yet.
So this will run on a simulated
blockchain, a so-called mockchain, but
apart from that, it will contain all
the pieces that you will also need for
real application as soon as Plutus is
available on the Cardano main chain.
And the example I've chosen for
that is the example of oracle
s.
So I want to show how to
implement a very simple oracle.
Now for this an oracle, an oracle in the
blockchain world is a service or a way to get
real world information onto the blockchain
and make it usable in smart contracts.
And there are numerous
examples of use cases for that.
So you can think of external data
sources like weather data, or election
results, or stock exchange rates,
or maybe randomness for games or
lotteries, or simply time, temperatures,
water levels, all sorts of things.
And often information like that is useful
or needed for real world smart contract.
For example, you could have a betting
smart contract that depends on the
outcome of a specific sports game.
And in order for the contract logic to
decide who wins the bet, you of course
need the information from the real world
who actually won that game, or maybe you
want some trading contract that takes real
world stock exchange data into account.
And there are various ways to implement
oracles of various sophistication.
And I want to choose a very simple
approach where we have one trusted data
provider that provides one feed of data.
And as an example for data, I want to
use the exchange rate from ADA to USD
And of course there are lots of problems
with this approach because you have to
trust that source, this data source.
And there are also ways to mitigate that
risk, the risk that this data sources either
untrustworthy or unreliable, maybe reports
wrong data, or for various reasons technical
issues or whatever fails to provide any data.
So for example, you could make the trusted
party to put down some collateral, and then
have some sort of mechanism that if the
provider fails to deliver or reports false
data or doesn't report data, he loses this
collateral, or you could combine several
such oracles into one, like only except the
value, if all these various sources agree
or only take like the median or the average
value of these different sources, or you can
think of much more sophisticated mechanisms.
But for this example, I think it's
enough to take the simple most case,
there we have one data provider that we
trust, and that is willing to provide
this real time data to the blockchain.
And as we know for anything to happen
on the blockchain, there must be a UTxO.
So the obvious idea is to represent this
data feed, the present, the current value
of the data feed, the oracle data as a UTxO.
That UTxO sits at the script address
of the oracle and in its data field,
it carries the value, the current
value of the provided oracle data.
So in this example, the datum
would carry the value 1.75.
And this is where we encounter our first
problem, because if I have said many times
in this lecture, validation only happens when
you want to consume something from a script
address, not when you produce an output at
a script address, which means that we can't
prevent anybody from producing arbitrary
outputs at the same oracle script address.
So we somehow need to way to distinguish
the true UTxO oracle output from other
output sitting at the same script address.
Luckily we learned about
NFTs in the last lecture.
And the point about NFTs, if you recall,
is that an NFT can only exist exactly once.
So there's only ever one coin of a given NFT.
So the idea to make the correct
oracle script output unique is
to give it an NFT in its value.
So not only have it carry the
data, the actual oracle value, but
also put an NFT at that output.
And because an NFT can only exist once
they can only be one output at the
oracle address that holds that NFT.
And that allows us to uniquely
identify the correct UTxO that
carries the correct oracle value.
How can such an oracle be used?
And here we come to something we haven't
seen before in all our previous examples,
when we designed validators and contracts,
we always knew the full API upfront.
So we always knew exactly how we intend
to use our smart contracts, in the case
of an oracle this is different, because at
the moment when the oracle gets created,
you don't know how people might want to
use the data feed provided by the oracle.
So in that sense, it's like an open API.
The oracle must be able to work
together with smart contracts that
haven't even been written at the
time when the oracle is created.
So as an example, for use case that
might make use of this specific oracle
let's consider a swap contract where
at the swap address, somebody can
deposit ADA and then somebody else can
take those ADA in exchange for USD.
Of course, we don't have USD directly
on the blockchain, but let's just assume
they're represented by some native token...
some USD native token.
So we have this swap contract and somebody
can make a swap by exchanging the ADA in
the contract for the USD Token And the idea
is to make use of the oracle by determining
the exchange rate by the oracle value.
So in this example, because the
current value of the oracle is 1.75.
If somebody offers 100 ADA in the swap,
the price for that should be 175 USD.
In addition to that, we also
need an incentive for the oracle
to actually provide the data.
Because if nothing else, the oracle
provider has to pay transaction
fees to actually create this UTxO.
So let's say that the oracle provider
determines a fee that has to be
paid each time the oracle is used.
So for example, let's say the fee is one ADA.
So each time, the oracle value
is used in a transaction, the
user has to provide one ADA fee.
So this means if in the swap example,
the buyer wants to buy the 100 ADA.
He would need to pay 175 USD to the seller of
the ADA and one ADA to the oracle provider.
So what will the swap transaction look like?
First of all, the swap validation logic
will need access to the current oracle
value, which means that the oracle UTxO
must be an input to the transaction,
so the swap validator has access to it.
Then we have the oracle validation logic,
and in this case, we want to use the oracle,
so let's say we have a redeemer called use.
And now the oracle validator
has to check several things.
First of all, it has to check that the
NFT is present in the consumed input to
make sure that the correct UTxO is used.
Secondly, it has to make sure
that there's also an output of the
transaction at the same oracle address.
Again, containing the NFT and
with the same value by using the
oracle, by using the oracle value,
we don't want to change the value.
We just want to use it.
So the oracle validator must make sure
that when this oracle UTxO is consumed
to use it in an arbitrary transaction,
like the swap transaction, the value is
not changed, the datum is not changed.
Finally, the oracle provider wants to
get paid, so it must make sure that
in addition to the NFT that identifies
the UTxO, the fee must also be paid.
So we have this picture that the transaction
that makes use of the oracle consumes the
current UTxO, the current oracle UTxO,
makes sure the NFT is there and produces
an output again to the oracle address and
make sure the NFT is again there, the fees
are there and the datum has not changed.
And now we can complete the transaction.
So, both the swap output and the price
paid by the buyer are consumed as
additional inputs to the swap transaction.
And we have two more outputs, the USD
that go to the seller and the ADA that
go to the buyer and that all of this is
correct and has the correct values as
the responsibility of the swap validator.
So the swap validator will make sure that
the buyer pays the correct price to the
seller whereas the oracle validator is only
interested in making sure that everything
concerning the oracle is correct, so that
we have this one oracle output consumed
which is identified by the NFT and we have a
continuing output to the oracle address again
with the correct value and the correct datum.
So this is a complete example of how
an existing oracle would be used.
And just to emphasize, once again,
this swap contract is just an example.
The oracle should be capable of working with
many different smart contracts that want to
make use of the data provided by the oracle.
Now, if that was all, then we wouldn't need
an oracle because if this one value was
fixed and it was always 1.75, then we could
simply hardcode this into our contracts.
So obviously, the value of the oracle
must be able to change, at least
in the case of an oracle like this
one where we have an exchange rate
that of course can change over time.
There might be other oracles like the
before mentioned outcome of a sports match
where it's a singular event in history and
either the one side wins or the other wins.
But that will never change again, but in
example of a price oracle like this one,
of course it's important that the value
can change, which means that the oracle
validator, in addition to the use redeemer
must be able to support another operation
where the operator, the provider of the
oracle can actually change the data.
So let's say that the value changes
from 1.75 to 1.77, and the oracle
provider needs to update the oracle.
Of course, we know that on a UTxO blockchain
or [E] UTxO blockchain, nothing ever changes.
So UTxOs can't change, you can't change
the datum of an existing UTxO, all you can
do is consume UTxOs and produce new ones.
So in order to update the value, we have to
consume the existing oracle UTxO and produce
a new one that carries the correct datum.
So we would have a transaction that
uses an update redeemer and now the
validation logic is somewhat different.
It's the same as before in that the
NFT needs to be present in the consumed
oracle input and also needs to be present
in the produced new oracle output.
In addition to that, that transaction
must be signed by the oracle provider.
So not anybody can change the value
only the provider of the oracle.
And we can use this update transaction
as an opportunity to allow the
oracle provider to collect the fees.
So we only insist that the NFT must
be present in the output, but we
don't say anything about other values.
So all the accumulated fees that
got there from other contracts using
the oracle, can be collected by the
oracle provider in this transaction.
So to sum up, we represent the
oracle as a UTxO and we identify
the correct UTxO by a specific NFT.
And the oracle value is
the datum of that UTxO.
And we support two operations, one
is use, which uses oracle in some
arbitrary transaction and the validator.
In the use case will make sure that the
consumed oracle input carries the NFT
and that there is an oracle output that
again carries the NFT, doesn't change
the datum and carries additional fees.
The second operation is update, which can
only be done by the oracle provider and for
an update transaction, again, the input, the
oracle input must carry the NFT, there must
be an oracle output, also carrying the NFT.
And otherwise there are no restrictions,
so the datum can change and the
accumulated fees can be taken out.
So now that we know how it is supposed
to work, let's look at some code.
And I know in the past lectures, I always
basically in live coded everything,
but this time it's quite a lot of code.
So I hope you all forgive me for having it
prepared and I just walk you through it.
So as always, you can find the
code in our GitHub repository.
So let's first look at the code, the Plutus
code that implements the oracle itself.
So I put that into a module
week six oracle core.
Right, so first of all, the oracle
will be a parameterized contract.
And this data type that I
called oracle is the parameter.
And it will depend on four fields, so
this is a record type with four fields.
First, the o symbol is the
currency symbol of the NFT.
So the NFT that will always be carried around
with the oracle UTxO to uniquely identified.
I don't need the token name because I
will use the empty string as a token name.
Second, the o operator, that's
the owner of the oracle, that's
the one that can make updates.
We saw, just now that the use operation
is supposed to be used by anybody,
but the update operation where the
datum actually changes can only be
done by the operator and that public
key hash here identifies the operator.
Then the fee is the fees in lovelace that
are due each time somebody uses the oracle,
this fourth field o asset identifies
the target of the oracle, basically.
So in this running example, we're talking
about exchange rates, ADA to something
else, and this denotes the something else.
So in our example, this would be an asset
class representing some sort of USD token.
So we do the usual boiler plate the type
classes we need for it to be serializable.
And liftable, and now we define the redeemer
and as we already saw in the diagrams I want
to support two operations, update and use.
So I just define in a new data type
that I called oracle redeemer that just
has these two values, update and use.
And I implement, I mean, use template Haskell
to implement is data for that redeemer type.
Then just some helper definitions,
so as I said, I want to use the empty
string as a token name for my NFT.
So this is this oracle token name,
and this is just a way to identify
the NFT asset class, given an oracle.
So this is not to be confused,
maybe the name is not good.
This oracle asset is not to
be confused with the o asset.
So remember the o asset is USD token
in our case whereas the oracle asset
will be the asset of the NFT that is
used to identify uniquely identify
the UTxO with the oracle value.
So it's just a simple method of
extracting the symbol from the oracle
and then using this fixed token
name which is just empty string.
The next function here, oracle value is
a little helper function that given a Tx
out and a way to turn a datum hash into
a maybe datum returns and maybe integer.
So the Tx out in question will be the
output of the UTxO that holds the oracle.
And then we want to some a lookup the datum
of that oracle and turn it into an integer.
Why integer?
In the example, when I showed you
the diagrams we used rational values,
or real values or double values for
the exchange rates, 1.75 or 1.77.
There is a ratio type of rational
numbers in Plutus, but that has some
issues that I think it's not, it
doesn't implement to json and from json.
So I've felt it was easier to just
use integer for the oracle values.
So basically I just take the true
exchange rate and multiply it
one by 1,000,000 and then round.
So, an exchange rate of 1.75 would cause
point to the integer value 1,750,000.
Right, and...
so we will see later how this helper function
is used, but it's quite interesting example
of using monadic computation in a monad
that's not IO or for example, contract.
So in this case, it's the maybe monad.
So this do block here, these monadic
operations are happen in the maybe monad.
So that means the bind captures the
fact that this could go wrong and
we could get a nothing, in which
case the overall result is nothing.
So it's just three steps.
First we take our Tx out and try to get
the Tx out datum which can fail because
not any output has a datum, it could be a
public key output that doesn't have a datum.
And if it succeeds, we get a
datum hash, so that's this DH.
Next, we use this provided function
F the second argument to maybe
turn this datum hash into a datum.
So this can again fail.
but If it succeeds, then we get
the datum D, datum is just a
newtype wrap around built-in data.
so then we can use Plutus Tx
dot from built-in data to maybe
turn this D into an integer.
So of course there could be a problem
that the datum is there, but it's
not needed at some other data type
in which case this would fail.
So we have to do these three
steps and each of them can fail.
And this is a nice application of the
maybe monad by using this no monadic
computation, this monadic notation
makes it much nicer to write down.
And as I said, we'll see in a bit
where we use this helper function.
So this is now the most important
function, the make oracle validator.
So it gets the parameter,
which was our data type oracle.
Then it gets the datum, which as I
just explained is integer in our case,
then it gets the redeemer represented
by the data type oracle redeemer.
And finally the contracts and returns a
boolean, whether you should validate or not.
And I mean, we do have two cases for use and
for update, but there are some similarities
between them as we saw in the diagrams,
because in both cases, we want to check
that we have the input that holds the NFT.
And there is an output
that again holds the NFT.
So those two checks I can do for both cases
simultaneously that's why I do them upfront.
So this first checks that the input
and validating holds the NFT and that
second condition checks that there is an
oracle output that also holds the NFT.
And then I distinguish the two cases
that I mean, the update or the use case.
So let's first look at input has token.
So first before I get to that, I have
two more helper definitions here.
So info that you saw before, just take
the context and extract the transaction
info from it and own input, this is the
output that I'm just trying to consume.
So validation is running as you know,
whenever I try to consume a script input.
So in this case I try to own script output.
In this case, I try to consume the
oracle output and this Tx out is
supposed to be that, oracle output.
And there is a this function that's provided
by the Plutus library, find own input,
which given the context gives me that input.
But that case a maybe because I might be
in a situation where I'm not validating
input, I might be in the monetary policy
context, for example, in which case
there's no input, that is being validated.
So there's nothing case should not
really happen because we know we are
validating the consumption of the oracle.
But in any case, if there nothing happens,
I just say that it's no input, but we
should never end up there and if you have an
input, then it's of type Tx in or Tx input.
And then I can use this Tx in info resolve
to get the corresponding out, Tx out.
So this own input is now the output,
the oracle output I'm trying to consume.
So now I must check that the token is present
and there's in the ledger dot value module,
there is a asset class value o function
that takes a value, an asset class, and
then returns and integer, how many coins of
that as a class are contained in the value.
So as value I use Tx out
value of my own input.
So that's the value attached
to this input I'm consuming.
And as asset class, I just use this
helper function oracle asset oracle.
So that gives me the NFT
belonging to the oracle.
So I check how often is the NFT contained
in the value of the oracle output
and it should be there exactly once.
I mean, because it's an NFT, it can
never be more than one, but it could be
missing in which case it would be zero.
So I must make sure that it is actually
there, so I check whether it's one.
Next helper function on output, as we
know, in both cases use and update, I
want exactly one oracle output again.
So I first want to find that.
There's another function defined in the
libraries called get continuing outputs that
gets the context and it returns a list of
all the outputs that go to the same script
address that I'm presently validating.
So right now we are in the context
of validating the oracle, the
consummation of the oracle output.
So this get continuing outputs would give
me all the outputs of the transaction,
that again go to the oracle address.
And I want it to be exactly
one, one oracle output.
So if this get continuing outputs
results in a list with one
element, I return this one element.
And if it's zero or more outputs going to
the oracle address, I produce an error and
say I expected exactly one oracle output.
Now I can use this very similar
to input has token, I can now
check where the output has token.
So that's basically exactly the
same, except that earlier the
value was from the own input.
And now I take the value from the own output.
And again, check that this NFT,
which is given by oracle asset
oracle is contained exactly once.
So this now checks that my oracle
input carries the NFT and this checks
that my oracle output carries the NFT.
So this covers these first two lines
here, which are common for both cases,
for the use and for the update case.
And now I make a case distinction whether
I'm in the update or in the use case.
So let's look at the update case first,
which was the second one in the diagram.
And there are two conditions we must check.
We must check that the operator
actually sign the transaction this is so
simple to check that I did it in line.
So I didn't write a specific helper function
for that, I just use this Tx signed by
that we have seen before, it takes the
info and it takes the signature we want.
And remember we know the operator from
the field in our parameter in the oracle
parameter, so o operator oracle gives
us this public key hash of the operator.
And we check here that the
transaction in the update case is
actually signed by the operator.
And the second condition we want to
check is that it again carries validator.
So as you know, in update, it can, I
mean, the exchange rate in the datum
can arbitrarily change, but it should
still be of the right type at least.
So in our case, it should
still be an integer.
So I checked it here using first
the helper function output datum,
which gives me a maybe integer.
And I just use this helper function
we discussed earlier oracle value,
which now takes my own output.
So I'm interested in the new
value, not in the old value.
I mean the old value I have given here
as parameter to my validator, any way,
that's the second argument, the X so
X is the old oracle value, but now I'm
interested in the new oracle value, in
the datum attached to the oracle output.
So I use my helper function oracle
value apply to this oracle output.
And remember there was a second argument
that given a datum hash gives me a
datum or tries to give me a datum.
So it gives, it's a function
type datum hash to maybe datum.
And there is one called find
datum that takes the info.
So, find datum takes info and
the datum hash and then tries to
lookup the corresponding datum.
So this has exactly the right type and
that will give me just the new oracle
value in case it succeeds and if something
goes wrong, it will give me nothing.
And now to check that it's valid.
I mean, I don't say anything
about the value of the integer.
All I care about is that it's not nothing.
So it's some integer.
So here in the valid output datum,
I just take this output datum, which
is maybe integer and check that
it's not nothing, that it's a just.
And there is a function in the prelude
called is just that does just that.
So is just will be true if it's a just
and will be false if it's a nothing.
So this is the second condition I check here.
So all I check is that the operator has
signed the transaction and that again,
I have a valid integer output datum.
In particular, I don't check anything
about the value apart from the
fact that it must carry the NFT.
So that means that this allows the operator
in this transaction to retrieve the
fees that have accumulated in the value.
I only check that the NFT is there, I don't
check that any other value that was on the
input site is still there on the output side.
So that allows the operator to get his fees.
Now the second case, is the use case,
which can be used by anybody as we saw,
but it is much more restrictive because
we don't allow the datum to change.
So when you use the oracle you
don't change the value of the
oracle, this is the first condition.
You already have this helper function
output datum which is maybe integer,
that's the new value of the oracle.
And I just check that it's just X,
remember X was the old value of the oracle.
So I'll just make sure that
the datum hasn't changed.
And finally, I must check
that the fees have been paid.
So remember when you use the
oracle, you're supposed to pay fees.
So this is the final helper function here.
So I just lookup the value that
was attached to the oracle input,
using Tx out value of our own input.
I check the value that's
attached to the own output.
And now I know that the output should be at
least as large as the input plus the fees.
So this is exactly what it says, output
value should be greater or equal, then
the input value plus, remember we can
use the semi-group operation to combine
values, plus and this is the fees.
So remember the all fee field in the
oracle parameter was just an integer.
And I said, that's the fee in lovelace.
So I use the ADA dot lovelace value of
function to turn this integer into a lovelace
value, add it to the existing input value.
And then I say that the old value
should be greater or equal than this.
I could of course also have said equal
and that would also be correct by writing
greater than equal, I basically allow users
of the oracle to give the operator a tip.
If they are very happy with the
oracle, they can give more than
just the fee, they can pay more.
I mean that's just a matter of
taste I could have written equal.
And...
also recall that, I mean, in the
example, on the input side, there
was just the NFT in the value.
And then the output side, there
was the NFT and one ADA fee.
And then in the next step, there
was an update, so the operator
collected that fee immediately.
But this is now designed in a
way that the operator doesn't
have to collect all the time.
So there can be several uses where
fees accumulate over time and then
with the next update, the operator
can collect all of them in one go.
Okay, this is basically the core
business logic of the oracle.
This is now in code what I tried to
explain earlier when I showed the diagrams.
And now it's just the usual boiler plate,
so I have this helper type Oracling where I
just combine the redeemer and the datum type.
So I say the datum type is integer,
the redeemer type is oracle redeemer.
Then I do the usual template Haskell
stuff to compile it to type validator,
and because it's parameterized, I do
what we always do with parameterized.
So I have to use this apply code and
lift the parameter into Plutus script.
So now we have the type validator and
then we can use the usual boiler plate
here, or to turn it into a validator and
to turn the validator into an address.
So now we have our script oracle
address, and that concludes the
on-chain part of the oracle code.
Now, I also provide some off-chain
part, namely to actually start an
oracle and to update it, not to use
it, because how it is used exactly?
Depends on who wants to
use it in which context.
So we, on the diagram, we had this swap
example, but they can many other example,
I called it an old maybe IO earlier.
So to create a valid transaction
that actually makes use of
the update, of the update.
No, not the update of the use redeemer,
is not the responsibility of the
author of this oracle contract.
Whoever wants to use the oracle, we'll
make sure to create a transaction
that actually invokes this.
So this is the first time we see something
like that, where we have some on-chain
code that is basically not mirrored
or reflected in the off-chain code.
So here we only do what is the
responsible of the oracle provider.
Right.
So the...
as I said two, two operations.
Start the oracle and update it and to start
it, we need parameters, the fees that we want
to charge, the currency symbol and the token
name, this is now the currency symbol and
the token name of the asset we want to check.
So USD token in our case, not the NFT,
because at this point we don't know the
NFT, we will actually mint the NFT in
this start oracle contract function.
And that's actually all we
will do, so we won't provide an
initial value for the oracle yet.
All we want to do in the start,
oracle function is mint the NFT.
Reason for that is that this minting
of the NFT can take a couple of slots.
So if you already provided the initial
datum data for the exchange rate that
might be outdated by the time we are ready.
So therefore I decided to not do
that here, so that will be handled
in the update oracle function.
So all this does is mint an NFT.
And I could of course have used the code we
developed in the last lecture, our NFT code,
that would have been perfectly fine, but I
decided to instead use one of the provided
use cases from the Plutus minus use minus
cases package in the Plutus repository.
And there's a currency module that provides
a mint contract function and that can be used
to mint NFTs, actually, it's more general.
If we check in the repl for the type of mint
contract, we see it takes a pub key hash.
That is the pub key hash of the entity
that will end up with the minted coins.
So we will just use our own, the
wallets own pub key hash there.
And then we see it takes a list of
pairs of token names and integers.
So, this mint contract will create a currency
symbol, which will depend on a unique UTxO,
the same trick we used in the last lecture.
But it allows you to specify not
just one token name and then making
NFT with it, but several token names
with arbitrary integer amounts.
So you can mint several coins with different
token names and also different amounts,
but they all will have the same currency
symbol, and it will be guaranteed that there
can only be one such minting transaction.
There's one slight problem, if we want
to use this, and that is the error type.
We want a contract where
we use text error messages.
But this contract here is polymorphic
in the error type, provided the error
type implements this as currency error
class, and unfortunately text doesn't.
So we can't use text here for E, so we
can specialize this function for text.
That means we can't directly use
it in our contract because then
we would get an error that takes
doesn't implement as currency error.
Luckily, there's a function called
map error, let's look at this.
That has this signature and this allows
us to change a contract with error type
E into a contract of error type E prime
provided, I can turn E into an E prime.
So if I can turn error messages of the one
type into error messages of the other type,
then I can turn a contract using the first
type of error messages into the contract
using the second type of error message.
So that's what I'm using and actually
one type that's provided in the currency
module is called currency error.
So we see this actually
implements currency error.
So this class that we need, so
this is a type we can actually use.
And it also implements show.
So, by first using show to turn a currency
error into a string, and then using pack
from data dot text, which turn string into
a text, we can turn a currency error into
a text, and then using map error with this
combination of pack and show, we can turn
a contract that has currency error error
messages into a contract that has text
error messages, which is what we need.
So that's what I'm doing here, so I use map
error pack after show, and then use this mint
contract function from the currency module.
And as list of tokens, I don't want several
tokens with the amounts, I just want an NFT.
So I just have one pair in this list
oracle token name, recall that's just
a empty string with the amount one.
So this will just mint NFT.
I have to specify the type here
because otherwise the compiler wouldn't
know which type to apply show to.
So I have to specify that I'm specializing
this mean contract to currency error.
And then I use map error to turn
that with show and pack into a text.
So now this has the right
type, I can use it here.
And I get this weird one short currency.
And that is a specific type,
specific to the currency module.
But I don't really care what that is, all
I care about is that there is a function
in that same module called currency
symbol that takes such a one short
currency and gives me a currency symbol.
And all I need is the currency
symbol of the NFT that I just minted.
Once I have that, I can
fill in my oracle type.
So the only information that was missing was
this currency symbol, so this is now here.
As operator, I take myself, my own
public key hash, which I looked up here
in the first line and the fees I just
take from the parameters and the asset
class I also take from the parameters.
I suppose I could have used asset class
here as well, instead of having two
fields symbol and token I could just
have, had one field of type asset class.
But that doesn't play so nicely with the
UI and if you want to try the playground I
felt it was easier to use these two separate
fields and then combine them like so.
So this now gives us our oracle and
we have minted the NFT and I just
log a message and return the oracle.
So the return type here of this
function is of type oracle.
Okay, and the second function is more
complicated, is the update oracle.
And this has to deal with two cases, the case
that we already have an oracle value that we
want to update, that's like in the diagrams.
And also the case that we just started
the oracle and there is no UTxO yet, so we
want to create one for the very first time.
Anyway, so it takes as parameters the
oracle, some oracle, the oracle parameter.
And integer is the new value, so
the value, the oracle value, we
want to update, the oracle two.
So first we use this helper function find
oracle oracle, which is defined here.
So that takes an oracle and it's supposed
to lookup the existing oracle UTxO, this can
fail because the oracle might not be there.
So if you have just started it, remember
we just minted the NFT, we didn't
create an output at the oracle address
yet, so in that case we won't find it.
But if it find it, we return a just
and then the triple is the Tx out
ref which if you recall from last
time, it's basically identify often
UTxO, then the Tx out Tx that's the
UTxO itself containing all the data.
And the integer is the current exchange rate.
This is of course encoded here in this Tx out
Tx, but to make it easier to work with the
extract that here in this helper function.
And how do we do that?
So first we use UTxO at that we
already know to get all the UTxOs
sitting at the oracle address.
So this is now a map from Tx
out ref to Tx out Txs, all the
UTxOs sitting at this address.
But remember, if you find more than
one, then most of them will be wrong.
I mean, we want the one
that contains the NFT.
So we filter this map, this map dot
filter comes from the data dot map
module, the standard container library
in Haskell, and it takes a function
of type the values in the map to bool.
And it will only keep those entries in the
map for which this function returns true.
And here, we now want to
check that the NFT is there.
So given such an UTxO, we do similar
to what we did to invalidation.
So we check the value of that UTxO and
check how often our NFT is contained in it.
And it must be there exactly once.
So we will end up with a map
that has either zero elements.
If the oracle UTxO is not or
one can be more than one because
this NFT can only be there once.
Right, and now we distinguish the two cases.
So the good case is that we find exactly
one element, so we convert the map
into a list of pairs of key value pairs
with the standard map to list function.
And there are two cases that we
find exactly one element or not.
Actually, the second case can only
be that we don't find anything.
As I said before, we can't find more
than one because it's an NFT, but
Haskell of course doesn't know that.
So to keep the compiler API don't
say just empty list here just use
the underscore, so all other cases.
Anyway, so if you find exactly one key value
pair, then in order to return this tripled.
So we now have the, the Tx out ref
and the Tx out now we need this
integer and that could still go wrong.
So even though we have the UTxO with
the NFT, there could be some corrupt
data in it for whatever reason.
So now I use this helper function again,
that I explained right in the beginning
that we also used in validation that gets
the Tx out, which I can get from my all
from my Tx out Tx by using Tx out, Tx out.
And remember the second argument was a
function that given a datum hash gives
me the corresponding datum, if it can.
And the way we can do this here
in off-chain code is we use the Tx
data field of the Tx out Tx, Tx o.
So the Tx out Tx, Tx o gives us the
transaction and that has a Tx data field.
And the Tx data field is just a
map from datum hashes to datums.
So we can use map lookup to lookup a
given hash and we can find it or not.
If not, it returns nothing.
If we find it, it returns
the value, the datum.
So using this helper function now, if that
succeeds, X would be the actual datum which
is an integer in our case, as we know.
So in this case we return this triple.
Now we just found out the X, if this
goes wrong, then it will be nothing.
And if we find, we don't find the
UTxO at all, it will also be nothing.
So this is find oracle.
So we tried to find it, and this is just
a helper definition because I need that
in both cases, this constraint, maybe
we can come back to that in a second.
So logically, so after we have tried
to find the UTxO, there are two cases
that we found it or not, if it didn't
find it, we just started the oracle, but
haven't provided an initial value yet.
So this is the first case.
And in this case, all we have to
do is we must create a transaction
that produces this output, the
first output at the oracle address.
So and this is you only need one
constraint and that is the C.
And I extracted that into this its own line
because I need, need the same constraint
later in the second case here as well.
So I didn't want to duplicate my work.
So I use constraints must pay to the
script so that as the name suggests
provides a way to say the the transaction
I'm constructing must have an output
that pays to a script address.
And the arguments are the datum, the
value I want to attach to that output.
And that's it, because which script
is then a specified here in the second
argument of submit Tx constraints.
So these script means the
script I'm looking at right now.
So all these functions, these
constraints functions always
have like one script in focus.
So in our case, it's the oracle script.
There's also a variant it's
called must pay to other script.
In which case I could pay to
an arbitrary other script.
And actually we used it down here
so I can talk about that there.
So anyway, so the datum is X because
this was one of the parameters, the
value we want to set the UTxO to the
oracle and the, I mean the datum and
the value is we want to attach our NFT.
So added class value, the
asset class of our NFT and one.
So we want to attach the NFT.
So this is all we have to do in that
case, that the UTxO isn't there yet.
So we just submit, wait for
confirmation and log a message that
we set the initial oracle value to X.
Now, in the other case so we
already have an oracle UTxO.
We don't care about the old datum
because we want to update it anyway.
So I can just use let's go here.
So now it's a bit more complicated.
So now, because now I need two conditions
again, the C it's the same as before.
So I want to create an output at the oracle
address with the new value, the value X.
But now I need the additional constraint
that I also must consume the existing UTxO.
And this is this constraint here so,
must spend script output is basically
the opposite of must pay to the script.
So, must pay to the script creates an
output and must spend script output
creates an input to the script address.
And as parameters it takes the reference
to the output, the UTxO we want to consume,
that's what we call oref here that we
looked up earlier and it takes the redeemer.
And in this case, it's an update, not
a use, and we just have to convert it
to data first and then to a redeemer.
And in order for this to work, we
need to provide a couple of lookups.
So, first of all, in order to find this
output that wants to spend, we must use
the unspent outputs lookup, which gets a
map of the UTxOs that we want to consume.
In this case, we can use map singleton to
construct this map, which will create a map
that contains exactly one key value pair.
So map singleton takes a key and
the value as arguments and creates
a map with one key value pair.
So we just put this one UTxO into this
map because there's nothing else we
want to consume, so all we need is this.
And then we must provide
the script instances.
And basically we have to do it
twice, once for the input side
and one for the output side.
Because, right...
so we give the oracle instance in the
lookups and we give the oracle validator
in the lookups and I always forget which
we need for what, but anyway, so one is
for two to be able to consume the input.
And the other one is to be
able to pay to the output.
And we didn't need that here because in
the first case, because we provided the
instance here in the submit Tx constraints,
a function, but now we have to use,
submit Tx constraints with, because we
have lookups and that doesn't have this
parameter where we can provide the instance.
So therefore we have to provide
the instance in the lookups itself.
So it's a bit confusing, but
you get used to it, I hope.
And we also have to give the
compiler and not yet to tell it
what script we are talking about.
Remember I said, all these
constraint functions are always
specific to a particular script.
And this basically signals what type
datum type redeemer type this script has.
So that was this weird Oracling type I
defined earlier, this helper type that
just says datum types is integer, redeemer
type is oracle redeemer, and we give the
lookups and these constraints, and then
hopefully get a balanced transaction that
we submit and we have wait for confirmation.
And we log that we updated,
the oracle value to X.
So again, the logic of update
oracle is first we check whether
the oracle is already in existence.
If it's not we create a transaction
that simply creates the first
UTxO with the oracle value.
So the oracle value is the datum and
we attach the NFT and if it already
exists, we create a transaction that
consumes the existing one and creates
a new one with the updated datum.
And again, containing the NFT and note that I
said something about fee collection earlier,
and this will happen automatically here.
So the way this balancing work, so
say that this UTxO the existing one
already contains fees, not just the NFT.
So in the constraints, we just say that
we want to consume the existing one.
And before one, one to provide
a new one that contents the NFT.
So if the existing one already contains
fees and we say that in the new one, we only
want the NFT and we have imbalance right?
On the input side, we have the
fees and the output side we haven't
specified anything about that.
And then what this balancing
algorithm by default always does,
is it pays that to our own wallet.
So if there is such imbalance, so if
this already contains fees, then it will
automatically here in this line, when
it constructs the actual transaction,
create an output that goes to our
wallet and constraints the difference.
So the fee the, the fees, and also
it will automatically create an input
to pay the transaction fees with.
So even though we only specify two things
here, the script, the oracle script
input and the oracle script output.
We might end up or we will probably end
up with a transaction with two inputs and
two outputs, one additional input coming
from our wallet to pay the transaction
fees and one additional output going to
our wallet, giving us the oracle fees that
use as of the oracle added to this UTxO.
And I think that's basically it.
Okay then.
So, this is basically the
bare bones that you need.
Now, I also for later provided a
function that combines this into these
two operations into one contract.
So, this is then for use, for example, in
the playground or in the emulator trace
monad also as we would see in the PAB.
So I define oracle schema, which
just contains one endpoint,
the update integer endpoint.
So all it does it, it takes
the new value as parameter.
And what does this run oracle do?
So first it uses our start oracle
function to actually start the oracle,
which remember doesn't do anything
oracle waits a just minds the NFT,
and gives us these oracle parameters.
Then for reasons that will become clear
later I use tell to write the oracle value.
So this parameter, and this is...
the reason is, I need to communicate
this parameter value to the outside
world so that people can use my oracle.
So, a time of writing, I don't yet
know what currency symbol is NFT value.
So I don't know the value of
this oracle parameter yet.
So I will only find that out at one time.
So once the oracle is actually started and
then other people that want to use my oracle
and need to know this parameter in order
to parameterize their contracts correctly.
So I have to communicate that out.
And the way to pass information
out of a contract is by using tell.
Now this last and just, remember
the tell expects monoid type.
So typical use from the write a monad is list
like list of strings that's when we talked
about monads I used that as an example.
So, each tell we take a list of strings
and then they will all be concatenated
to one big list of all log messages,
but it doesn't have to be list.
It can be other monoids and in data dot
monoid, we have this last monoid, so I
must import that from data dot monoid.
If we look for information, it's
just a newtype wrapper around maybe.
And the point of it is to change the
provider specific monoid instance.
And the idea is as the name suggests,
it's the monoid operation that
always remembers the last value.
So let's say I have last just
X and combine that with last
just Y, then I get last just Y.
So it forgets about the
X and remembers the Y.
But if the second one is a nothing,
it will remember the first one.
So basically what last the last monoid does
it always remembers the last just value.
If both are nothing, it will be nothing.
Okay.
Now it complaints, because it doesn't know
whether it's nothing into a character.
It assumes it's nothing unit, but anyway,
so it's a nothing, so last nothing and last
nothing is nothing, but if one of the two
is a just, it will remember the last just.
And this is very useful and it's
used all the time in these contracts
for the tell, because it basically
allows us to, to keep current state.
So it will...
the value of the log would
basically be the last just retold.
Actually in this contract
we will only do that once.
So after starting the oracle.
So in the beginning, it will
end up is nothing, last nothing.
So at the beginning will be last nothing.
And then we mint the NFTE we get our in
line 192, we get our oracle value and
then we tell it, and from that point
onward, it will always have that value.
So as soon as we have our NFT and
have oracle value with other contracts
from the outside query the state,
they will always get the just oracle.
So they will be able to
discover the value of oracle.
Okay and then...
so after I've started it, I just call
this helper function go with oracle as
parameter, and this will now loop forever.
And it all does is it will
block at this update endpoint.
And as soon as somebody provides an integer,
which is the new value, it will call our
update oracle function with this value.
And then just loop to go again.
So what is run oracle does is, it
starts the oracle, tells the oracle,
so that others can discover it.
And then forever just waits for new
values and updates the oracle accordingly.
So, that's the run oracle function.
And that concludes the
code for the oracle itself.
So that's the core oracle code,
both on-chain and off-chain.
So what's now missing is an example,
some contracts that actually
uses the oracle, a swap contract.
And then of course, using the
Plutus application backend
to actually run this code.
In the real world or at least in
our case, in a simulated blockchain.
Now let's look at an example contract that
I put into this module oracle dot swap.
And the idea is that it's a smart
contract where somebody couldn't
put ADA and then somebody else can
exchange those ADA for a token.
So in our example, we will use some
token that we call USDT for USD token.
The idea is the price, so the amount
of USDT tokens that the buyer has
to pay for the offered ADA will
be determined by the oracle value.
So that will change overtime depending on
the exchange rate encoded in that oracle.
And...
so the idea is that we use
lovelace and we also use this USD
token with the fact of 1,000,000.
So one dollar would cause point
to 1,000,000 of those tokens.
So I start with the helper function that
I called price, given amount of lovelace
and an exchange rate expressed as I said
before, it's an integer that where the
actual rational number is multiplied by
1,000,000, get the price of the token.
And I must just multiply the lovelace by
the exchange rate and divide by one million.
Second, just another helper function,
given a value, extract the amount of
lovelace in there, the called lovelaces
and that's just a combination of two
functions provided by the Plutus libraries.
First given a value I can get ADA
and then given the ADA value I can
get the number of lovelaces and then
I can provide this swap validator.
The idea is that it takes two parameters.
It's a contract with two parameters.
The oracle we are using that comes from
this other module that we discussed
before, which I'm importing here.
And I'm importing another module
that I called funds, we'll
can look at that in a moment.
And second parameter, the address.
This will be the address of the oracle.
So, normally I given the oracle.
I can compute the address from it
in the core module we saw a function
oracle address that takes oracle and
computes the script address from it.
But that is a function that I can't
use in the validator, because it uses
code that is not compatible, that
can't be compiled to Plutus script.
So I'll use a trick here and
explicitly hand in the address as well.
So when I actually call this validator,
later I will compute the address from
the oracle, but now I just give it
as a second parameter explicitly.
And for datum, we will use the pub key
hash which is the pub key hash of the
seller that will receive the prize.
And we don't use an interesting
redeemer so we can just use unit.
Okay, and...
if you recall from the diagram, so
such a swap transaction, should have
three inputs, so two script inputs.
The oracle to check the current exchange rate
and the swap output that holds the lovelace.
And then as a third input where the
funds are actually coming from the
buyer, and it should have three outputs.
The oracle output again, but we don't have
to worry about that because the oracle
validator takes care of that, that we
saw in the core module that the oracle
validator makes sure that whenever it is
used, there will be an output with unchanged
datum and added fees if you recall.
So, so we want that, and then the
seller must get the tokens and the
buyer should get the log lovelace.
And we want to support a second
use case, namely that the
seller can retrieve his assets.
Otherwise they could be potentially
locked be, locked there forever.
So there are basically two ways to unlock
the lovelace log by the script address.
One is if somebody actually does this swap,
gives tokens to the seller in exchange
for lovelace and the other is that the
seller himself retrieves the lovelace.
So, doesn't want to do this swap
anymore and gets his money back.
So this is the first condition,
so if the seller himself signs
the transaction, then it's fine.
There's no additional condition that doesn't
have to be an oracle involve to anything.
So if it's signed by the seller, he can
just get his hands back on the lovelace.
And the more interesting case is the
second one where we check two conditions.
First, we check that they are exactly
two script inputs because we only want
the oracle and we want the, this a swap
UTxO itself, the all additional inputs
to pay transaction fees and to actually
pay the price must be probably key inputs
because we don't want to worry about
interference with others smart contracts.
And secondly we want to check
that the seller gets paid.
So, I need define a couple of helper
functions to check this, so again we
define the info extracted from the context.
Then we find the oracle input and
we do that by taking all the inputs
that we get from the info field.
So this is a list of all inputs and I'm
using lists comprehension here, so that's
a nice way to construct lists in Haskell.
So it has the syntax with the square
brackets and then vertical bar.
And I can basically draw from other lists.
So this is, I is now basically looping
over all inputs of the transaction.
And I can have let expressions in
such a list comprehension as well.
So, I is an input and I compute the
corresponding output with Tx in info
resolved that we saw before, and I can
also put filters or conditions here.
So, if the condition is satisfied,
then this I will be kept and
otherwise it will be dropped.
So, in the conditioner check here is that
the address where this output sits at is
actually this error parameter, which as I
said before, will be the oracle address.
So this tells me get all inputs with
corresponding output O that sit at the
oracle address, and I keep all those Os.
And then I check that
there's exactly one of those.
So I make sure that there's
exactly one oracle input.
Otherwise I throw an exception.
So this now gives me the oracle
input or output, the oracle
input consumes the oracle output.
Now I want to check the actual
exchange rate, and I again.
I use this helper function that we
defined in the core module that given
the output where the oracle sits.
Computes me the actual exchange rate, the
datum, the integer datum and as before.
So I applied it to this oracle input that
I found in the previous helper function.
And again use find datum info to lookup
the datum to a hash, and this can fail.
In which case I didn't find an
oracle input or it can succeed
in which case I provide the X.
And I was just wondering, wether I forgot
to check that this oracle input actually
holds the NFT, but I don't need to
check that because seeing as there isn't
oracle input, we made sure of this here.
We know that because of how validation
works, the validation script for
the oracle input will also be run.
And if you recall, from the core module,
that script checks that the NFT is present.
So we don't have to do that here
in the validator for the swap.
Okay.
And now this check here
has two script inputs.
So we Loop over all inputs and
we filter with this function.
So this gives us the output to the input.
This gives us the address of that output.
This gives us the hash,
validator hash of this output.
If it's a script output or nothing,
if it's a public key output address.
And then it's just, we talked about
that before that is true if it's a
just in false, if it's a nothing.
And if filter by that, so the
XS is now all the script inputs.
And we check that the length of at
least is exactly two because we expect
two, the oracle and the swap itself.
So this is the first condition.
We check that there are exactly these two
script inputs, and now the second condition
is that the seller actually gets paid.
So this is the seller paid.
How do we do that?
So first, we compute the minimum
price that has to be paid.
So we check again with this find own input.
Remember that gives me the input
that is just being validated.
So it should be the swap input if
we don't find it, that's an error.
If we do find it, we again
compute the corresponding output.
Take the value and use our helper
function lovelaces to check
how many lovelaces are there.
So this is now this lovelace
in this, how many lovelaces are
locked in this swapped UTxO.
And then we use the price helper function
that we defined before given this amount
of lovelaces and the oracle value that
we looked up here to compute the price.
And then we can define
this seller paid condition.
So first we check how much he did pay.
And there's a helper function in the
Plutus library is called value paid
to given info and the public key hash.
It adds up all the values of
all the outputs, the public key
outputs that go to this address.
So this is now the total value that
is sent by this address to the seller
and we use this asset class value of
function to check the component of this
value that is the O asset of the oracle.
Remember that is the asset what that the
exchange rate of the oracle is actually for.
So in the USD example, this would give
us now the USD tokens that are sent
to the seller by this transaction.
And we just check that, the at least
as many as the min price dictates.
So we allow overpaying.
So if the buyer wants to be generous,
he can pay more tokens, but he must
pay at least this minimum price that's
determined by the exchange rate.
So this is all, that's our swap trans...
validator than the usual boiler plates.
So we define this swapping helper type
that records the datum and redeemer.
So again, datum is pub key hash,
the ha pub key of the seller.
No interesting redeemer.
Do the usual template Haskell
stuff to compile this given...
the oracle to a script and here received...
earlier we had two arguments, the
oracle and the oracle address.
Now we don't need this.
We just need the oracle.
Because as I said before, you can
compute the address from the oracle
using the oracle address function.
We just can't use that in Plutus
code, in code to code, in this
validator function itself.
But here we as expected get a way
with just one parameter, the oracle.
In case we now have the instance and if
we do the usual thing, get the validator,
get the address, and now we can come,
come start a couple of contracts.
So the first one offer
swap is for the seller.
If he wants to provide such a swap.
And that takes as parameter the
oracle and integer, that's the
amount of lovelace he wants to offer.
So we lookup his own public key.
And then as in the transaction, we want
a transaction that locks this amount
of lovelace in the swap contract.
So we only need one constraint, must
pay to the script that takes the datum,
which is our public key hash because
we as a seller and it takes the amount.
So lovelace value of the amount we
specified as argument to this function,
we submit and wait for confirmation
and log a message that we offered.
So-and-so many lovelace for swap.
Then a helper function that finds all
swaps that satisfy a specific predicate.
So given an oracle and the predicate
on pub key hashes, it gives us
a list of all the UTxOs that...
that sit at this swap address.
So again, the reference to the UTxO
the UTxO itself and the, this public
key hash is the datum of the UTxO.
So that's as follows, so we use
the UTxO at, at the address.
So that gives us all UTxOs
sitting at this swap address.
And then we use map maybe on the
list that we get from this map.
So this map, maybe we can check.
So if we import data dot
maybe ask for map maybe.
So this takes a function from A to maybe
B and a list of As and returns a list
of Bs and the way it works is it applies
this function to each A in this list.
So we will get a bunch of maybe Bs where
there can be just Bs and nothings, and
then it will throw away the nothings and
just keep the just and remove the just.
So as an example, we could, for example
F and Int, if, if you have an even
integer, then we return just div N two.
So we divided by two and if
it's an odd integer, nothing.
So that we...
okay, sorry...
I must activate that extension.
Okay.
So now I can try this also.
So if I try it on on even
number, I get just half of it.
And if I applied to an
odd number, I get nothing.
And now I can use map maybe in
combination with this F I just
define on the list of integers.
So for example, I don't
know 2, 4, 10, 11, 13, 100.
And I get now the list of the half of the
even numbers, but the odd ones are dropped.
So I get one and two, half of 2 and
4, and 10 is five, 11, and 13 are
dropped and I get half of 100 is 50.
So I want to use that to filter
my UTxOs here in the find swap.
So I Def I use this function
G and, but first I...
I I define another helper function F that
just takes one of the UTxOs I'm looking at.
And gives me a maybe pub key hash.
And what I do is I first
lookup the datum hash.
And again, this is a maybe monad.
So this two block is in the maybe monad.
So I lookup the datum hash attached to this
output that could fail that's a maybe datum
hash, but if it succeeds, so the hash, the
datum hash is DH, then in the Tx data field
of the transaction, I lookup this hash to
get to the datum, datum D, D of type data.
And finally, I try to deserialize it
basically from data to pub key hash.
So I expect of course that all the
swap UTxOs, the datum will be there
and it will be a public key hash.
So in this case I will get
just a public key hash.
Okay.
And now this G function
has now the right type.
So it takes a pair of key and
value on these UTxOs and returns a
maybe key value and pub key hash.
And what I do is, first I use my
first helper function to get the
public key hash if it's there.
So that's the datum now.
Then I apply this this predicate that
was argument here to my helper function.
And guard, we haven't seen that before.
So in some monads, including maybe
this guard is available and that takes
something of type boolean and what it
does is it fails if this boolean is...
if it's false, then this computation fails.
And if it's true it just continuous.
So that means I check whether this
predicate, whether the datum of
the UTxO satisfies my predicate.
And if it does not, then
this will return nothing.
So I've dropped this UTxO.
And if it is, then I return the triplet...
assisting of the reference, the UTxO
itself, and the datum included in it.
And we would see how we use
this find swaps in a bit.
So this helper function.
Right, the next contract I
define is this retrieve swaps.
So that's for the seller if he changes
his mind enforces swap, swap spec.
And so how does it work?
It just takes the owners public key hash.
Now it uses our helper function and
here as predicate, it checks that
it's the swaps that belong to himself.
So, remember the datum is the seller,
the public key hash of the seller.
So, I check that, I only take
those UTxO sitting at that
swap address that belong to me.
So this is now this Xs.
If there are none, then
there's nothing to retrieve.
So, if it's the empty list has nothing to do.
If it's not the empty list, I now construct
a transaction that retrieves all of those.
And how do I do that?
So, I take all the UTxOs in this
list and for each of them, I build a
constraint and say I want to spend that
UTxO, must spend script output, this
UTxO and as redeemer, just the unit.
So now I have a list of constraints
and M concat is a function that if
I have the list of elements in the
semi-group, it combines all of them.
So, I mean, normally we did that explicitly.
So we had, for example, two constraints
and we use this operator here to
combine them together to one constraint.
So now I have a list of constraints, I
don't know how many elements there are.
And with M concat, I can
combine all of them together.
So now I have this Tx is now the
constraint that all the UTxOs that
belong to me, sit at the swap address.
I want to consume in this one transaction.
I want to get all the lovelaces
from all those swaps back.
And as lookups for, for this to work, I must
provide all the UTxOs, but that's, I mean,
those I have, those are in this list XS.
So I just, I don't care about this hash.
I know it's mine anyway, this pub key hash.
So I have the oref and the O from all of
these, and I can use map from list to turn
this list of key value pairs into an action
map, and then apply this unspent outputs
constraint to it, to get me the lookup.
So now when I try to solve this constraint
and construct a transaction, I will
find all these UTxOs I want to consume.
And I must as before provide the
validator of the oracle actually, and
also not of the oracle of the swap
itself, it's parameterized by the oracle.
Because I must provide the, I must
include the validator script in
the transaction because I want
to consume those script outputs.
Okay.
And then I submitted...
I wait until it's confirmed.
And then I just say, how many
of these swaps I retrieved.
Okay, and the interesting one, is now this
one where actually make use of the oracle.
So this is I want to use as swap.
And, I mean, there can be several swaps in
that didn't want to make it too complicated.
So basically what I do is, I lookup
my own funds that's in this third
module I mentioned earlier that's why
I have to import the funds module.
You get to that in a second, but all
that does this own funds module this
own funds contract, it checks my own
wallet and adds up all the money I have.
So funds is now of type value, contains
all the funds I own, because I want to
check how much USD tokens or tokens I
have to actually pay for these swaps.
So I given all my funds, I check
how many of the tokens that we are
talking about in the oracle I have.
So that's not amount.
I just log that as
information how much I have.
This find oracle function comes from
the core module, we used it for some
of the oracle functionality before.
So it finds us the oracle, the UTxO
that contains the oracle and the value.
If you don't find the oracle.
Then we just log a message
that we didn't find it.
And if we do find it, so oref and
O reference the oracle UTxO and
X is the current exchange rate.
So we log a message that we found it.
We check our own public key.
We now look for all the available
swaps where we are not the owner.
So where the owner is not us.
Now we use a helper function find, that's in
the Haskell prelude, it's in data dot list.
So given a predicate on elements of
list, it finds us, maybe finds us one
that satisfies this prep, predicate.
And this is defined here and
we give it two parameters.
So the amount that we have, the assets
that we own and the current exchange rate.
So this predicate now takes the amount
we have, the current exchange rate,
and now it goes over the elements
of the swaps we found and the return
whether this is a suitable swap or not.
And all we do is we check that the price we
would have to pay for that specific swap is
at most as high as the tokens we own and this
get price function is to find above here.
So, given exchange rate and an output,
we just use our price helper function
and apply it to the lovelace is contained
in this swap and the exchange rate.
So what this line does is it tries to find
a swap that we can afford where given the
current exchange rate that oracle tells us
and the amount locked in this swap UTxO we
have enough assets to actually pay for it.
If you don't find such a swap, then we log
a message that we didn't find such a swap.
If we do find, find one,
we just take the first one.
I mean, that's not really realistic.
Of course, in, in a real world example...
would probably use, I mean,
specifying the exact amount how
much we want to swap or whatever.
I just wanted to keep it simply
because it doesn't matter.
I mean, we are talking about oracle.
It's not about the swapping,
it's just an example.
So I just pick a swap that I can afford.
And now I construct a transaction.
So this is the output for the oracle.
So that will be the existing
O value in the oracle.
So the O I remember is
the oracle we found here.
So this is the value that's already
in the oracle, which will be the
oracle NFT, and maybe some fees that
previous uses of the oracle paid.
And I just add my fee to that.
So this is now the output value.
Remember when I use the
oracle I have to add fees.
Okay.
And the P is the price
I have to pay actually.
So I take the lovelaces contained in
the swap and the exchange rate from the
oracle use my price helper function.
And this is just a number and integer,
how many of tokens I have to pay.
And I convert it into a value with
asset class value and this asset class.
Right, now let's look at the constraints.
The first constraint says we
must use the oracle as an input.
So this is the reference to the oracle
and as redeemer, we use the use redeemer.
So this is now the first time we actually use
the use redeemer, in the oracle code itself
we never used the dev, we only used the
update because the oracle provider is only
responsable for providing the oracle values.
The oracle provider doesn't
care about using it.
So now here in the swap contract,
we actually want to use it.
So that's the first constraint,
consume the oracle input.
Second constraint is consume the swap input.
So there is a trivial redeemer, and
this is the reference to the swap input.
Third constraint is we
want to pay to the oracle.
So the value we computed before.
So we, this is now this pay other script,
because now two scripts are in play,
the oracle script in the swap script.
So other script is now the oref script.
So we provide the oracle hash, as datum we
must use the existing datum, so we mustn't
change the exchange rate when we use it.
Only the operator of the oracle
can change the exchange rate
by using the update redeemer.
And the value is the one
we computed before the V.
So this was the existing value in the
oracle and the fee that we have to pay.
And last constraint is we must also
pay the seller of the lovelace and
that's the price we calculated.
And then we need these lookups
to actually make that work.
So we must provide the
validator of the swap contract.
We must provide the validator of the oracle
contract and we must provide the two UTxOs
we want to consume, the oracle and the swap.
And then the usual things.
So we submitted, we wait for
confirmation and we log a message
that we actually made a swap.
And just for information,
we log the price we paid.
Okay that's basically the raw
contract then that also provide like
a bundle that contains all of them.
So I define a schema blockchain
actions as always with four endpoints:
offer to offer a swap
for given amount of ADA,
retrieve to retrieve all my swaps,
use to actually do a swap and
funds just give me my
currently available funds.
Okay.
And how do I define that?
I use the select operator.
I'm not sure whether we have talked
about that before, so that allows,
it's basically a contract that wait.
I mean, if, if there are several
endpoints, it waits until one of those
is picked and then executes this one.
So this will offer simultaneously the
offer endpoint, the retrieve, the use and
the funds and whatever of these components
makes progress first will be executed.
So in, after I've done that I just sequence
with recursive fee calling myself again.
So over and over again, I will offer
these four endpoints and these four
endpoints are basically just rip us of
the contracts we defined before, except
that now I, I actually add an endpoint.
So for example, for offer, I know
block with the offer endpoint until
some body from the outside, provides
me with an amount in integer.
And then I call the offer swap oracle
amount contract that I defined before.
Same for retrieve, except
there is no parameters.
So I just block until somebody invokes the
retrieve endpoint and then call my previously
defined retrieve swaps contract, same for
use and funds is a little bit different.
Again, so this own funds comes from
the module we haven't looked at
yet the funds module, but what this
does is ignore the H for a second.
That's just an error handler which I...
by the way use everywhere.
So I must explain that anyway.
So this blocks until this endpoint
is invoked, then I call the own funds
function from the funds module, which
gives me the V, the value that I own.
And then I tell that.
So I log that value away.
So when somebody calls a funds
endpoint I log that to the state
and then it will be possible from
the outside to look at that state.
So that's a way to report back to
the outside, how much money I own.
And now for the H this
is just an error handler.
So it uses this handle error
function that we saw before.
And if there's an error,
I just log that error.
So I wrap all these into these error handlers
so if anything goes wrong in between.
I don't want the whole thing to crash.
I just log the error and then continue.
Okay.
And that concludes the swap
contract, the swap example.
Now let's quickly look at the funds
module, which just provides two contracts.
So it's a very short module.
And as I said before, it particularly has
this own funds function, whose goal it is
to sum up all the value in my own UTxO.
So how it works is just looks up my own
public key, then looks up the UTxOs at
the address given by my own public key.
So that's the UTxO sitting in my own wallet.
And then I get this map of UTxOs.
And now I apply to the values of this map.
So that's remember that's a map from
basically references to UTxOs to UTxOs.
So map also implements functor.
So I can basically map over the
values of this map, change the
values from UTxOs to something else.
So I first get the output belong
to the UTxO, then its value.
So now I have a map from
UTxO references to values.
The map elems function forgets
the keys and just gives me the
list of all values and M concat.
As I said before given a semi-group or monoid
combines a list of values of the type to one.
So what that does is it
just adds up all the values.
So V is now the sum of all the
values of all the UTxOs that I own.
And I just log that result and return it.
So this is a contract that has a as a
return value this value, and this here
is just a variation, which instead of
returning the value permanently tells it.
So what does it do?
It calls this own funds function and
then uses monadic binds, so result
of his own funds functions a value.
And then it tells just last that value.
So it writes the sum of money
that our own to the log.
And if there's some error there, I
handle it and just log the error.
Then I wait one slot and recourse.
So this own funds contract will run forever
and every slot check how much money I have.
And write that value into the log.
Let's look at the test module next,
which tests the contracts we have
written using the emulator trace monad.
In order to test it, I of course need
some assets that I can use to swap.
So I just make up an
arbitrary currency symbol.
So this FF, obviously it's not the hash
of some policy script, but same as in
the playground in the emulator trace
monads we can do that and as token name I
just pick USDT and this time in order to
actually run the trace that I'm writing,
I'm not using the run emulator trace IO
by the prime version, which takes two
more arguments to have more fine-great
control about the emulation environment.
So the first one would determine how exactly
the various log messages are displayed.
So by picking def I just choose the default.
So that's the same as in the unprime
version, but the reason I'm using this
extended version is because I want to
configure the initial distribution and I
can do so the so-called emulator config.
And what I specify is that everybody
has 100 million lovelace, so 100
ADA in the beginning, and everybody
has 100 of these USDT tokens.
So then I define a helper
contract check oracle.
So the idea is it just
supposed to permanently check
the oracle value and log it.
So I use the find oracle functions
that we have seen before the contract.
And if it's nothing, I just stop.
So this would stop if, if the oracle
is not there, but if I do find it with
value X, I just log the oracle value.
And then afterwards I wait
for one slot and recurse.
So if the oracle is not
there, this won't do anything.
I just wait for one slot.
If it's there I log the value
and do that permanently.
And now I can define my trace and
that's all things we have already seen.
So I just define some
parameters for the oracle.
So I just pick fees of one ADA,
100 sorry, 1,000,000 lovelace.
And as asset class, I use this
tokens I defined up here that I now
have in the initial distribution.
Then I start the oracle with
these parameters for wallet one.
I wait for one slot and now
I use this get oracle helper
function that's defined down here.
The idea is because in order to
run the swap contract, they are
parameterized over the oracle value.
And so I must somewhat discover that.
And remember this run oracle writes
down, as soon as the oracle is
created it, it tells the oracle.
So I must somehow get that state and that's
the purpose of this get oracle function.
So I use the observable state function
that we saw before with the handle.
So that takes the observable
state of the run oracle contract,
which should contain the oracle.
If it doesn't, the oracle might not be
there yet, one might not have started yet.
So I just wait one slot and try again.
But if it's there, I now have this
value and I just log it for for
debugging purposes and I return it.
So that means I start the oracle.
I get it, get the value.
And now once I have the value, I can use it.
So now on wallet two, I start this check
oracle function that we saw here, whose job
adjusted to every slot printer oracle value.
Then I initialized the oracle to 1.5
dollar per ADA, wait for three slots.
And now I start I just call the own
funds function on the wallets one, three,
four, five to check the initial balances.
And now I start this swap contract
on H three H four and H five.
Right, and now I just try some scenarios.
So wallet three offers 10 ADA for
swap, wallet four offers 20 ADA
for swapping, I wait three slots
and now wallet five uses a swap.
So it will pick one of the two it's
not obvious which one, which ever
it finds first and pays USD for it.
According to the current value of the oracle,
which we sit here at this point it's 1.5.
Anyway another three slots.
Now, wallet one updates, the oracle
value to 1.7 and H five tries again.
So now it will grab the remaining swap
of these two, but now pay a different
price, pay 1.7 dollars instead of 1.5.
Wait again, now I set it to 1.8
the oracle value to allow wallet
one to extract all the fees.
So by now fees should have been paid twice
because the oracle was used twice here.
So each one should be able to collect
two ADA fees, wait another three slots.
And now I retrieve our remaining swaps,
but that shouldn't do anything because
I only had those two to begin with.
And they were both used by H five.
So this I could have left out, wait
another three slots and that's it.
And in the repl we can run it and
hopefully be some desired result.
Okay.
So let's see lots of output.
So here the oracle was started.
So this is when the NFTs minted.
And we have now the oracle value,
the parameter we can use for...
everything else.
Here this get oracle is, is started,
which once every slot logs the oracle
value just for our information.
So the first one, it find is indeed this 1.5.
And now I start the the, I get the funds.
So I see the initial funds of all
the wallets to three, four, and
five, still have the initial ones.
One has a bit less because it
started the oracle and needed to
pay transaction fees for that.
So oracle value is 1.5.
Now the offers are made,
the two swap offers of 1...
10 ADA and 20 ADA, wait a bit.
So the funds are still the same,
oracle value hasn't changed.
And now the first use happens.
So the wallet five tries to use,
and has enough money to do the swap.
And at some point it will happen.
So not exactly clear yet
already has happened.
And we wait a bit now the oracle gets
updated to 1.7 and here is the second
use where it's five tries again to swap.
And some fund logging and basically
nothing interesting happened anymore.
And if you look at the final balances, we
see that wallet two still has everything
from the beginning, because our wallet
two does is this oracle checking,
which doesn't cost any transaction fees
because it's purely an off-chain meta.
Wallet one paid some transaction
fees, but ends up with roughly two ADA
more than it started with, it started
with 100 and now it almost has 102.
And that it's because it collected
the two ADA fee for the oracle use.
Wallet three and wallet
four, they both made offers.
So wallet three offer 10 ADA,
wallet four offer 20 ADA.
And we see, so the first swap that
happened was wallet two where the exchange
rate was one fifty and because it...
of a 20, it got 30 dollars in return.
So it ends up with 130 dollars.
Then wallet three had an exchange rate
of one seventy but only offered 10 ADA.
So it got 17 dollars in return and wallet
five finally had to pay these prices.
So the 17 plus 30, so 47 but got the offer...
at, ADA return, so, so it
paid, this is the 47 less.
So it started with 100 now 53 dollars left.
But for that, it got the...
basically would have gotten 30 ADA, 10 plus
20, but had to pay one ADA each oracle fees.
So that's why it's only 28 and
it's a bit less than 28 because
of a normal transaction fees.
So it's exactly what we expect.
And we see here apart from the wallet.
So the oracle is still happily going.
So this here is the oracle NFT.
In, in this log we don't see the datum value.
So we just see that the
oracle is still there.
Apart from the idea how to actually
do an oracle in Plutus, nothing
we have seen until now is new.
I mean, there may have been some Plutus
library functions we haven't seen before or
some Haskell functions, but in principle,
we are all familiar with the way validators
are written for on-chain code and contracts
are written for off-chain code and how we
can test it with the emulator trace monad.
So now in the second part of this lecture, we
talking about something new namely the Plutus
application backend, which allows you to
take all that, what we have done until now,
and turn it into an actual application, a
executable that actually runs the contracts.
If there was a Testnet or if Plutus was
available on the main net already, we could
then actually deploy this on those testsnets,
but for now we have to be satisfied with
using a mock chain, a simulated blockchain.
But the process of turning this into a
Dapp is virtually the same as it will
be when a proper Testnet is available.
So we need one more tiny
module that I called PAB.
And it's just basically
just one type definition.
And the idea is it reifies the
contract instances we want to run.
So we have various contracts and now
we define the data type where each
value of the data type corresponds to
a contract we eventually want to run.
This init is nothing we have written
until now, but this basically
corresponds to what I did in the emulator
trace monad to give initial funds.
So we will just use that to set up
an environment where there is a USD
token available and where the wallets
have an initial supply of those.
Then this constructor, the oracle
constructor corresponds to the run oracle
contract that will actually start and
then run the oracle and provide this
update endpoint, the currency symbol
parameter I will use to communicate the
currency symbol we use for our USD token.
And finally, the swap parameterized
by oracle will be used to run the swap
contract, which if you recall offers various
endpoints like offer retrieve use and funds.
So this is just this definition that
I have to put it in a separate module
because I will use it both from the
PAB and also later from the front-end.
But now let's switch to the, or let
first look at the cabal file actually.
Sorry, because everything we have
seen so far is in this library.
So, all the modules we have now discussed.
Now I have various executables.
So first, now will talk about this
oracle PAB, which would basically start
a simulated wallet and initialize all
the contracts and start a set up a web
server that allows the outside world
to interact with these contracts.
And then I have two more executables, one
that would be run by the oracle provider.
So that will interact with the run oracle
contract and actually fetch exchange rates
from the internet and feed them into the
system and then a swap client executable,
which would be run by the clients that
want to make use of the swap contract.
So let's look at all of these
interns starting with this
one, that's an app oracle PAB.
And before we look at this
code, let's first look at...
this stuff here, this is boiler plate.
So I basically just copy pasted that from...
until here.
So these handlers thing, this is boiler
plate to somehow hook up the data type
I just defined, these reified contract
instances with actual contracts.
So...
this basically just assigns for each
of these three, reified instances we
defined in it, oracle and swap to hook
that up with the correspondent schemas
and contracts that you defined earlier.
So init won't have any schema so it just
is blockchain actions, and oracle uses the
oracle schema and swap uses the swap schema.
No surprise there.
And init will run the init contract, which
I defined down here, oracle will run the...
run oracle contract that we saw earlier.
oracle params I think I define up here.
So that just takes the currency symbol of
USD and then defines example oracle params.
So fee one ADA currency symbol the provided
argument and token is just hard coded USDT.
And finally, the swap will just given
an oracle value., will run our swap
contract with this value as parameter.
This is poor boiler plate that
I just copied, copy pasted.
And this is now this init contract which is
supposed to, to generate the initial funds.
So that's not important.
I just need that for, for the demo.
And it's very, I mean, it's,
it's very straightforward.
So I again make use of this forge
contract from the Plutus use cases.
And as before I used the forge contract,
but before we just minted one token, this
So I lookup my own public key.
NFT, and now I mint more, so basically
this amount is just, I think, a hundred
million So I want to give each wallet 100
dollars So I count how many wallets there
are and just multiply it and the wallets
I hard-coded here, so I just use five
wallets for this, it's completely arbitrary.
So I use this forge contract
lookup the currency symbol...
provide the value how much
each wallet should get.
And then I just create transactions that
sense each of the wallets, the amount
except myself, because I already have it.
So one wallet will mint all the USDs and then
distribute them evenly to the other wallets.
And in the end, I tell this currency
symbol that was the result of forging.
Right.
And now we can look at the actual PAB code.
And...
so this is in IO, it's a proper main program.
So that will be a proper executable
and it makes use of yet another monad
that we haven't seen before and that's
specific to the PAB, but it's very, it's
called the simulator monad, but it's
very similar to the emulator trace monad.
So in principle, it has exactly the
same, more or less the same capabilities.
So you can start contracts on wallets and
you can like inspect the log, the state
and, and so on, and you can call endpoints.
So it's a bit unfortunate that there
are actually two different monads
for this because they are so similar.
And I know from the Plutus team
that they plan to align these
and maybe turn them into one.
So probably you shouldn't pay too
much attention or spend too much
effort on learning the intricacies
of this model because that will
probably change soon and will be
aligned with the emulator trace monad.
And Similar to how we have this run emulator
trace IO, there's something run simulation
with, so we need these handlers, this boiler
plate to find downstairs further down.
And then this is a script
in this simulator monad now.
One significant difference to the
emulator trace monad though is the
emulator trace monad was pure code, no
revert side effects, no IO involved.
So we couldn't do IO in the
run emulator trace monad.
In particular there was this pure
interpreter run emulator trace
without IO, just run emulator trace.
That's a pure Haskell
function, no side effects.
So in this emulator trace
expressions, you can't do any IO.
Simulator is different.
You can do IO and the way it
works, it's a so-called monad IO.
And monad IO is one method lift
IO, and that takes an IO action and
lifts it into the monad in question.
So if you have some arbitrary IO
action that you can do in Haskell,
then by applying lift IO to it, you
can move it into the simulator monad.
So inside this two block, we can do arbitrary
IO as well, plus the specific things that
the simulation monad allows us to do.
Right, but apart from that, I
mean, if you squint, it looks
very similar to emulator trace.
So first thing I do is I just log.
So is that we also have a log capabilities.
So there's a function called log string.
And I just say, okay, I start
the server, is PAB server.
Then this starts over the
back actually starts it.
And the return value is an action that
I can later use to shut down the server
again, right now I use something called
activate contract and that's very similar
to, I think it was called activate contract
instance in the emulator trace monad.
So that's basically the same thing,
but now in the simulator monad.
So it gets a wallet where I want
to start that instance, and then a
value of this reified contract type.
So remember this init constructor
we associated down here, somewhere
here with this init contract
that was then defined here.
So what this will do, it will on wallet
one, launch this contract, and remember
the contract just means this USD token
and distributes it to the other wallets.
Now we need the currency symbol.
So this is now an example of
how we get information back
out of a contract using this...
a monad right-hand detail.
And we'll see that in a second.
Right.
And I do that here with his helper function
because I need to do that couple of times.
So I've wrote a helper function,
wait for last that I defined here.
So given such a constants
contact instance ID.
I use a function that's provided by the
simulator, that's called wait for state.
That's similar to the observable state
function we got in the, in the emulator
trace monad, so what wait for state
does is, it takes the contract instance
and it takes a predicate that gets a
json expression and returns a maybe A.
The idea is, so it will read
the state of the contract.
Remember we write the state
from the contract using tell.
So this reads this, but it's serialized
to it, it gets a json value, realized
as json and then it applies that
json value to the provided predicate.
And this provides returns, as I said a
maybe A, so if the result of applying
our custom predicate to this, json
value is nothing this will simply wait
more until the state changes again.
But if it's just X it will return the X.
So this will block until we get a just here.
And, So this helper function, it's just
a special case where the state is in
this last monoid that I explained before.
So and success is that's comes from
the data dot aeson library for json
handling in Haskell, so if you...
sorry, I use this from json to parse to json.
So if that succeeds, I should get...
last ex...
last A if A is the type, but of
course the json parsing can also fail.
And this is so-called result type
that's defined in data dot aeson.
So if it succeeds, it says succeeds and
then the value it's successfully parsed.
So in the good case, it succeeds
the json passing succeeds, and we
get last of just of state value.
And they are two ways it could
fail either the parsing could,
could fail, or even if the parsing
succeeds, we could get a last nothing.
In which case we also consider
that as failure and wait some more.
So this waits until the state
of the contract has told a just
value and then returns that value.
Right?
So to go back to our simulator
script, So we use this wait for last
on the handle for the init contract.
And if you remember the init contract
in the last line, when we are done.
We wrote the currency symbol of
the USD token that we minted.
So this means that this line will block
until this init contract has done its job
has minted the USD and has distributed
the USD tokens to the other wallets.
And then it will return the currency
symbol, then there's another
function called wait until finished.
So we just wait until this
init contract has finished.
Now, next step is we start
the oracle on wallet one.
So it's again makes use of this
data type I explained before.
So given the currency symbol, we basically
do run oracle where the O asset of
the oracle params field now uses the
CS that we got from the first step.
So after this, the oracle should not run.
So we log a message and here
I'm using No, no, sorry.
We don't log a message.
The point is I need these handles
in order to, from the outside world
later, interact with these contracts.
I need to get my hands on
these these, these handles.
So this cid contract identify oracle,
I need that, because if I want to
use the web interface later to talk
to the contract, I need this cid.
So what I do here is I write that
into a file that I call oracle cid.
So I just basically extract the...
uuid that, that basically is this cid
and write that into oracle cid file,
that's just, I mean, this is of course
quick and dirty in production code.
You would probably use a safer mechanism,
but this is just for demonstration.
So we start the oracle, we get the handle to
the contract and we write that into a file.
And now I use my wait for last again,
to actually get the oracle value.
Remember in the run oracle contract,
once we have the oracle, once we have
minted the NFT, we tell this oracle
value and I need that because the swap
contract is parameterized by this value.
So I use this wait for last again.
So this will block until the NFTs minted,
and I know what the oracle value is.
And then I loop over all other wallets.
So I exclude wallet one that runs to oracle.
And activate the swap
contract for that wallet.
And I do a similar trick to here
because I need those handles as well.
So here I use the file oracle cid.
And here I use files W wallet number dot
cid to write the contract instance id cid.
And that's it.
So basically I have a file.
I mean, produced initial funds
started the oracle, started the
swap contracts swap, swap contracts.
Now I just basically block
until the user presses enter
and then I shut down the server.
And actually it's not necessary to do
all of this because you can also start
instances from outside via the web interface.
I just found it easier to do that, basically
in a scripted way at least for this demo,
but in principle, you don't need any of this,
you just have to start the simulator, and
then you could immediately basically wait
until you shut down and you can do all the
control, you can trigger starting contract
instances and stopping them from the outside.
And in case you are curious what API is
provided by the PAB, what web API, you
can check that in the Plutus PAB module in
sorry, in the Plutus PAB package, in the
module Plutus dot PAB dot web server dot API.
And there are several
ones, but the relevant one.
Is this one, at least the one I'm using now,
this what's called new API and there's also
a web socket API, but I didn't play with it.
So I haven't tried that.
So I only worked with this one here.
And I mean, this is...
makes use of the very popular Haskell library
servant to write type-safe web applications.
But I think it should be readable more
or less even if you don't know servant.
So that's just mean, so the path
is API slash news slash contract,
and then you have various options.
So this symbol here means alternative.
So you have activate, you have
instance, instances definitions.
So for example, here, the first endpoint
a web endpoint would be API slash
new slash contract slash activate.
It's a post request.
And in its request body, it takes
in json format contract activation
arguments, whatever that is.
And it will return a contract instance ID.
So that's what I said you, instead of
doing it in the simulation monad, you could
also have done it via the web interface
to actually start a contract instance.
But I didn't try that out, then
for, if you're using instead API
new contract instance, and then the
instance ID, that's what I need.
That's what I wrote in these files.
Then you'll have various options.
For example, status gives you
the status of the contract.
endpoint allows you to call endpoints,
so endpoint, endpoint name, post, request
weather parameters for the endpoint are
provided as json and the request body.
And you can also stop a contract instance.
And then there are other ways, here for
example, for given a specific wallet,
you can check all the contract instances
that are running on this wallet or you
can get all the instances overall that
are running in the system and some
definitions, but I also haven't tried that.
So all I'm using in this
demo is status an endpoint.
So endpoint to, to call an endpoint
and status, to get feedback from the
contract to read the, of what I wrote
with tell to read that out again.
So let's actually try it.
This is now an executable and I can just
run it, so I can use cabal run and the name
of the executable, which was oracle PAB.
And we get log output similar to what
we get when we do the emulator trace.
But this is now a running executable
in IO that set up a live server.
So if we scroll up, so this is probably
to mint this USD token, and then we later
mint this oracle NFT and so on, and we
see that here, for example, an instance.
So this is the oracle, so on
activated instance on W1, wallet one.
And this is this contract instance
idea is talking about that we need
as parameters to our HTTP endpoints.
If we want to interact with this specific
instance, and then further down here,
these four are the other wallets W
two, three, four, and five that now
activate that the swap instances.
Let me stop that quickly.
If we just look in the directory, we see
these files that the script now wrote out.
So for example, if you checked the W
five cid, that should be the same number
that we see here in the log, and it is.
So I just, as I said, wrote that in the file
so that's easy for me to, to then use that
to interact with these instances and I could
in principle, and I would demonstrate that,
but the lecture is very very long already.
So I think I won't do that, but I could
just use any tool now, for example, curl
or wget or even the browser for the get
requests to just check at the correct port.
I think that's 8080 that should
say source here somewhere.
Yes, so starting PAB backend server on
port 8080, so I can just go to 8080 and
then use any tool I like to interact with
these HTTP endpoints, but instead I like
wrote little demo programs that do that.
And of course, because it's just a
rest API, HTTP endpoints, you can use
whatever programming language you like.
I of course use Haskell because Haskell is
my favorite language, but you could also
use whatever you want, Python or Java or
JavaScript, or as I said, curl and bash.
So let's just look at first oracle client.
And I don't want to go into detail
here because I mean, the point is not
to show you how to write a front-end.
Just give you the general idea.
So actually I'm using a Haskell
library called REQ or req,
request to do these requests.
So, what I do in the main program
is, I read this file to get the
uuid that has the correct instance,
just log that and then go to go.
And this loops forever and what it
does it, looks up the current exchange
rate, ADA, USD on coin market cap,
checks whether that has changed.
So this parameter here is the old value
that starts with nothing in the beginning,
I don't have any, so then it checks the
new exchanged rate and if this exchange
rate has changed, it calls update oracle.
We'll get to that in a second, so that
calls the update oracle endpoint on
our contract that we defined before.
Then it waits for five seconds and loops.
This is of course arbitrary, I
don't know whether coin market cap
does some sort of rate throttling.
So I didn't want to risk being
bent for having too many requests.
So I just did it five seconds, in
reality seeing as blocks on Cardano
only appear every 30 seconds on average,
probably even five seconds is too
much and should rather be 30 seconds.
But anyway, so this oracle, update oracle is
now the interesting one where I demonstrate
how to interact with the running contract.
So this stuff here is just
comes from this req package.
So that's not important, but
basically the essence of what I'm
doing is I prepare a post request.
So I go to my local server.
With this endpoint we just saw.
In the API model, so API new
contract instance, then the
next parameter is this uuid.
So I just converted to text
then endpoint, the name of the
endpoint was, which was update.
And now I must provide the request
body in json format of the value I
want to update to that is this X.
And this just says that I expect a json
format response, and this gives the port.
And then if that goes well, sort
of the status code to 100, I
just log a message accordingly.
And that's it.
And as I said the details don't matter.
You can do that in the programming
language of your choice.
It's just a plain old when
they learn HTTP endpoint.
And this here is it's very, my very
quick and dirty way to get the actual ADA
USD exchange rate from coin market cap.
I, of course they also provide a proper
API, but I just basically get the whole
website for currencies Cardano and then use
a regular expression, which of course is very
fragile and would never work as production
code just to, to grab the exchange rate.
And basically that's it.
And then I just multiply it one by
1,000,000 and rounded to get this integer
value you want to use and log a message.
So we can try that out.
Let me just run a start the PAB again.
Wait until the oracle start it.
The funds are distributed.
Okay.
So now everything should be running.
And let me just go to another terminal
window and I run the second executable
that I just showed you, the oracle client.
Okay.
Now it's a, when to corn market, Kevin,
it seems right now the exchange rate
is 1 dollar 75 and now I call update
oracle with this 1,750,000 value.
If you switch back to where the PAB runs, we
see that we also get log messages for this.
So this update transaction that
updates the oracle UTxO has actually
been received and processed.
And we also get the correct log message
that we saw earlier in the core module that
the initial oracle value was set to 1.75.
Now, of course I have no
control over the exchange rate.
So I don't know whether this will
change from 1.75 anytime soon.
Maybe we wait for that, we look
at the swap client, which is very
similar so that can actually, sorry.
So that uses the same technique,
same req library to handle HTTP.
And the idea is I just want to offer
a very simple console interface.
So I didn't bother with
graphics or a nice web UI.
It's just console based.
So the idea is I just want to
offer these four possibilities.
You can make an offer, you can
retrieve, you can use, or you can
check your funds and it loops forever.
So I don't have to go into that in detail.
Same thing here.
I...
well, one difference is I actually provide
the command line parameter because I want
to run this clients for different wallets.
So I provide the wallet number
as a command line parameter.
Then I read the correct uuid from the file
and log something and then loop forever.
And this loop, all it does is it
just parses this command that I
enter by a text from the console and
then calls the appropriate endpoint.
And this endpoint calling is defined here.
And it's basically always the same,
always the same thing, for example,
for get funds, we want information
out of, out of the web interface.
So we must use this status status endpoint.
So we...
no, sorry.
We call first, we call
the the funds endpoint.
And then remember in the funds endpoint
in the swap contract, what it did, it
checks its own funds and then tells them.
So here we checked them.
And now we do a second request
where we use the status endpoint
to get the status of that instance.
And then we basically can extract
the observable state from that.
So we just have to, so we get the
response body then have to play cic
current state and then observable
state, and then parse it from json.
And if all goes well, then finally we
get our value that the contract totaled.
So that's how you get information back out
of a contract and offer, the others are
simpler because we don't need information
out, so we only have to do one request,
we call the appropriate endpoint that we
defined earlier in the contract monad.
So this is for offer, this is
for retrieve and this is for use.
And once again, the details here don't
matter, you just need the programming
language of your choice that allows you
to do post requests and get requests
and handle the request bodies and so on.
So let's see whether the
exchange rate has changed.
No, it's still 1.75.
So we are still at our initial value.
But nevertheless, let's
start this client as well.
So cabal run swap client, and you pass
command line, if you use cabal run and
command line parameters, you have to
do double dash and then the parameters.
So this will execute this executable
I just showed you for wallet two.
So let's do that.
And let's also do it for wallet three.
Okay.
And now I have this, this
primitive console interface.
So now I can issue these command and actually
I forgot, I just see that I missed the funds
here, so I not only have offer retrieve and
use I also have funds so I could change that.
Of course.
Okay.
Let's try that again.
If we get the proper help message,
it's either the no exchange rate.
Ah, now it just changed.
So now it changed from 1.75 to 1.76 and we
call the update endpoint on our contract.
And if we switched back to the
PAB, now we see a log message here
that updated oracle value to 1.76.
So now the UTxO on the blockchain changed
from having 1,750,000 to 1,760,000.
Okay.
Now we should be able to try it.
So this is now wallet two, let's
start with the funds command.
Okay.
And I still have on my initial funds.
So hundred USD one hundred ADA.
I can do that for the other wallet as well.
Great.
But anyway, so same thing
here, 100 USD 100 ADA.
Now let's switch back to wallet
two and let's offer a swap.
So offer let's say 10 ADA.
So ten, one, two, three, one, two, three.
Now if I call funds again,
there's a difference.
So I still have all my USD
but now I have 10 ADA less.
And the bid for the transaction fee,
if he switched back to the PAB, we
should see that something happened here.
So a couple of own fund endpoints
were called and we get these log
messages that the offer was made.
Let's just check what the
current exchange rate is.
Okay.
It's still 1.76.
So if I now go to the other wallet
to wallet three and call use.
I should be able to exchange
those 10 ADA for 17 dollars 60.
Let's see.
Okay.
Now let's check the funds here.
That hasn't updated yet,
sorry, it takes a while.
Okay, now it has updated.
So now I have more ADA.
I got the, well, the swap was 10 ADA,
so I got the 10 but in order to use the
oracle, I had to pay one ADA oracle fee.
So that's why I only have nine and
I have a little bit less because I
had to pay transaction fees as well.
And in exchange, I had to pay 17 dollars 60.
Now, if we switch to the original wallet
that did the swap and do funds, then
hopefully that will have changed as well.
Right.
So that now got the 17.60 dollars.
So the swap is compete and the correct
value of the exchange rate, the actual
live right now exchange rate USD to
ADA was used, which was injected into
the mock blockchain via my oracle.
So now we have seen end to end example
of a Plutus Dapp from front-end.
So it talks to the outside world goes on the
internet, gets information interacts with
Plutus smart contracts, which then submit
certain transactions to the blockchain.
And then on the blockchain, the validation
logic clicks in and makes sure that
everything follows the business rules.
So this is a complete walk through
from on-chain code over off-chain
code over PAB code to front-end.
And as I said, it's very similar to
what the real system will look like.
At least in the beginning, until we have
like a browser based way to, to interact
with Plutus, the only difference of
course is because now it's a mockchain.
I only have one instance of the
PAB running and all my simulated
wallets use the same server, which of
course in real life would be silly.
So obviously different wallets will
have different instances of PAB running.
But now it has to be one instance because
this, I mean, otherwise, because there's
no real blockchain, so there's this one PAB
instance holds the simulated blockchain.
So this is slightly different, but if you
squint a bit and, and forget about that
it's almost exactly end to end how the
real system will work in the beginning.
This was a very long lecture.
So congratulations to all
that made it to this point.
And I'm sorry about that, but I really
want to honor your request to talk about
oracles and to provide an overview of how
an end to end Plutus application works.
And unfortunately, that required
me to talk about lots of things.
So I think because the lecture was long,
I don't want to post specific homework.
I think what you should do is
try to get this demo running.
So run all these executables and see
whether it works for you and play
a bit with the UI and issue various
commands from various wallets.
And then of course, if you are ambitious,
you can improve this in various directions.
So you could, for example, write
different front-ends either in different
programming languages or also in Haskell
but offering different features like a
nicer graphical UI or whatever, or you
could also make the oracle more secure.
I mentioned before.
One way to not have to rely on one trusted
party would be to have several oracles.
You could imagine having three wallets
running oracles and have using different
front-ends, so maybe one wallet uses
data from coin market cap and the other
two use data from different sources.
And then in the swap contract,
instead of requiring just the
one UTxO, the oracle UTxO in...
as input to a swap transaction, you could
require all three oracles to be present
and then decide on some way to get the
value out of those three, for example,
throwing away the min and the max and
just keeping the one in the middle.
That of course would be a lot of work, but it
also would make this a much more realistic.
So there are various ways you could
improve that, or you could support more
than just one token, more than just USD.
So I just recommend playing a
bit with it and modifying it.
If you, if you feel like it.